<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>ali</PNAME>
<INAME>herb</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
ali	
herb	Why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
ali	Why is it warmer in the winter, why is it
herb	Warmer in the summer
ali	Oh
herb	 And colder in the winter
ali	 Well it has to do with the angle of the Earth because um- I remember I went home that day when we had the interviews and was like researching  and um, I found that it was the angle of the sun, so, and the distance I guess
herb	 Okay
ali	 It relates back to what I said about the experiment that we did
herb	 So let's say that, you know , here's North America or South America and here's Chicago right there
ali	 Mmm hmm
herb	 Um, now, in the summer and in the winter, are you saying that the light is different somehow?
ali	 Oh, no, well, not the light itself
herb	 Right, but I mean the light that hits the Earth
ali	 Yeah
herb	 The light that hits the Earth is different?
ali	 Yeah
herb	 The light that hits Chicago is different?
ali	 Yeah because of the angle of the Earth
herb	 Okay.  So what does it look like in the summer as opposed to in the winter, like in terms of the angle
ali	 Mmm, well, it would be- like, I don't know, I was reading about the southern hemisphere and the nor- like, uh, the, hold on, let me think
herb	 The equator?
ali	 Yeah
herb	 What happens?
ali	 Like um, when one part of the Earth was like, in a picture, was like lighted up and the other one was dark, because it wasn't facing the um, the sun, like this part would be dark and this would be light.  So this would have light, and this wouldn't, so I don't know, that would mean that it's winter, because, so.  And if the Earth like rotated , well, the Earth does rotate .  Okay, the Earth rotates and then this part came here, then it would be dark, uh, there would be more light then this than this part came here would be darker
herb	 Bruce, can you check the mic?  Is mine okay?  Okay.  So it's this light dark thing that happens
ali	 Yeah
herb	 Okay, now, does that- what about, what about day and night, though
ali	 Day and night, um, well, the Earth rotates- I don't know.  Um, day and night
herb	 I mean, does this have something to do with day and night as well
ali	 Yeah, I think it does.  Wait, hold on, yeah, I think it does, 'cause, I'm not sure, but
herb	 Okay.  Um
ali	 I remember in class we were talking about that and I'm trying to remember.  Gee, now I know that I don't listen that much 
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
