<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>amanda</PNAME>
<INAME>betsy</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
betsy	I asked you back in the first interview about why's it's warmer generally in . . . well why it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
amanda	Oh, because like I said, the Earth's on a tilt.
betsy	Okay, and here , want to draw on the other side?
A 	Okay, so since the-  okay, here's the sun.  And since the Earth is on a tilt, like if this side is tilted towards this, and if this is like North America or whatever, and then, so this, and then, so this is the northern hemisphere, then the northern hemisphere would be having summer and the southern hemisphere would be having winter 'cause the northern hemisphere is closer to the sun and also it's like, it has- it's more direct sunligh- it gets more direct sunlight than the southern hemisphere does, 'cause the north pole, that's not as much of an angle as this.  And so, but then, in- since it rotates around, then pretty soon, it'll get so it's like this and the southern hemisphere will be having summer, so here's South America and here's North America.  So they're having summer and we're having winter 'cause we're less, we're farther away from the sun and the angles are more , so it's 
betsy	Okay, okay.  That makes sense.  So can you draw me a picture that shows both the summer and the winter, maybe, so how the Earth moves in relation to the sun.  And if you need more paper . . .
amanda	 Okay .  So this is the northern hemisphere.  And then, when it goes around, it's like that and then, like, when that happens, it gets like this and then it goes around again and it gets like that again .
betsy	 Mmm hmm, that makes sense.  So where's summer in which hemisphere, on which side of the . . .?
amanda	 Well when the northern hemisphere's like- this is summer in the northern hemisphere and then this is summer in the northern hemisphere. 
betsy	 Okay.
amanda	 'Cause the southern hemisphere is tilted towards it and the northern hemisphere is tilted towards it.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
