<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>edgar</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>cf</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	 Um, so why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
edgar	 Um, it's when it's , um, rotation- can I draw it on here?
bruce	Yeah, why don't I give you a new piece of paper
edgar	  Um, here's the sun here, and here's the Earth
bruce	 Mmm hmm
edgar	 And here's the place where it revolves around the sun
bruce	 Mmm hmm
edgar	 And I think like once, in the summer, it's closer to the sun and it get more heat in an area and when it turn , um, it tilt on its axis and it revolves too
bruce	 Mmm hmm
edgar	While it's turning, it goes around the sun  and when it finally reach closer to the sun, I think it should be summer
bruce	 Mmm hmm
edgar	And like once it turn like this, like here would be the winter
bruce	 And why is it winter there?
edgar	 Uh, it's further from the sun, wouldn't get much heat from it and like um, wouldn't get much heat from the sun when it's far off and like not much heat
bruce	Okay, so it's winter here  because it's further away.  And what does the turning around have to do with the seasons?
edgar	Causes night and day
bruce	 Oh, okay
edgar	 So
bruce	Okay.  So one question I have is, have you heard that when it's summer here, it's winter in other places like Australia, have you ever heard that before?
edgar	 Yeah
bruce	So you have heard that?
edgar	Oh no, no I didn't
bruce	Oh.  So if I was right that it's summer, when it's summer  here and winter in Australia, could your picture explain that?
edgar	No
B 	And why is that?
edgar	Because, um, say the United States is over here
bruce	 Uh huh
edgar	And Australia is over here, any time it turns  and it takes a year to go around the sun and I think it would be impossible for it to have winter.  It's just the summer's over here and winter's over here, it's impossible to Australia to have winter, 'cause it's turning every night and day so I think it's impossible
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
