<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>jacob</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Um, oh, okay, this is sort of a related question, I'm not sure if you talked about this or not, but I'm sort of wondering why it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter
jacob	Oh, I remember that question
bruce	You remember us asking that question?
jacob	 Yeah
bruce	 Okay, so what's the answer?
jacob	Well, oh how did I explain it last time
bruce	You can try to figure it out again, too
jacob	 I know.  Well, in the winter, it pretty much, I don't remember if it has to do with . . . I believe it has to do with like um, the, can I get the paper again?
bruce	 This one?  Can I give you a different piece?
jacob	 Yeah, whatever
bruce	 Okay, here you go.  I'm just gonna check how my camera is [something]
jacob	 Okay.   Here's the sun, and then like this and then, pretty good.  That's, whatever.  Okay
bruce	 Okay, so what you got?
jacob	 I believe that um, if, it has to do with like how the sun rotates around  the, um, the, I mean the Earth rotates around the sun
bruce	 Mmm  hmm
jacob	 And um, when the su- when the Earth goes, when, uh, let's see.  Sometimes the Earth is farther away from the sun um, than other times and I think that's what creates like um, it's kind of like how we said about the distance, when the Earth is over here on this part, then the sun's rays have to go a farther than they do here, and causing cooler temperaures
bruce	 I see
jacob	 It's kind of what I was trying to say
bruce	 Okay, that makes sense.  Um, one thing, though, have you heard that when it's summer here, it's winter on some other parts of the Earth, like when it's summer here, it's winter in Australia, have you ever heard that?
jacob	 Did kind of hear it.  Actually, I think I heard that, yeah
bruce	 So if that/
jacob	So, wait a minute, let's see.  I think then it would have to do more on how the Earth is turned around, like when the Earth, let's say here's Europe and here is us.  Then when the sun's rays go directly right towards Europe, it's gonna be hotter in Europe and the sun's rays would still come through, it would still warm this area around here
bruce	I see
jacob	But it, they wouldn't be as strong, they wouldn't heat as well
bruce	So this is summer in Europe and winter somewhere else?
jacob	Yeah
bruce	And when, let's say it was winter in Europe, what would that look like?
jacob	 It w- let's say this is Europe and this is America, or kind of is.  Then it would be right here and then, Europe, and then the rays going through, everything like that
bruce	 I see
jacob	 Kind of the same thing
bruce	How does that relate to day and night?
jacob	 Uh, day is like when the sun's light is, I don't know how to explain this.  Day is when the sun h- lights the, oh, it's hard to explain 
bruce	 Okay, just do your best
jacob	 Well it's day in one part of the- it's also kind of the same thing actually.  When it's day in, um, let's say Europe, it's night in America because um, the sun's light is heating, no, is um, shining on Europe and America.  That wouldn't really explain the seasons because it goes around 24 hours so there has to be something else.  Hmm
bruce	Okay, I don't think I- so, there's something tricky there
jacob	Yeah
bruce	Um, so that, you can ask some, okay this, you want to think about it for a second?
jacob	Actually, I think it still has to do with the, when it goes around the sun 
bruce	You think- yeah
jacob	I think when it goes around the sun and it's over here, um, it, it, the sun heats m- let's see . . .it's hard to explain how.  Doesn't seem accurate because when the sun, I would think that when the sun turns around, I mean when the Earth turns around, then it would be warmer in one part
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
