<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>kurt</PNAME>
<INAME>herb</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
herb	 Um, why do you think it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
kurt	 Warmer in the summer, colder in the winter?
herb	 Mmm hmm
kurt	 Because of, uh, the heat rays, like, well it depends on where you are in the country, like
herb	 Let's say Chicago
kurt	 Chicago, why is it like
herb	 Warmer in the summer and colder in the winter
kurt	 'Cause well I think more light rays are hitting the Earth, more um, like right now, how all of a sudden turn warm again  in Chicago, um, I think that's 'cause uh, the . . .the way the Earth's revolving around the sun, maybe, the sun's giving off more light rays towards Chicago
herb	 Uh huh.  Um, I guess I'm not following you exactly.  How would that work exactly?
kurt	 Um . . .should I draw a picture?
herb	 Yeah, sure, draw a picture
kurt	 Um like the sun  and the Earth's here, like Chicago's like right there
herb	 Okay
kurt	 And um, I guess it just, when it hits the center, like the center, I think it bounces off into Chicago more, up here more
herb	 Okay, if it's here  it bounces off onto Chicago more?
kurt	 Mmm hmm.  And around different states and everything
herb	 And how is that different in the summer than it is in the winter?  Is the sun, is the sun different in the summer?
kurt	 Um, no, I think it's still the same like heat and everything, I just don't think it's giving off that many light rays, er
herb	 So the sun's giving off fewer light rays in the wintertime?
kurt	 Mmm hmm
herb	 Um, so the sun kind of knows when it's winter on the Earth?
kurt	 No, it just, I think it's uh
herb	 The sun somehow controls when it's winter on the Earth?
kurt	 Kind of
herb	 So like when the sun decides, when the sun gives off less light rays then it just becomes winter
kurt	 Um, well really, if like the Earth is uh, and it revolves around the sun, like, it could, when it hits like differen- I don't think all, the sun all around gives off equal amount of light rays
herb	 It doesn't or does?
kurt	 It doesn't, I think when you're like, when the Earth is traveling around  the sun, at different parts of the sun that it's traveling around, doesn't give off as much
herb	 Oh, okay
kurt	 And it could be colder then.  And 'cause the Earth spinning at uh, every 24 hours, like it turns , um, it could be 'cause we're not like facing the sun as much
herb	 Uh huh.  So does the Earth turn differently in the wintertime?
kurt	 Um, not really, it just, I think it's just spinning the same but it's just the different parts of the sun isn't giving off that- as much light rays in, so it travels around the sun
herb	  So you have sort of the situation where you have the sun here and the Earth's going around, right?
kurt	 Mmm hmm
herb	 And you've got some parts that are brighter than others?
kurt	 Mmm hmm
herb	 Is that how you're seeing it?  And when it's going through here it's summer, go through here it's winter?  Okay.  Um, have you heard that like um, when it's summer up here it's winter down in South America?
kurt	 Mmm hmm
herb	 Um, so how does that work?
kurt	 Um . . . I don't think two- um, uh, sun's light rays, they're like, it's still uh, sunny like there but um, it's not giving off as much heat as it should be, down there than up here
herb	 Okay.  So that's why/
kurt	 I think 'cause the refl- , uh, like, it'll, see it's sunny there and sunny like in Chicago, it's 'cause the light rays are bouncing off and hitting there , from, they're like kind of bouncing off like everywhere I think.  They're not like, the whole Earth isn't light at once  , like, so here's this side and this side, on this, like, other countries are on this side and America and you say Alaska?
herb	 Yeah
kurt	 Are on this side, um, and I think it's um because uh, when the sun's up here  hitting down onto the Earth, they're bouncin- the light rays bounce up and hit there but they're like not as um, heated up as it was when it just hit the sun, I mean just hit the Earth
herb	 What about the other way around, so if it's winter here and summer in [inaudible]
kurt	 Um then, it's the same thing but it's, uh, the sun's really hitting Alaska now
herb	 You mean South America?
kurt	 South America, sorry, South America then it's bouncing up into Chicago
herb	 Okay, so do you think South America gets as much sun in its summertime as North America gets in our summertime?
kurt	 Pretty much
herb	 Pretty much?  So how does that work with this idea here  that you've got parts of the sun giving off less light?  Because if it's winter here for Chicago it's summer in South America
kurt	 Mmm hmm
herb	 And if they're giving off the same amount of, if they're getting pretty much the same amount of light then um, it would be hard for the sun to be darker here, right?
kurt	 Mmm hmm
herb	 So how do you figure that works?
kurt	 Um, because the Earth's turning , it could be on a different side
herb	 Um, what do you mean?
kurt	 Like when the Earth's , you know, it's spinning around like, you said like, can you repeat the question, sorry
herb	 Um, what I was saying is that you brought up this idea earlier that the sun doesn't shine the same brightness on different parts, right?
kurt	 Mmm hmm
herb	 Um, do you still buy that?
kurt	 Pretty much, it depends on uh, what end, like if we're over here  and the other place is over here, it's not gonna get as much sunlight, it's not facing towards the sun
herb	 Right
kurt	 If it's gonna get any sunlight, it's gonna be reflection 
herb	 Right
kurt	 So, that's not
herb	 But does that mean that the sun is darker in this part?
kurt	 Um, not really, no
herb	 Okay.  So the sun, does the sun shine the same brightness on all sides?
kurt	 I guess so, yes
herb	 Okay.  So the summer and winter thing is due to this reflection idea
kurt	 Mmm hmm
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
