<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>mark</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	 Okay, okay.  Oh, I wanted to ask you about the seasons, we asked you this last time, too.  So I wanna know, why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter
mark	 Um, it's how the Earth's axis, like, 'cause it takes a whole year to completely go around the sun and how the Earth's axis, like, it keeps changing, like it slants more , so like
bruce	 Maybe this is something to draw a picture of, would that help to draw a picture of this?
mark	 It might
bruce	 Okay, give it a try
mark	 I'll give it a shot
bruce	 Okay
mark	  It's like, the sun, and this is the Earth's axis, 'cause the Earth's axis is not completely a, like, a perfect circle, so like a little bit spread out a little bit like that around, so.  The Earth, so the sun shine, but sometimes when the Earth goes around it's like farther and it's more tilted down, so like, it's like, so this is probably summer right now, 'cause it's like shining right down at us
bruce	 Mmm hmm
mark	 But like, when the Earth turns, it's like, that's why we only have same seasons, say like, while Chicago's having, um, summer, say like somewhere around the world, I don't know, Chile or somewhere else is probably having winter, or Argentina, anywhere
bruce	 And why is that again?
M 	 Because it's like, closer to Earth, 'cause like it's shining down, and Chile is like, below us and it takes l- another longer way to get down there, so it's like shining directly at us then again, it takes a long time down here so maybe that's why we're a little bit warmer during the summer
bruce	 So this is summer in Chicago and winter in Chile or something
mark	 It's possible or
bruce	 What would it look like when it's winter here and summer in Chile, where would, what would the Earth look like then?
mark	 Well it'd be at another different angle, if it was like summer
bruce	 What might it look like?
mark	 So, sun's here, maybe, well, my drawing [something] it's like, maybe it'll come around up and then, all of a sudden Chile has summer and then it takes longer for us, we have winter
bruce	 So we're- that's Chile sort of over here and we're 
mark	 Yeah, this is US, Chicago and Chile's down here
bruce	 And it has to do with how the Earth's angle is
mark	 Yeah, the axis, how the axis [something] the Earth
bruce	 So where's the Earth's axis, here?
mark	 Right here, the circle around
bruce	 Okay.  So the Earth is just sort of moving around
mark	 Yeah, slowly.  That's why the, in the morning, morning hours, when we wake up, it's usually colder, say this morning, it was very cold, like 9:30, but later on during the noontime, afternoon time, it gets warmer
bruce	 Uh huh.  And why is that?  Does that have something to do with this, or
mark	 Yeah, because while the Earth's, you know, completely spins  around 24 hours, not around the axis but just like spinning, it's like, sort of like it's in an angle, it's like how, um . . .how, it's like when we wake up, it's like the sun's in this angle , like, this is the sun, and this is the sun, the tip right here and this is like America right here and we slowly spin, so it's still in an angle, it's like slanted, until we turn around directly and the sun's, at noontime, it's like directly above us, that's why we're shining as much as, much hotter.  It's because when  we wake up, it's like still kind of slanted in a way, like the sun rays, so it's still in an angle, that's why the sun is closer to the horizon like in the morning hours 'cause it's like, so it's not shining directly at us, but like in an angle also
bruce	 Yeah, that makes total sense
mark	 In a very odd angle, you could say, so that's why.  So like, that's why we have different time zones, because well in Chicago it's probably like 8 in the morning it's like pretty cold but New York, it's probably a little bit warmer, 'cause it's more like, this is New York  and this is Chicago and the sun, so it's like slowly, um, that's why we got different times, so it's like, 'cause by the time they're noon, 'cause it would be directly above them and then it turns to 1 so th sun would be like in the other angle for them, like another way and while it comes back, the sun comes direct to us and that's when we hit noon and they hit 1 o'clock, 'cause noontime, around noontime, like a little bit after, that's when the sun's directly on top of us
bruce	 Mmm hmm.  So the key thing is how directly the light's hitting it
mark	 Mmm hmm.  So that's why we have, um, time change, a couple days ago, Saturday night, Sunday, we had change hour forward because our Earth's axis is changing 'cause it's maybe rising up more , we're a little bit closer to the sun and
bruce	 So that's an adjustment for that?
mark	 Yeah, for slow.  'Cause if it's like 11 . . .so right now, it's actually, um, it's like 10:45 right now, right now it'd be 9:45
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
