<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>ovadya</PNAME>
<INAME>betsy</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>cf</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
betsy	 I'm curious to know what you think about it now, why there're seasons, like why it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter and if you need to draw a picture we can do that or we can talk about it and then draw a picture.  Like, does it have anything to do with the sun and the Earth, what we're studying?  Do you have any idea or, you can just take a stab at it, we can talk about it
ovadya	 I don't know
betsy	 Like uh, the Earth, like, sometimes it's, well, it's winter and it's also, part of the Earth's winter and part of the Earth's summer.  Um, do you have any idea why it's winter and why it's summer, what might influence it or cause it?
ovadya	 Oh, 'cause, I think, the sun is going around the world so it's moving and I don't- it might - I think the sun rotates around  and then when- no, I'm not sure
betsy	 You're on the right track, you're really on the right track
ovadya	 It rotates around and then um, like if it's right here , this part of the world might get, it'd be warmer and it's on top, the pole might be warmer, um
betsy	 Yeah, there's one piece that you're missing and it's hard and as I said, we didn't talk about it in the workshop.  I'm going to give it to you now and I'm gonna ask you some questions I asked you a little bit ago again, just to see what you're thinking about it.  You're right, it's the movement of the sun and the Earth, but it's not the sun that's moving, it's actually-
ovadya	 The Earth
betsy	 The Earth, right. So like , sun, and then you have this Earth that's going around, so Earth is moving and uh, what that really means is that the sun's always in the same place and the Earth is moving so um, let's see, do you, if the Earth is moving around the sun , do you have any sense of why it might be warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
ovadya	 'Cause, uh, 'cause when it's moving around and uh Earth is spinning 24 hours a day and while it's spinning it, I don't know how long it takes it, I don't know how long it stays in one place, but, like in the summer it might be near to the sun and it's warmer and in the winter it's like back where it is and it's colder
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
