<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>stan</PNAME>
<INAME>betsy</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
betsy	 Okay, makes sense.  Let's go back to a question that I asked you earlier, like why it is warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
stan	 Because in the summer, the Earth is tilted more towards the sun, like we're here , the sun's here and then during the winter, we get, the Earth tilts back the other way so we're over here and the sun's like this so we're getting hit less directly instead of right on
betsy	 Okay
stan	 So it's summer here but winter in the south, but it's summer in the north, it's winter in the south- I just said the same thing there
betsy	 Summer in the north
stan	 Summer in the south it's winter in the north
betsy	 Okay, sorry, I was looking at my sheet, can you tell me again, you said something about the angles or something of the
stan	 Yeah, if you, like here's the Earth  and the su- 'cause it's at an angle, the Earth kind of wobbles like that, the angle of like how directly the sun hits you affects whether it's summer in the north or if the sun's down here, it's summer in the north so it gets like less intense and cooler in the north or it gets less intense and it gets cooler south
betsy	 Mmm hmm.  Can you draw me a picture of the relationship between the Earth and the sun as far as their movement?  Like maybe where summer might be and where winter might be?
stan	 Wait, you want me to draw like
betsy	 Yeah, you can draw here or you can draw on another piece of paper
stan	 Wait, say it again?
betsy	 Like, tell me what you think about or understand like the relationship betwee- of the Earth and the sun as far as how they move in relation to each other
stan	  There's the sun.  And the Earth goes around, pretty much in a straight line and it's wobbly
betsy	 Mmm hmm
stan	 And then the Earth spins day to day, it spins on its own axis and then it wobbles back and forth over a long period of time, it kind of slowly wobbles
betsy	 Mmm, the axis slowly wobbles.  But, so does the axis, let's see.  Sort of comparing these two pictures 'cause they kind of work together, where would summer be and where would winter be, if we're talking about, maybe might even want to draw the axis and how it
stan	 Well, um,  you have the axis like that, there's Earth, and see how it's kind of tilted towards the sun
betsy	 The southern hemisphere?
stan	 Yeah, tilted towards the sun, southern hemisphere, and it stays the same all around, kind of stays at the same angle  so now the north is more angled towards the sun and the south isn't
betsy	  Mmm hmm.  That makes sense.
stan	 It's not quite right, but okay
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
