<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>vanessa</PNAME>
<INAME>betsy</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
betsy	Uh, the same question I asked you in the beginning, why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter generally?
vanessa	 Because, oh we did talk about this.
betsy	 Oh did you?
vanessa	 'Cause  the sun's right here and then like Earth is over here and then this could probably be like winter but then when it gets over here closer to the sun it's like summer.
betsy	 Okay.  So it's summer here  because it's closer . . .
vanessa	 It's closer to the sun.
betsy	 Okay.  And it's winter  'cause it's . . .
vanessa	 Farther away.
betsy	 Farther away?  Okay.  Let's see, did I ask you in the beginning like what you think about people talking when they say it's colder in Alaska, or winter in Alaska when it's summer here?  Did we talk about that, I forget.
vanessa	 I don't know, I don't think so.
betsy	 You don't think so?  Yeah, I'm just curious to know.  I've heard people say that it's winter in Alaska when it's summer in Chicago
vanessa	 Well it's their summer actually 'cause like we're all having summer at the same time but um, it's like in Alaska, it's always cold there so . . .it's different.
betsy	 Oh, right, right, I meant Australia, sorry, sorry.  Uh, my question I meant to ask you, when it's, uh, summer in Australia and it's winter in Chicago
vanessa	 Oh, 'cause it's, Australia's in a different part and like at the Earth's tilt  the sun is at a different angle on Australia than on like Chicago or something.
betsy	 Oh, okay.  So the tilt has something to do with whether it's summer or winter
vanessa	 In a different place, yeah.
betsy	 Okay.  Hmm, I'm wondering how- what picture.  Some of th- this might just kind of, draw that idea, I'm thinking about it.  Can you talk to me more about like, so it's, just to describe what you were saying, um, so it's summer in Australia and it's winter in Chicago and that's due to the . . .
vanessa	 Earth's tilt.
betsy	 The Earth's tilt, okay.  So how might the Earth's tilt, if you want to draw a picture on this one or on another one, how might that make a difference?
vanessa	  That can be Chicago and that can be Australia.
betsy	 Okay, perfect.
vanessa	 And then , like, that's supposed to be over here, but, the sun is like, doesn't hit everything directly
betsy	 Mmm hmm.
vanessa	 So like, if it was somewhere in Australia, the sun would hit Australia more directly than it would Chicago.
betsy	 Okay.  So, so, and that's due to the  tilt of the Earth?
vanessa	 Yeah.
betsy	 Okay, why does the Earth tilt?
vanessa	 Because it's on an axis.
betsy	 Okay.  Where would the axis be if you were to draw that?
vanessa	 I don't know.
betsy	 You don't know?  Okay, that's fine, just thought . . .okay, so that makes sense , so then how does it work when it's uh summer in Chicago?  Could you draw what that looks like?
vanessa	  Kind of like that?
betsy	 Okay.  So here the sun is hitting the Earth in looks like in the northern hemisphere
vanessa	 Mmm hmm.
betsy	 Um  what would you say, less, more . . .
vanessa	 It's hitting it more in the northern hemisphere rather than down here
betsy	 Okay.  That makes sense.  And in this picture  you talked about how the, this is the Earth and that's the sun and we're spinning around the sun
vanessa	 Mmm hmm.
betsy	 Okay.  So the Earth spins around the sun , does it- how else does it move?  Like does it . . . 
vanessa	 It . . .
betsy	 Oh do you know
vanessa	 It goes around and then it spins at the same time 
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
