<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>william</PNAME>
<INAME>herb</INAME>
<PREPOST>post</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
herb	 Okay, what does it have to do with the seasons?
william	 Well, when the Earth is more, uh, more farther than, more farther than other planets or just farther from the sun
herb	 Uh huh
william	 It get, uh, colder
H 	 Okay
william	 So that makes the seasons
herb	 Um, okay, good.  So the interesting question there is, um, is, do you know that sometimes, have you heard that you know, when it's winter here, it's summer somewhere else?
william	 Yes
herb	 Um, so how does that work, if it's winter in one place and summer in another place?  What do you think exactly?
william	 The uh, I think it's uh, the Earth, are circle around  and uh I think it circle whole wor-, whole circle, I mean, do you know what I mean?
herb	 The whole orbit 
william	 Yeah
herb	 Yeah?
william	 It's different places, different season
herb	 Different places, different seasons?  Okay
william	 Uh, I think it's, I don't know, I forgot which place is uh, se- summer or spring
herb	 Okay
william	 Okay.  Just uh,  when it circle, that area, it turns uh, I think the sunlight shines on that [something] and the other places not getting many sun as the others so it gets cold
herb	 Okay.  Um, so, how does that relate to your idea that when the Earth is farther away , it's winter?
william	 Oops.  Just say the orbit here 
herb	 Uh huh
william	 See the Earth get farther and uh the sun is, let's say just North America, that's China or something.  The light shine in here and this doesn't get, uh, not enough sunlight
herb	 Uh huh
william	 So this is called summer and that is winter
herb	 Okay, so you're saying that this part , this is North America here, get sun?
william	 I think it's China or somewhere else
herb	 Oh, this is China?
william	 Yeah
herb	 And this is North America?
william	 Yeah
herb	 Okay, so you're saying that's what winter looks like for here
william	 Yeah, [something]
herb	 Um, did the, what about the idea that the Earth spins  by itself?  Spins on its own axis?
william	 Yeah
herb	 Um, do you know anything about that?
william	 I don't know if that's, Earth is, uh, everytime it orbits, it's farther, different everytime spinning around in the orbit, is that different from each time, is that different from each time?
herb	 Is it different from each time?
william	 Yeah
herb	 Mmm, I'm not exactly sure I understand your question, can you ask it again?
william	 I mean, when the su- Earth's orbit, is that each time the Earth orbit is different?
herb	 Is different than what?
william	 Different than the first time
herb	 Oh, you mean does it orbit  in a different way every time?
william	 Yeah
herb	 Um, no, actually it doesn't, yeah, I'll show you, I mean like, basically, uh, well you know that the Earth goes around the sun, right?
william	 Yeah
herb	 So  if this is the sun, and the Earth basically does that and it keeps going around and around and around in the same way every, you know, so it goes around, um, yeah.  So do you know how long it takes to go all the way around?
william	 I think it's one year
herb	 Right, so every year it's here again 
william	 Yes
herb	 And so every year it goes around the same way
william	 Okay
herb	 So, how does that um, does that, how does that relate to your idea that um, that it's
william	 That picture?
herb	 Yeah, exactly
william	 Uh, I think it's the orbit, this place  is different from the places, let's just say the Earth, yeah, is different from here, the distance, you know what I mean?
herb	 Yup, so you're saying that, for instance, maybe it's farther here than it is here?
herb	 Okay.  So if it's farther here than it is here, right
william	 Yes
herb	 Then, um, is it winter or summer?
william	 I think this is, just say here is uh, summer
herb	 Uh huh
william	 And uh, here is spring probably, this is winter and this is fall
herb	 Okay, so you're saying that maybe right here it's winter
william	 Yeah
herb	 Okay.  So if we draw a picture right there, that's wintertime, right?
william	 Mmm
herb	 So is it winter for North America or is it winter for China?
william	 I don't get it, how does the planet's other side get
herb	 Well, aside from the Earth going around the sun, does the Earth also spin ?
william	 Yes
herb	 It does?  How often does it spin?
william	 One day it turn 
herb	 One day a turn?
william	 Yeah
herb	 Okay.  So um, and what does that do?
william	 Uh, it could, um, week and month
herb	 Week and month?
william	 Well and it also move around
herb	 Right, but when the Earth- let's say the Earth spins around  once a day like you said
william	 Okay
herb	 Does that affect winter and summer?
william	 I think
herb	 You think so?
william	 Yeah
herb	 Does it affect day and night?
william	 Yes
herb	 How does it affect day and night?
william	 Well when sun is here , shine on Earth, and uh, turn, this place, such as Japan, someplace, when the Earth turn, if Japan is here, and uh, Mexico or something, the sun is shine on it, so it just day and Japan is night
herb	 Okay.  So how does Japan become day?  How does it become day in Japan?
W 	 Uh, the first is when, uh, sun shines on it and the Earth turn 
herb	 Okay
william	 Turn, slowly turn, turn, to the dark side of the Earth so it become night
herb	 Okay, so then it's nighttime in Mexico?
william	 Yeah
herb	 And daytime in Japan
william	 Yes
herb	 Okay, good.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
