<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>ali</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	The question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?  That's what I want to know.
ali	 Because of the su/ because of the Earth's movement .
bruce	 mm hmm
ali	 er...yeah, the axis of the Earth. 
bruce	 So how exactly does that work?  How does it make it...?
ali	 Well, like when the Earth goes around the sun it's kind of tilted.  It turns too  like every 24 hours it turns and so that changes our seasons
bruce	  but how does//
ali	So when it's away from the sun it's colder and when it's like directly in front of the sun it's hot
bruce	 I think, I think this calls for a picture, just because it's hard to talk about these things, so can you-
ali	 A picture, I don't know, I've seen a lot of pictures in books and stuff
bruce	 Well, just do your best to do one that makes sense to you
ali	 umm  The sun is right here
bruce	 mm hmm
ali	 And all these little planets are over there, I don't know
bruce	 Okay
ali	 And this is, well it's kind of tilted
bruce	 Okay
ali	The Earth.  And there's this imaginary thing right here , this line, and it's like going around.
bruce	 Okay.
ali	 No, actually it goes from, no, it goes from East to West, Right? This, when it moves around the sun 
bruce	 uh huh
ali	 I think it goes from east to west...Yeah, it goes like this 
bruce	 uh huh
ali	 Okay, yeah anyways, it goes around and it's kind of tilted 
bruce	 mm hmm
ali	And that's it, I guess 
bruce	 So where are we on this picture?
ali	 umm, well what's right now?  I don't know, well, winter // probably right here
bruce	//  Pick some time, like //suppose it's
ali	//Summer, like North America right here
bruce	 Okay, and we're right there
ali	 mm hmm
bruce	 So let's put a little picture of us right there.  Let's draw a little man there or something.
ali	 Like right here? 
ali	 Okay, let's see.  We're turning, > so in the winter we'll probably be away from the sun, like right here or like right there...actually, huh...we'd be like down here , no like here
bruce	 Right there
ali	 Yeah
bruce	 So could you put a little person there?   So that's us in the winter...And why is it colder then?
ali	 Oh, because it's away from the sun.
bruce	 And here you're sort of toward the sun.  So how is it that the Earth's moving?  The Earth's moving around like that?  And spinning?
ali	 mm hmm
bruce	 And in the winter will it sort of be back to the same spot but on the other side?  Or will it be kind of over here 
ali	 In the winter?
bruce	 Yeah, so here it's going around and its twirling.  Let's say it's right here in the summer.
ali	 mm hmm.  No it would be somewhere else.  Yeah, like down here or here
bruce	 Okay.  Like would the Earth be like right here?
ali	 Oh, oh, umm, I think it would be...I think it would umm, well if this was summer, if somebody was over here, then this would be winter, I think
bruce	 I see.  So it's on the opposite side.
ali	 Yeah.  It would be on the opposite side.
bruce	 And why, why is it on the opposite side?
ali	Well, I read in books, I think I did.  I've seen pictures and stuff.
bruce	 Okay, so it just seems familiar// to you 
ali	 //Yeah, it does.  We kind of talked about this in class.
bruce	 Okay, I think that's it for that.
ali	 Are you showing this to Miss Whitcomb?
bruce	 Probably not.  She might be interested.
ali
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	 You're doing well, though.  This is- the thing I'm really interested in is to see is the ways you have to reason about this stuff.  And you're doing the right thing. You're kind of thinking it through.  I don't, I didn't expect you to know exactly what the answer is.  I was hoping you'd do your best to reason it through, and that is exactly what you're doing.  Umm, here's- so we just talked about why it's warmer in the summer and kind of here in Chicago and colder in the winter here in Chicago, but there are some places on the Earth that are kind of generally warmer than each other, like Florida is warmer than Alaska//
ali	 //Because of the equator. 
bruce	 So why, so why is that?
ali	 The equator?  Because the equator is always facing the sun.  It's in the middle.
bruce	 So if you're near the equator, so why does that make Alaska,  I mean Florida warmer than Alaska?
ali	 Because Alaska is on the top, there's like this pattern, like here, can I see that (last drawing) for a second?
bruce	 Yeah, here.
ali	 Like I'm the computer person, and so we have this map. >  It was a July thing, the month July, and the equator was right here, so it's like warmer here, and then it's warmer here, and it starts to get like colder here, and then real cold right here (points moving up on drawing), Like Antarctica, and the arctic, and Greenland and Alaska
bruce	 So it's warmer here and colder as you go away?
ali	 Yeah
bruce	 But why is that?  Why is it warmer near the equator and colder farther away?
ali	 Because of the sun, and because, maybe because of the water
bruce	 mm hmm, so wh-
ali	 Like we were in Whitcomb class talking about how water, like there was this map and umm people just colored in land but no one colored in the water, and Miss Whitcomb asked why we didn't color in the water and she asked and we didn't know how to answer and all of us were like "we don't know" and then like someone raised their hand and said that like the heat or like the moisture or something like that
bruce	 You also said it might have to do with the sun
ali	 Yeah
ali	 Well, it's going around,  so- like these two parts are always away from the sun, I don't, I don't/  I just know it's real cold there.
bruce	 uh huh.  So these two parts are always away?
ali	 uh huh, yeah...cause it's like always tilted like that 
bruce	 But would that make this part sort of 
ali	 Yeah, it would, but I know like, I just know that Alaska is real cold. 
bruce	Okay.  So one thing I'm sort of wondering about is, here's the equator  so this seems like it would be warm, but this is the equator too but it's on the other side from the sun
ali	 I know, but the sun's so big.  I know it's like, the heat.  There's a lot of heat.
bruce	 There's a lot of heat where?
ali	 There's a lot of heat and it travels, I guess, to here ...mmm, I don't know, I can't think of anything, but I know that it's warmer in the equator
bruce	Okay, okay, perfect, perfect
ali	 Maybe it has to do with the water or the land, I don't know.
bruce	 Okay, that sounds fine.  You sort of know it's warmer here// and you get parts of ideas about why that is but you're not a hundred percent sure//.  Okay, that's what I wanted to know.  And that's the sort of thing you're going to learn about in the next couple of weeks too, specifically, pretty much.  You're going to learn exactly what the answer to that sort of question is.
ali	 //Yeah., //Yeah
ali	 Oh really?
bruce	Yeah, in the next couple of weeks you're going to work on that stuff.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
