<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>amanda</PNAME>
<INAME>betsy</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
    <SEASONS>
betsy	 Why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
amanda	 Cause the Earth is tilted toward the sun in the summer and in the winter it tilts, like since we're on, since we're on top, sort of to the north, and then in the summer, the North part of the Earth is, tilted, then like our hemisphere is tilted towards the sun, but in the winter, the southern one is tilted toward the sun and we're tilted away.  We're less close.
betsy	Okay, good.  I definitely need a picture of that.
amanda	 Here's the sun...and this is the summer one, and we're kind of...this is the Earth  .  Here's the hemispheres, and here's us, whatever we look like.  And so we're kind of tilted towards the sun.
betsy	Okay.
amanda	And in the winter, it's not supposed to be bigger, I just drew it that way
betsy	 That's fine.
amanda	 And it's kind of like this like this.  And we're right here.
betsy	 Okay.
amanda	And we're tilted away and the southern part is tilted towards it.  So more of the light goes here.
betsy	And why is it tilt?  Do you know why the Earth tilts?
amanda	 Um, because of the gravity of the other planets or something?
betsy	 Okay.  Can you show me  how the Earth and sun interact as far as which one moves around who or-
amanda	 Oh,    The Earth is like right here.
betsy	 Okay.
amanda	 And there's a couple of planets in here, and it kind of goes around like that 
betsy	 Okay.
betsy	 That's pretty easy.  You understand it.  So you don't know why, or thinking about why maybe it's tilted.  Sometimes it's closer to the sun - In summer it's closer to the sun, and in the winter it's farther
amanda	 I don't know why it tilts like that
betsy	 Okay.  Well, it's something we can learn about this week.
betsy	 Actually, on your picture, now that I'm thinking about it, can you show me where the light, how the light hits the Earth in the summer and in the winter?
amanda	 Well, in the summer, it's more direct, and then since the southern hemisphere is tilted away, it doesn't hit it as closely, so it has to warm up more land because it has a diagonal , and in the winter, it has to hit us more diagonally because it's not so- it's tilted and it has to warm up more.
    </SEASONS>
    <CLIMATE>
betsy	 Great.  Great.  Okay, thank you.  Okay, next question.  Why do you think, in general, it's warmer in Florida than it is in Alaska.
amanda	 Because Florida is closer to the equator, the middle part 
betsy	 Okay.
amanda	 And since it doesn't get as tilted as Alaska does, because Alaska's like way up here.
betsy	 Okay.
amanda	 And so...
betsy	 It has something to do with where it is?
amanda	 Yeah.  On the Earth.  So like Alaska is more tilted away, it has to warm up more land in Alaska, and Florida, since Florida is near the equator
betsy	 Yeah
betsy	 Okay, okay.  Alright, that's great.
    </CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
