<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>angela</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>cf</TCODE>
<BODY>
    <SEASONS>
bruce	 I want to know why it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter.
angela	That's because of the sun is in the center and the Earth moves around the sun and the Earth is like at one point in the winter, it's like farther away from the sun // and towards the summer it's closer it's near, towards the sun.
bruce	 //uh huh, uh huh.  I think I get it.  Can you just draw a picture so I'm completely sure? 
angela	 Okay.  The sun's in the middle  and the Earth kind of orbits around it
bruce	 uh huh
angela	 And like say at one - it's probably more of an ovally type thing  In the winter, er probably this will be winter since it's further away ,
angela	 See, that's winter would be like, the Earth orbits around the sun .  Like summer is the closest to the sun.  Spring is kind of a little further away, and then like Fall  is further away then spring but not as far as winter, and then winter is the furthest.
bruce	 mm hmm
angela	 So the sun doesn't, like the flashlight and the bulb, it hits summer, the lines like fade in , they get there closer, like quicker
bruce	 mm hmm
angela	 And by the time they get there [winter], it fades and it's a lot colder for winter
bruce	 mm hmm
angela	 And spring it's kind of between the two and same for fall
bruce	 mm hmm.  Is this something, have you done this already for your class that you know this from?
angela	 uh, kind of, like from first and second grade I remember the time that Earth orbiting and whatnot
bruce	 mm hmm, okay.  So that makes a lot of sense.  One thing I wanted to ask you though about was, one thing that you might have heard is that at the same time, and you can tell me if you've heard this, when it's summer here, it's actually winter in Australia
angela	 mm hmm
bruce	 Have you heard that before?  So I was wondering if your picture the way you drew it can explain that or if that's a problem for your picture.
angela	 Umm, I need another picture.
bruce	 So is that a problem for you picture? 
angela	 Yeah, that is.  Um, ok.  There is the sun.  Yeah, I remember that now cause um it's like as the Earth is rotating, as it's orbiting, it's rotating too. I guess I don't understand it.
bruce	 You're saying as the Earth is going around here, it's doing what?
angela	 It's like spinning, cause it's going like , that's how it's day and night too
bruce	 Spinning like a top
angela	 Yeah
bruce	 Okay
angela	 So, yeah, I guess I really don't understand it that much...Yeah, I have heard that, cause I was supposed to go to Australia this summer but it was going to be winter when I was going, but their winters are really warm
bruce	 So you're thinking that somehow the spinning, that somehow if you take into account the fact that the Earth is also spinning, that might help to explain why it's summer and winter at different times
angela	 I gue- yeah.
bruce	 That's what you were thinking?
angela	 Kinda, yeah
bruce	 Just to be clear, what was the problem with this picture for the-
angela	 Because, yeah I rethought that and it looks really stupid because summer is really close but how could you winter on the other side, how could it be winter on the other side if it's really close here, and how could it be really warm if this [winter earth] is really far away.  I don't know.  That looks really dumb to me now.
bruce	 It doesn't look really dumb to me.  A lot of people explain it this way.  Okay, I'm not going to give away answers yet to find this out.  You can find this out in your class
angela	 Alright.
    </SEASONS>
    <CLIMATE>
bruce	 And I have just one last question.  The last question I want to ask is why is it...So this is about changes from summer to winter, summer to winter, but also it's generally warmer in Florida and colder in Alaska.  So why is that?
angela	 That's because Alaska is like at the very top, it's the furthest from- the sun hits the equator, I guess, and that's why the equator is so warm, and so the top part, so the very top parts and the very bottom parts don't get as much heat as anywhere else
bruce	 Why is it they don't get as much heat?
angela	 Because
bruce	 Would it help to draw a picture of this too?
angela	 Okay
bruce	 I just know sometimes it's easier to explain things in pictures
angela	 Yeah.    The sun is like, when the Earth  is rotating I guess, it's rotating on that line  and it's spinning on that line too, so the equator would be like there and the very North part doesn't get as much heat from the orbiting of the sun, because the sun is kind of in the center and it hits the equator, I guess, that's at the top and that's at the bottom so it doesn't get hit with the sun.
bruce	 Which is the top?
angela	 It's that, and that's the bottom.
bruce	  If this was the sun, and this was the Earth, where would the equator be?
angela	 It would probably be in the center , right there.
bruce	 I see.  And the North Pole is here? 
angela	 The North pole's there, the south pole is there  and it doesn't get as much heat from the sun.
bruce	 And why doesn't it get as much heat?
angela	 Because it's like sticking out from the top.  Because it's not getting hit directly.
bruce	 Uh huh.  
angela	 It's getting hit less.
bruce	 So it's less directly getting hit, //I see.
angela	 //Right
bruce	 So here, it's kind of straight on.  Okay, that makes sense.  That was my last question.  You did great.  I know these questions are hard, but that's what I wanted to know is how you think about this stuff.
    </CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
