<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>beth</PNAME>
<INAME>betsy</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
betsy	 The next question is very different.  I generally want to know why is it colder in the winter and warmer in the summer.
beth	 Because in the winter, the Earth is, you know, the Earth moves on its axis, it gets further away from the sun  in the winter, so we don't feel the heat as much, I guess it tips, the southern 
betsy	 If you want to draw 
beth	 If I can use an example or something or even one of these 
betsy	 Yeah, sure
betsy	 Okay
beth	 So I guess the northern hemisphere moves away from the sun
betsy	 Okay
beth	 So that's why it gets colder
betsy	 Okay.  Umm .  And just generally I think I understand exactly what you're saying, but the movement of the Earth and sun in relation to each other is what exactly? 
beth	 I guess the gravity of the sun makes the Earth move around it
betsy	 Okay
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
betsy	 Okay, umm...Next question is can you think or explain to my why it's warmer in Florida generally and colder in Alaska?
beth	 Because Florida is nearer to the equator  and the equator is always I guess going to be closer to the sun cause it's the part of the sun that extends the furthest, like that way  I guess towards the sun so it's closer and it will always like, the equator isn't ever going to be out far - far north or far south  so it's never going to get that cold
betsy	 So  it's just a function of this  being closer than that .  Is that what you're saying?
beth	 Basically.
betsy	 Okay.  If you could draw a picture sort of how the sun's, I think we were talking about the light from the sun-
beth	 Yeah
betsy	 Sun gets to the Earth.  Showing again like the ideas of rays, that would be helpful
beth	 Sure.  I can try.
betsy	 Yeah, don't worry about it, it doesn't have to be anything...a masterpiece or anything.
beth	  There's the sun, and here's the Earth , and it's kind of like this, so say it's summer right now so it's more like that
betsy	 mm hmm
betsy	 mm hmm
betsy	 mm hmm
beth	 I guess, and if like the sun's rays are coming out  like this, du du du du, Alaska, there just going to come there but it's going to be this much longer and I guess proportionally from the distance here  it's not going to be that much, but it'll be a big distance in temperature from this close to that close 
betsy	 And it's just the, okay, so it's a function of the distance from the, from the sun being that it's farther 
beth	 mm hmm
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
