<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>deidra</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
    <SEASONS>
bruce	 So what I want to talk about is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
deidra	 Here we go again.  I got in trouble with this last week.
bruce	 Did someone ask you about this last week?
deidra	 Yup.
deidra	 Ms. Whitcomb
bruce	 Oh really?
deidra	 We had like a half an hour conversation on this.
bruce	 Oh really?
deidra	 Yup
bruce	 Okay, well you should know a lot about this then.
deidra	 Uh oh, I don't know how much I learned about it.
bruce	Okay, well tell me what you think.
deidra	When the Earth orbits around the sun and it goes around around over, and the light, and the sun heats it up and cools it down and the axis turns and I guess heats up on different ends. 
bruce	 Say it again.
deidra	Okay, the Earth rotates around the sun.  And the Earth rotates around its axis, so it changes, I didn't say that the last time.  So it changes its temperature at the day and at night, during the seasons also.  So during the winter, it's going to be cold here, but it's going to be warmer on the other side of the Earth, basically.  The sun's basically on it, lighting on it.  When it turns around and its summer, it's going to be cooler on the other side and it's going to be warmer on our side.
bruce	 Okay, for this I definitely need a picture.
deidra	 I don't know how to draw that.
bruce	 Well, let's just start and see where we get.
deidra	 Alright.  This is the sun right there.    I can't draw.
bruce	 That's a good sun.  That's about as well as I can draw.
deidra	 You can draw better than that.  Okay, and the Earth's here, and you've got the invisible axis going through it .  And this turns whichever way it turns, I don't know.  It goes round and round.  And then this, while the sun is going, circle of motion, and then it goes around the sun also.
bruce	 Okay
deidra	 And then, I don't know
bruce	 So the Earth goes around like this.
deidra	 Okay, we're going to do this before I get messed up.  Gotta think clearly here.  When this rotates by itself, it creates the days and nights.  And when this is rotating around the sun, that creates summer and winter, and the fall and spring.  You're totally confused.
bruce	 Well, I think I get the basic, I get parts of it.  So where, can you show me summer first?
deidra	 Okay, so which side are we on?
bruce	 Well, you can put us wherever you want.
deidra	 Okay.  Summer would be  I don't know if the sun's going to be here or not [referring to planet]- we're going to be here.  The United States is going to be there.  And then it will be, and then winter will be over here  and where we are 
bruce	 And why is it summer here?  Because 
deidra	 We're close to the sun.  And over here we're further from the sun [referring to winter drawing] so we're not getting as much heat.
bruce	 I see.
deidra	 does that make any sense?
bruce	 I think so.  So one thing I know, so we go around like this  and we're sort of rotating.  But the main thing is if whether you're closer to the sun or further away.
deidra	 Yeah.
bruce	 I got it.  Umm, one thing I, you may have heard and I know is that when it's winter here, it's summer in Australia.  Have you heard that before?
deidra	 That's what I was just thinking.
bruce	 So is that a problem for your picture?
deidra	 I don't know.  Where's Australia at?  I don't know my geography.  That's one thing I don't know.
bruce	 Well, we're sort of in the north part of the Earth.  And Australia is-
deidra	 Down south.
bruce	 Yeah, way down south.
deidra	 Australia is also on the opposite side of the Earth though.
bruce	 That's true.
deidra	 Or somewhat on the opposite side of the Earth
bruce	 Yeah, I think it is on the opposite side.
deidra	 Okay, so Australia will be over here .  So during our summer they'll be having winter if that theory is true.  I don't know if it's true or not though.
bruce	 Right.
deidra	 And then over here, they'd be over here so they'd be having summer.
bruce	 Right, so that works for Australia.
deidra	 Yeah
bruce	 Okay.  Okay, I think that's enough for that question.
deidra	 That's good.
bruce	 So you talked about this with your teacher?
deidra	 Yeah
deidra	 Well, I was in class and since we're getting pulled out of our class for graduation practice, we were just like talking.
bruce	 I see.  But it wasn't like your whole class working on it or something.
deidra	 No, it was just me.  Everyone else was on the computers doing research.
    </SEASONS>
    <CLIMATE>
bruce	 Umm, one last question.  So we were just talking about how it gets warmer in the summer and colder in the winter, but another thing is that year-round, it's kind of generally hotter in Florida and colder in Alaska.   So I'm wondering if you have some kind of idea why that is.  Why is it hotter in Florida and colder in Alaska?
deidra	I can do this one.  Okay .  The world's there, the equator's there , and then further south toward the equator it's going to be warmer than it is from the North, I just, I don't know
bruce	 I think you said it right
deidra	 I was just thinking did I say this was north [equator] and this was south [north pole]
bruce	 No, you did it right
deidra	 So this is North, this is South, and Florida is down here in the South and Alaska is up here in the North, so further up North is going to be colder than it is down south.
bruce	 And why is that?  You knew that was coming right?
deidra	Yes, I did.  I know this though, that's the scary thing.  Okay.  I forget though.  I don't know why I don't know right now.  It has something to do with the sun shining in that area.
bruce	 uh huh.  So where is the Sun?  The sun's out here  somewhere
deidra	 Yeah.  No idea.  So the sun's going to be shining more in this general area  than it is up here, something like that, I don't know.
bruce	 But you're not sure why it's shining more
deidra	 Yeah.  I don't know why shining more on there
bruce	 mm hmm, the sun's way out here
deidra	 Yeah
bruce	 My sun... Shining like that.
deidra	 If the sun's shining right there, the equator is catching all of the rays.  But if the sun were right here, the northern part would be getting more of it.  And if the sun were shining right here , this side would be getting more of it.  So I don't know where the sun's shining on the world, but you know
bruce	 But let's just start with this, if the sun were right here, then you would, then the equator would be getting more of the rays and that would make sense with what you s-
deidra	 It'd be getting more heat
bruce	 why does it get more of the rays?  Why does the equator get more of the rays?
deidra	 Because it gets direct heat, it comes at a straight line right there.
bruce	 uh huh, but what about, does some of it go up here? 
deidra	 Some of it will go up there, but not all of it.
bruce	 uh huh, but you think for some reason more goes there 
deidra	 Yeah, cause it's a direct light [sic]
bruce	 So the key is that this is more direct than it is to there?
deidra	 It's basically like when the sun is shining right above you and you go under a tree and it's colder than it is outside, like outside of the tree.  Cause when you go outside, the leaves are absorbing all of it and when you're out and it's not, it's hotter, so this is basically the tree and this is not the tree. 
bruce	 So how is this like being in the tree?  The North Pole?
deidra	 Basically, the sun's here, so it's shining directly here , but it's not shining directly here , so it's going to be cooler up here than it is down here  cause it's not in direct light.
bruce	 So when you're in the shade of a tree, you're not in direct light?
deidra	 Yeah
bruce	 Okay, I see.  But are you getting, you are getting some light?
deidra	 Yeah.
bruce	 Okay, how does the light get to you when you're under the tree?
deidra	 Just through the leaves.
bruce	 So some goes through the leaves?
deidra	 Yeah.  
bruce	 I see
bruce	 I see
deidra	 Unless the sun's like, if this is like you're tree right here  ugh, I can't draw again.  If that's your tree and the sun is shining like this  then it's going to be hotter.  But it you went over to this side it would be a little cooler because of the shade.
bruce	 So some of it gets through, a little bit.  //And that's why you get a little warm.  And it's the same thing here that there's kind of more here  but less kind of gets up there?
bruce	 I think that's all my questions.
deidra	 That's it.
bruce	 You did great.
    </CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
