<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>denise</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
    <SEASONS>
bruce	 So the first thing I want to know is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
denise	 Cause the Earth is rotating and it's closer to the sun when it's like, summer is when your part of the country is closest to the sun and winter is like when it's on the other side
bruce	 When what's on-
denise	 Like when we're in summer, in China it's winter
bruce	 uh huh, 
denise	 And when China is in summer, we're probably in winter, because we're further away from the sun
bruce	 uh huh
denise	 And they're closer to the sun
bruce	 mm hmm.  That makes sense, but just for the fun of it, I want to ask you to draw a picture.  I'm into pictures today.
bruce	 You can start again if you want to.
denise	 Okay 
bruce	 Okay
bruce	 mm hmm
denise	 And when the United States is over here, it's winter.
bruce	I see.   So the United States is here in summer, and the Earth rotates around like that.  Is there any other ways the Earth moves?  Or is that pretty much it, the Earth is here and it's rotating?
denise	 Oh, and it may go around the sun?
bruce	 mm hmm, so it also goes around this?
denise	 mm hmm
bruce	 Does that have anything to do with summer and winter?
denise	I don't know.
bruce	 You're not sure?  Okay.  How does this relate to when it's day and night?  Or does it not have anything to do with that?
denise	 Maybe when it's going around the sun?  Well, I don't know.
bruce	 You're just not sure?
denise	 huh uh
bruce	 But this sort of makes sense to you that you've got this is summer and when this moves around out of the way, it would be summer in China and winter in the United States?
denise	 mm hmm
    </SEASONS>
    <CLIMATE>
bruce	 Okay, okay that makes sense to me.  And this, by the way, is more like the stuff we'll be working on in the workshop, understanding why it's different temperatures in different places.  And speaking about that, here's my next question.  So we just talked about it's, um summer sometimes here and winter sometimes in China kind of changes over the course of the year.  Even here in Chicago, sometimes it's much hotter sometimes and much colder sometimes.  But there's some places that are generally hotter and colder.  So in general, Florida is pretty much all the time warmer than Alaska.  So I'm wondering why that is?  Why-
denise	 Cause Florida is closer to the equator than Ch- I mean Alaska, and the equator's warm.  It's warm close to the equator.
bruce	 Mm hmm.  And why do you think its warm closer to the equator?
denise	 Don't know
bruce	 So that's something you're not sure about.  Okay.  That's good.  That's something we can learn about next week.  Okay.  I'm done with asking about Florida and Alaska.  You're doing just great, exactly the sort of stuff I want to know.
    </CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
