<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>edgar</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
    <SEASONS>
bruce	The first thing I want to know is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
edgar	 For us?
bruce	 Sure
edgar	I think the Earth is like tilted on an angle and usually it rotate and like I think it stops right there where the sun hit directly at the state so I think it get hotter, and for winter it turns on other side and the sun's not reaching it so it will be colder
bruce	mm hmm, can you draw a picture of that?
edgar	Yeah.  Here's the Earth slanted.  Here's the axis.  Here's the North Pole, here's the south pole, and here's our country.  And the sun's right here, and the rays are hitting directly right here, so things are getting hotter in the summer and when this thing turns, the country will be here and the sun can't reach as much.  It's not as hot as...the winter.
bruce	 mm hmm, I see. This is- In the winter we're on this side.
edgar	 And the summer's right here, it turns, it rotates.
bruce	 I see.  It's rotating around like this . 
edgar	 uh huh
bruce	 Is that the only way the Earth moves, or does it move in some other way too?
edgar	 I don't think so, only this way 
bruce	 So the sun is here and the Earth is here and it kind of goes like that 
edgar	 like that, but it goes all around.
bruce	 Oh, so it also goes around like this?
edgar	 Orbits.
bruce	 So where ...Say we're here and it's summer, where is it, where will the Earth be when it's winter?
edgar	 Actually, I don't think this moves, it turns and it moves like that and it turns and it's further away once it orbits around the sun.
bruce	 It's further away?
edgar	 Yeah, and somehow like that goes further off and the sun rays wouldn't reach as much to the Earth.
bruce	 Oh, in the winter it's further away.  Is that a different explanation?  Before you said it has to do with this thing of
edgar	 Yeah, that's a different explanation because I thought it wrong
bruce	 So you think, so now you're changing your explanation for this
edgar	 Yeah, changing it
bruce	 Okay, let's hear the new one.
edgar	 It's basically, what someone say about the orbits
bruce	 Oh, okay
edgar	 (pointing) once it turn right here, it's a little closer to the sun
bruce	 Let's do another picture real quick.
edgar	 Like here's the orbit, here's the sun (draws them)
bruce	 mm hmm
edgar	 It's like summer right here, cause it's actually closer to the sun than over here (points at opposite point), so when it moves, it turns to another country, it reach here and it's further away from the sun and it doesn't get as much heat, energy, rays
bruce	 So the main thing is that it's closer in the summer
edgar	 And further in the winter
bruce	 Have you heard this though, that when it's summer in the northern hemisphere,  like when it's summer here, it's winter in Australia, or like the southern hemisphere?   Have you heard that before?
edgar	 No.
bruce	 Oh, okay...Okay. (talks about putting name on paper)
    </SEASONS>
    <CLIMATE>
bruce	 Okay, I have one last question about these things.  We talked about here in Chicago, it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter , but there are also some parts on the Earth that are generally warmer and some parts that are generally colder, like it's generally warmer in Florida and colder in Alaska.  So why is that?
edgar	  I'm not so sure about that question
bruce	 Okay.  So you're not really sure why it's warmer 
edgar	 No
edgar	 I think it's something about the sun rays, like they hit there more than Alaska
bruce	 uh huh
bruce	 mm hmm
edgar	 And basically Florida is like in the middle or something and it goes more heat and sun rays from the sun than Alaska because Alaska's further up middle, by Canada and that part, North Pole
bruce	 mmm...Can you draw a picture of that?  I'm pretty sure I get what you're saying and it makes sense.  Just to be doubly clear let's draw a picture.
edgar	 Umm, Alaska's right here  , and there's Canada  , and United States right here.  I'll just draw squares, Alaska.
bruce	 Oh that's Uni - oh I see.
edgar	 And umm, the sun rays hit directly (points toward US) and basically it warms this part more, and Alaska is further up to the North Pole around Canada and the further it goes up it's colder and the lower it goes it's colder. 
bruce	 Why do the sun's rays hit more directly here (points at US)
edgar	 Cause it's in the middle and in the summer it hits right there, like it's near the equator too, so...
bruce	 Okay, and why does being near the equator help? 
edgar	 The equator - I think if like a country lies between the equator, that area is hotter than the normal temperature of the country 
bruce	 Oh, okay.  And why does the equator, why does being near the equator make it generally warmer? 
edgar	 I'm not sure - I think it's the middle of the Earth or something? 
bruce	 What do you mean the middle?
edgar	 I'm not sure, it's like the light part directly hits from the sun
bruce	 Oh, okay.
edgar	 That's what I think.
bruce	 Oh, it's because it gets a direct
edgar	 mm hmm, just direct, and that's why it gets warmer.
bruce	 What if I drew a diagram like this? (draws)  So here's the Earth, and here's the sun over here somewhere.  Can you explain it with this picture somehow?
edgar	 It's on axis, and here's the equator and the summer it usually hit like this and it hit like direct around near equator area 
bruce	 uh huh
edgar	 So I think a country lies between right here it's getting hotter in this area
edgar	 Less directly
bruce	 Okay
edgar	 So, that's what I think 
bruce	 Okay, that makes a lot of sense, that's about right.  And this is the sort of stuff, I don't think you've gotten to this yet, and this is the kind of stuff you're going to learn about.  This exact question in the next week or two. 
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
