<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>alex</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Okay? So the question is, the first question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter.
alex	Well it's warmer in the summer because of how the earth is on its axis, it's, when it's rotating it's closer to the sun and then it's tilted a little. And in the summer it's, your, our part of the, where we are is tilted closer to the sun, so it's warmer, and then in the winter we're tilted like away from the sun.
bruce	Okay. So how does that work? What if this is, if this is the sun , what is the earth?
alex	This, if this is, then the earth  like if you hold, this is like the north pole and the south pole, it's tilted a little, kind of. And if we're here  right now it would be winter because we're farther away, but then in summer in would be tilted like that, and then we're closer and it's warmer.
bruce	Okay. And how, where  so, and how, how so, how was the earth moving it's - ?
alex	Just around the sun .
bruce	Okay, and so let's say we're here.
alex	It's not, but it's not in like a perfect circle. It's, I don't know, it'll be farther away here and then maybe a little closer depending on what time of year it is.
bruce	So how close it is, does that effect
alex	Yeah, how close it is, and then how it's on it's axis.
bruce	Okay. So both those things effect summer or winter.
alex	Mhm.
bruce	Okay, so can you draw me a picture? I think I got it.
alex	Sure.
bruce	Did Rosemary have you draw pictures too?
alex	Yeah .  Like, like if that dot on the earth is us, we, it'd be like summertime now, because it's tilted more towards, the earth's tilted more towards the sun, so it's warmer. And then, it's, yeah closer to the sun on its rotation around the sun.
bruce	So, okay, so it's, and we're, so can you draw winter now?
alex	Yeah.
bruce	Can you draw it on the same picture, or can you not?
alex	Um, I guess. Um, you'd, like this is  I don't know, I guess you can't really. I mean.
bruce	Okay, so you can make me another picture if you want.
alex	So  um, we would be like there. And we'd tilted away a little. And then we're farther from the sun.
bruce	Okay.
alex	So.
bruce	so this is, we're farther from the sun, and we're the, we're tilted away?
alex	Well, it'd  it's  so, like it's, the sun I guess should kind of be, they should switch where they are, but then the top would be pointing that way, and then we'd be there because then it'd  so it'd kinda, like that's the sun and then earth, there it's the winter and then it's a little closer here in the summer.
bruce	I see.
alex	And then it goes around. And then, the axis, or, uh, it would be like that and then, like that.
bruce	Okay. It's a little further away here and it's tilted away. 
alex	Yeah.
bruce	You also, you have it tilted away, but you also put the dot on the other side, is that?
alex	That, that
bruce	Is that right? Is that what you meant to do?
alex	Um, not  um, kind of. Well, I'm trying to like picture it in my head of how it would be, but I guess  hmm  well yeah, this, well this is kind of like, um sort of, if you compare this picture of the winter summer it would be kind of bad because they're on the same side of the sun, but  so yeah, I guess I probably shouldn't have put that one there so.
bruce	Okay, okay. Um, now have you ever heard that when it's winter here it's summer in other parts of the earth?
alex	Yeah.
bruce	So does that fit with your like, does that fit with your picture?
alex	Well, yeah, cause if we're on somewhere on this side of the earth, and it's winter time, then like right here it'd be sort of summer time there. Cause they're tilted closer.
bruce	So wait, so we're, so this is winter for us, right?
alex	Yeah.
bruce	And where is, where is it summer?
alex	On the, like this side it would kind of be winter and fall, and over here it would be summer and spring.
bruce	On this, on this side of the earth?
alex	Like if you sort of split ‘em down the middle like that, this side is summer, and then that's winter.
bruce	This side is summer and that side is winter?
alex	Yeah.
bruce	Okay, um so this, if it's summer here, then this side, this area is having its summer when it's further from the sun?
alex	Well
bruce	You know what I'm asking?
alex	Yeah. Yeah. Um  well, it's I don't know if it would be, cause I'm not really sure, but what I think what I think is what I remember from school and stuff is, it's not like in a perfect circle around the sun, and so it kinda  yeah, so it, although it's sort of farther from the sun, I guess it could still be summer, and one part in winter and the other part it just, yeah.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay, that makes sense. Um, what else did I want to ask you, um, I want to, I guess what I want to ask you next is, um so we talked about like why here it's sometimes warmer and sometimes colder, but there are some places like Florida that are always pretty warm
alex	Yeah.
bruce	And some places like Alaska that are always pretty cold. 
alex	Well, that I guess is not as much I mean it's still the earth's axis and how close it is from the sun, actually it's more how close it is to the sun because Alas—uh, if you look at it the equator, it's like sort of this, the closest in the center part of the world with the most light and heat hits it, and Florida is closer to the equator than Alaska, so it's mostly warm, and then since Alaska is kind of in a weird spot above, far from the equator, and then sort of up there, um, the earth it's usually kinda cold.
bruce	Could you just draw a picture of that?
alex	Yeah.
bruce	Let's move this because the colors bleed sometimes.
alex	 And then
bruce	So that's the earth?
alex	This is the earth, and then the dotted line's the equator,
bruce	Okay.
alex	And then up here is Alaska, and then sort of down here is where Florida would be.
bruce	Okay.
alex	And then, since the light from the sun, it, this is, it like, since that where the equator is is more like towards the center of where all the light goes to, it's warmer, the closer you are to the equator, it's warmer and, there whereas, that's above the equator and it doesn't get as warm.
bruce	Okay.
alex	So it's yeah.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
