<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>blake</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	So my first question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
blake	Um, the reason why it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter is because the way earth tilts.
bruce	Mhm  So how does the tilt make it
blake	The tilt  tilts some sides to more toward the sun and the other sides away from the sun.
bruce	Okay. Um  so can you draw a picture?
blake	Yeah. So  and the line going through it is the tilt. 
bruce	Okay.
blake		So sometimes it's like that and then the other times it's like that. And then here's the sun.
bruce	Mhm.
blake	And then the orbit  So sometimes one side is tilted more toward the sun, so this side, so everything above here would be getting more sun and then everything above here would be getting less sun because this side is closer to the sun.
bruce	Okay. So  so sometimes we're tilted away and we're further from the sun?
blake	This, yeah. I'm not sure how to draw it. So it would be like
bruce	You're drawing it well.
blake	This side, the side that I would be shading in  this half 
bruce	Okay.
blake	Is  not getting as much sun because it's tilted further away from, or it's tilted, it's getting more sun because it's tilted more towards the sun.
bruce	The sun's over here?
blake	Yeah.
bruce	Okay. Okay, so that makes sense and, so sometimes, like in Chi- we're tilted toward the sun, sometimes we're tilted away. How does that happen? How does the earth get from one position to the other?
blake	When it's rotating. So when the earth  is on an orbit I guess it gets, so each line represents the tilt of the earth.
bruce	Let's, let's do it on a separate piece because it, it kind of bleeds through.
blake	Okay. So each, so then  so then now each line that I draw is, is how much the earth is tilted.
bruce	Mhm.
blake	I'm pretty sure this is not  and these lines are supposed to get straighter. And then once it's here again it will, the day and night will, or the tilt of the earth will be exactly the same.
bruce	Mhm. So where, where's  the north pole on each of these lines?
blake	The north pole is there.
bruce	Mhm. The north pole is there. Okay. So we - can we, can we do that in three dimensions maybe? So what if, what if this is the sun  and let's say, let's say this is the north pole . Can you show me with the pen how it moves?
blake	Yeah. It would be like  so starting here it would be like  so it would be starting straight up and down here, then it tilts more, then it starts to tilt this way, then it gets less of a tilt and then it's back to there.
bruce	Okay. Okay, that makes sense. Um, great. Um, I just have one other question I want to ask you.
blake	Okay.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Um, so we talked about like why it's warm here in Chicago sometimes and why it's cold sometimes. But there are some places like Florida that are generally always hot.
blake	Because that is closest to the equator. So  this is earth and here's the equator. Here's the prime meridian, and then, since the equator is, for whenever it's tilted so if it's tilted this way, that way, it will always be facing closer to the sun. Or since it's in the center it won't be tilted that much.
bruce	Okay, and so wait, why does being in the center, because it's not
blake	Because it's not going to be tilted that much.
bruce	Mhm.
blake	When the earth tilts. So let's say that um,  this is the equator.
bruce	Mhm.
blake	When the earth tilts it doesn't move that much.
bruce	Yeah. But why does that make it be warmer?
blake	Because it's always pointed closer to the sun.
bruce	Okay. So it's because it's closer, or because it's 
blake	Because it's in the center  and not being tilted as much.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
