<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>candice</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	No? Okay. So my first question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
candice	Um, I think I don't know. I haven't really thought about that . Um,   maybe cause the sun is closer.
bruce	Uh-uh.
candice	Yeah
bruce	So how would that work?
candice	Um so planets are like revolving around the sun, and then I don't really know.
bruce	You're on a good track here, so keep, let's hear a little more. So the planets go, go around the sun, is that what you said?
candice	Uh-huh. And then   um,   I don't know.
bruce	So what's   so, so let's say this is the sun , and how are the planets moving?
candice	Like around 
bruce	Okay, and so they're going like this?
candice	Yeah.
bruce	Okay. Um, and what, what are some of the planets? Like just name some of them.
candice	Jupiter, Saturn, and Neptune.
bruce	And the one we live on?
candice	Earth .
bruce	Okay, and, okay and how does the earth move?
candice	Like all the other planets around.
bruce	Okay, so it goes around like this .
candice	
bruce	And you were, so how might that relate to why it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
candice	Um,  
bruce	Just what were you thinking a minute ago?
candice	I, like I said, I think the sun's closer in the summer than the winter.
bruce	Mhm. 
candice	Yeah
bruce	And if we're going around, how might that be the, how might that work out that the sun is closer?
candice	Um,   I don't know. 
bruce	Well let, can we try drawing a picture? I'll tell you what to draw to start, okay?
candice	Okay.
bruce	So start by drawing the sun. 
candice	So this is the sun.
bruce	Very nice sun.
candice	
bruce	And, okay, let's have an earth.
candice	Okay, so it's like first it's, I don't know which planet is first, but some planet.
bruce	Mercury.
candice	Oh yeah, okay. So, um and then it's, um oh I can't draw 
bruce	It's very nice.
candice	And then, um, we're the third planet.
bruce	Yeah.
candice	Okay, and the second one is, um, which one's second one?
bruce	Venus.
candice	Okay  V and then us is earth.
bruce	Yeah.
candice	Yeah. 
bruce	Yeah, the third one is earth.
candice	And then us, earth.
bruce	Mhm.		
candice	And the other planets. And then like we're all revolving, like going around the sun.
bruce	Okay. So let's, let's see if we can use this now to help us come up with ways that it might be, you were saying in the summer that the sun is closer.
candice	  Or maybe we're closer to the sun.
bruce	Okay.
candice	Yeah. Um,   I really don't know how that would happen. I think something like we're closer to the sun in the summer. 
bruce	So on your, on your drawing here I mean, like over here the earth is a little closer than it is over there. Is that just sort of an accident of how you drew it?
candice	Yeah 
bruce	So in, in reality would it sometimes be closer, or is it more of a perfect circle around the sun?
candice	I think it's sometimes closer to the sun like, you know, like wouldn't it revolves, like you know when we have four seasons right and so maybe at a point like it's, like the orbital is like farther or closer to the sun, um
bruce	So, just say that one more time 
candice	 Like so the orbiting, the orbital could be either closer or farther from the sun.
bruce	So what do you mean? You mean like sometimes this orbit might be bigger, or smaller, or might it be
candice	Like, like let's just say like over here it could be farther, and over here it could be closer.
bruce	Oh, okay, okay. So it's kind going around, and sometimes it's farther, and sometimes it's closer.
candice	Yeah.
bruce	Okay. So that makes sense as, as we've kind of worked out why, um, one explanation of the seasons, okay. That's a good job. We're on the right track, but there's um a problem with that explanation, um, and one, so have you ever heard that when it's winter here it can be summer in some other part of the earth?
candice	Yeah.
bruce	Um, so do you see that that poses a bit of a problem for this explanation?
candice	Yeah.
bruce	Can you, can you just say why? Just to say it out loud why it poses a problem?
candice	Because like, the world, the all the world can be like summer, some parts are like winter and some parts are like summer.
bruce	Right.
candice	And like some parts are like 
bruce	And, um, that's a problem for this explanation because   because here the whole earth is farther away.
candice	Yeah.
bruce	So can you think of any way out of this problem, or a way we can explain why when it's summer here it can be winter someplace else?
candice	um [
bruce	What are you thinking about?
candice	Um, I know that earth spins on an axis.
bruce	Hmm-mm. Mm. Okay.
candice	And I don't really know lik.
bruce	The spinning on an axis might help in some way.
candice	um, I don't know
bruce	So that might help, you're just not sure how? Okay [pause] Okay, well let's, let's come back to explaining summer winter in a second. Let me ask-  I'm going to ask you a couple of related questions. Um, so how about day and night? Do you know why, do you know why it's daytime sometimes and nighttime other times?
candice	Yeah because like earth spins around on an axis, and then like when it's day, like you know we're facing the sun, and when it's night we're facing like the other way.
bruce	Okay, so can you draw a picture of that?
candice	I think so , the sun, and then like, like this side of the earth is daylight, and this side is night.
bruce	Okay.
candice	So night, and then day.
bruce	Okay. And how is the earth moving?
candice	Like spinning around on an axis. Like, I think when it spins around one time it's like one day.
bruce	Okay, so I'm just trying to understand a little bit how, so let's say this is the sun , where, and where's the, let's make the earth somewhere, let's say this is the earth . So can you show me how the earth, so how is the earth.
candice	 Um, it moves around, and then one turn is a day.
bruce	Okay. And where is the daytime?
candice	Okay so if it's facing this way it's daytime over here  and then nighttime over here 
bruce	Okay. And then it spins around and
candice	Yeah,  and then like that 
bruce	Okay. Okay. So that's day and night. And how long does it take to go all the way around once?
candice	A year.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay. Um, alright, I just have one other, one last related question. Um, so we were talking about why it's, why it's warmer in Chicago sometimes in the, in the summer, and colder in Chicago in the winter. But there are some places that are like always hot like Florida, and some places that are like always pretty cold like Alaska. So why is that? Why are, why are some places hot like that and some places cold?
candice	Um, cause you know how like earth is spinning on an axis, so it's like tilted, and then like on the bottom, or like it's colder, I mean warmer, like towards, and then on the top it's colder, I think.
bruce	I think, I think that would help again to have a picture, so let's do a picture of that.
candice	Okay , the sun again, 
bruce	Okay. Another lovely sun.
candice	And then earth, and then it's like the axis is like tilted.
bruce	Uh- uh.
candice	And then, so the sun is shining, and then this part is warmer and this part is colder.
bruce	Okay, where's, so where's Florida?
candice	Down here.
bruce	Okay, just put a little dot, a big, a nice big dot for Florida. And where's Alaska?
candice	Alaska? I think it would be around like up here somewhere.
bruce	Okay, so somewhere up near the top?
candice	Yeah.
bruce	Okay, and on the other side too, or?
candice	The other side?
bruce	Well I just, you put it like here, I was just wondering if you might have put it there. But, like, is it 
candice	Yeah.
bruce	It could have been there? 
candice	Mm.
bruce	Okay. And it's, and why is it warmer down here?
candice	Because, it's like this part is kind of closer to the sun than this part.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
