<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>caitlin</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Um, okay, so my first question is, why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
caitlin	Uh, I think its because like the tilt of the earth, it tilts away and from the sun.
bruce	Mhm.
caitlin	And
bruce	So, how does that work?
caitlin	Like this is - this is the sun  and like this is the earth  and the sun always stays here, but the earth goes around like this , but it also tilts, so if this is like the northern hemisphere 
bruce	Here you wanna Yeah, okay, go ahead, that's fine.
caitlin	And then its like, here's us right there , and if its like if this if its going around like this  or if its going around like this  then we get we don't get as much direct sunlight so then it's colder, but then when it goes like this  we get more direct sunlight, so it's warmer.
bruce	Okay, could you draw a picture of that? I think I got what you were saying, but.
caitlin	Okay.
bruce	It would help me to have, may help me to have a picture. Here use the black one.
caitlin	Okay. Well, here's us on the earth , and here's where we live, here's the hemisphere  well actually that's kind of lopsided, but then here's south America  and here's north America , and if this is the sun .
bruce	Nice sun.
caitlin	Thanks. I always draw my suns with sunglasses .
bruce	
caitlin	Um, uh, then this is going around  but it's tilting back and forth also like this . And so its like, when it's tilted like that  the southern hemisphere is kind of in the dark.
bruce	Mhm.
caitlin	Not really in the dark though, cause it takes I think a long time for it to go around.
bruce	Mhm.
caitlin	Ya.
bruce	What's a long time?
caitlin	Um, well I'm really not sure right now that's why I said a long time. But it's either one day, oh wait no the earth spins itself like this  like .
bruce	
caitlin	And when the earth is spinning
bruce	Uh-huh.
caitlin	But it's like really fast, but it's also really slow.
bruce	Uh-huh.
caitlin	So when it's going around the sun like in the day.
bruce	Mhm.
caitlin	I'm going to make a diagram. 
bruce	 okay.
caitlin	If you're the sun, its going like this  and if we're over here then its night, and when its over here where its day. Cause it's light out.
bruce	Okay.
caitlin	And that's why the sunrises in the  east I think. Yes, no, the east  cause the sun rises over the lake that's why I never see the sunset because it sets over by California.
bruce	Okay. But, let's get back to why it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter.
caitlin	Oh, ya.
bruce	So, so its sort of doing this tilting back and forth thing.
caitlin	Yeah, but while its spinning, its also kind a like going on axises.
bruce	Mhm.
caitlin	Around the sun.
bruce	You mean it's wobbling back and forth, is that what you mean. No?
caitlin	Well, I don't know if it's wobbling.
bruce	Okay.
caitlin	It's not wobbling.
bruce	No. Okay.
caitlin	I don't really know because I don't really like astronomy.
bruce	Mhm.
caitlin	But, I think I saw this on some tv show once. So, but I'm just trying to remember what I saw.
bruce	Mhm.
caitlin	 Yes.
bruce	So it has, so, so wait, lets, lets just focus on, so there's us in Chicago .
caitlin	Mhm.
bruce	Okay, so what's. Is it summer or winter in this picture in Chicago the way you drew it.
caitlin	Well, if this, I think its summer. Wait, actually Chicago is kind of like over here  so since its kind of tilted a little bit that says its summer, if it was going that way, then it was winter. See, then it goes like this shhwh.
bruce	Okay, so could you, so this is, so where would we be if it was, if it was
caitlin	Summer? Winter?
bruce	Yeah, winter.
caitlin	 there's us.
bruce	Okay. And this summer we're here .
caitlin	We're moving around the sun and this is winter see, this is fall , fall, winter, spring, summer .
bruce	And, what, what's different here that is making it summer? 
caitlin	 This side of the earth is facing the sun, instead of on the other side .
bruce	Oh wait though this is winter right.
caitlin	No, this is summer.
bruce	Oh, this is summer, okay. And it's summer because this side is
caitlin	We're closer. See it's going like this . And also, I'm really am not really sure about this.
bruce	I'm more trying to wor
caitlin	I get confused with days, and years, and months.
bruce	Okay.
caitlin	But, not like in the real world, like in astronomy.
bruce	 In real life you know the difference between a year and a day?
caitlin	Yes.
bruce	So, I'm just trying to, so, but lets just work, think it through together a little bit now, so, so you're saying the earth is, lets say this is the earth , so lets say this is the sun  and this is the earth , and okay so, lets say, so is it summer or winter now.
caitlin	Well it depends where you are.
bruce	Okay, well lets say in Chicago.
caitlin	Well if this is Chicago then no , but if this is Chicago then yes .
bruce	Okay where it, if, oh if Chicago is
caitlin	Pointing towards the sun.
bruce	I see. If Chicago's pointing toward the sun. And, where would the north pole, where's the eq, north pole and south pole you think?
caitlin	North pole  wait, no, if this is Chicago  this is the north pole , this is Chicago , this is the south pole , and this is the equator  this thing.
bruce	Okay. And this is, and this is, summer or winter I forgot, if it's like this.
caitlin	Well, if it's like this it's winter , and if it's like this it's summer .
bruce	Okay. Okay, and how is the earth look now, make the earth move how how it would usu how it would move?
caitlin	Well it's not a sphere. Can I use this?
bruce	Yeah, you can use that.
caitlin	
bruce	Going like that. Okay, and where are the north pole and south pole on that? Could we put dots for them or something.
caitlin	This would be the north pole .
bruce	Okay.
caitlin	And this would be the south pole .
bruce	Okay.
caitlin	Can you see those?
bruce	We'll remember.
caitlin	Okay. 
bruce	Okay.
caitlin	There always staying. You can't, you don't know that this is happening, this is just what, right now were moving so fast, but we're just used to it.
bruce	Uh-huh.  So the, so what the poles are kind of, it's flip flopping like this, sometimes the north pole's up and sometimes.
caitlin	Actually, that doesn't really sound right.
bruce	Okay.
caitlin	I'm, hmm, do you have another question?
bruce	Okay. But that's the I, I'm just trying to understand what you meant.
caitlin	Yes.
bruce	So I do have, so, so.
caitlin	My point is just that the tilt of the earth is showing which way the seasons are.
bruce	Okay.
caitlin	And when its closer that means the sun is closer, so the rays can come to you and you can get a sun tan. And when you're in Florida, it's closer to the equator, and the equator always has direct sunlight.
bruce	Okay, so why. So that was another question I wanted to ask you
caitlin	Oh, wait, actually I know it goes like this , instead of like this , it goes like this .
bruce	Okay. So now how do you get the seasons then, if its going like this  if its spinning like this? You have it, now you kind of have it twirling around its axis.
caitlin	Yeah, its like sheeeww, sheeew, sheeew . But it's going one way. Night's, and then you come around here , and  as you , ewwww, I think as you get closer to the sun.
bruce	What do you get closer to?
caitlin	The sun, the earth goes closer to the sun because right now in Australia it's like almost, its almost winter, when here its almost summer, well actually its not almost summer its in the middle, it's the end of winter, right now it's the end of summer.
bruce	In, um
caitlin	Australia.
bruce	In Australia, yeah.
caitlin	See, they're down here  and we're up here , and it's summer down here  because I don't know.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	 Well, you kind of explained it. So, let me ask you my other question now, okay?
caitlin	Yes.
bruce	So, we talked about why it's sometimes warmer in Chicago and sometimes colder in Chicago, but you started to say there are some places like Florida that are always hot, and some places like Alaska that are always cold.
caitlin	I'm going to Florida, next Wednesday.
bruce	You are lucky.
caitlin	Actually, next Thursday.
bruce	For spring break?
caitlin	Yes, for spring break. And we're leaving a couple of days early.
bruce	You are lucky. I wish I were going.
caitlin	I know. But
bruce	So, why is that Florida is always warm?
caitlin	It's always warm because it is closer to the equator.
bruce	And why does that make it warm.
caitlin	Because the sunlight is always direct on the equator, see .  When this it has to ta it goes, see. Oh, I know! I need a new paper.
bruce	Okay.	
caitlin	Okay, this is going to be the sun here . And this is the earth . Here is the equator . And the sun's rays go onto the equator  like that. See that.
bruce	Uh-huh .
caitlin	Then here's a North America . 
bruce	Uh-huh.
caitlin	And the sun's rays have to go like  The sun's rays, see there the strongest when they go right down the middle they can go straight without breaking, so the light rays don't have break.
bruce	When they go there? What do you mean they don't have to break?
caitlin	Like  if I was to run, wait if - hmm, uh, okay see this .
bruce	Mhm.
caitlin	Actually I gotta do this. So this is like, if this is the equator , and I'm the sun, and I have to hit this pen at the equator, uh, it's easier for me to just go like this  than if the northern hemisphere I have to go like this and on a diagonal .
bruce	Oh.
caitlin	So it takes longer for the sun rays. Actually it doesn't take - It's easier for the sun rays to go straight to the middle . Like, scheeww . Instead of, schhheee . Like if you're running, if there's like a course of running , and you have to go like this  that's a farther distance than it is going like this . 
bruce	I see. And because it's a farther distance
caitlin	It, the sun, the rays aren't so violent.
bruce	Okay.
caitlin	Uh-huh.
bruce	Okay. So it's because they have to travel a farther distance?
caitlin	Yes.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
