<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>cassandra</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS> 
bruce	Okay. We've got good sound? Okay. So my first question is, um, why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
cassandra	Because, the, um, the earth moves around , and then make the temperature change.
bruce	And how does it moving around?
cassandra	Move around by the sun, and sometimes it's by the sun. When it's by the sun then it's hot, and sometimes not. Sometimes it's not by the sun, and it's not hot.
bruce	Okay. Can you just draw a picture of that for me? Of what you just said, since you were just sort of tracing it out there on the table.  It doesn't matter what color.
cassandra	Okay . This is the earth,
bruce	Mhm.
cassandra	Okay, oh yeah, wait, hmm, no that's the sun
bruce	Okay 
cassandra	This is the earth.
bruce	Okay.
cassandra	And it goes around, around, around, around, around the sun.
bruce	Mhm. And
cassandra	Like that. So yeah.
bruce	And how does that make it summer and winter again?
cassandra	When it's like, in different parts sometimes it's summer sometimes it's winter. So in this part of earth, see it's facing the sun there?
bruce	Mhm
cassandra	Then that means it's summer. And when it turns, and that means it's summer there, and summer there, and summer there.
bruce	Okay so, so it's, when it's summer in, when it's summer here it might be winter someplace else?
cassandra	Yeah.
bruce	Um, is that different than what you were saying a moment ago before I asked you to draw a picture?
cassandra	I don't know 
bruce	You're not sure? Okay. So let's say, let's say it's summer here in Chicago right now. Okay, so can you show me where we'd be, and what it would look like?
cassandra	Chicago would be right here.
bruce	Okay, and then what would it look like when it's winter in Chicago?
cassandra	 
bruce	So the earth would be in another place?
cassandra	And it turns.
bruce	Okay, um, so you think that maybe the earth, so what's happened between here and here? The earth is
cassandra	It turned like that, and it got there.
bruce	So is it spinning like this, and moving around the sun at the same time?
cassandra	Mhm.
bruce	Okay, um, and, okay.  And so here it's winter, and can you, where would it, where do you think we, it would look like when it's fall in?
cassandra	 
bruce	So, so why is that fall?
cassandra	Wait no, not that side, this side. Cause it's kind of warmer in the fall time.
bruce	Okay.
cassandra	No, no, no this is spring, that is fall, that's fall.
bruce	Okay, where, and the earth would be maybe over here. So on here, summer is on this side of the sun
cassandra	Mhm.
bruce	And we said this is fall and the earth would be over here?
cassandra	Mhm.
bruce	Okay. Um, okay good. And, so, let me bring in something else now. Um, so I wonder if you could talk a little bit about how day and night work? So sometimes
cassandra	Oh. Oh yeah, but mhm, okay. 
bruce	Does that matter, what are you thinking now, does that matter?
cassandra	Because I forgot about day and night, so. Okay. The earth when it's day, is by, you can see the sun, when it's night you can see the moon.
bruce	So what, what causes so it to be day?
cassandra	It spins. The earth spins, and that make it day. Like some places it's day, some places night. So if it's day here, then it's night over there. So yeah.
bruce	Okay, um, but how, so how does that fit with what you were saying about the seasons?
cassandra	I don't know, I forgot about day and night when I said about the seasons. 
bruce	Mhm.
cassandra	So I don't know. 
bruce	So does that, does that pose a problem for your explanation of the seasons.
cassandra	Mhm.
bruce	Can you just explain what the, what the problem is?
cassandra	Cause it has to be by the sun to be day, but also it can't be the sun all the time in the. Okay, it can't be, the sun, the sun can't be always on this part of the earth all day, so how is it summer? I don't know, I'm just confused.
bruce	Okay. So it's, it's kind of a problem because you were saying this is summer and this is winter, but then you were also saying this is daytime and this is nighttime. 
cassandra	Yeah, mhm.
bruce	So it can't be like it's daytime all summer long and nighttime all winter long. 
cassandra	Yeah.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay. Um, so we'll, we're going to come back to this in a minute, and I'll, I'll show you how to, how to actually, how you actually resolve that problem, but I want to ask you one, one other question before, before we do that. Um, so we talked about why it, you know, in the summer it's warm here in Chicago, in the winter it's cold here in Chicago. But there are some places that are generally hot like Florida, and some places that are generally all the time kind of cold, like Alaska. So why is that, why is Florida? 
cassandra	Cause, um like in the south, down the south, by where Florida and Mississippi, and all those states, then it's um, hot. Then the north, and I don't really know why, but  yeah, I just know that it is.
bruce	So you just know that places further south are hot? Okay. And, let's say, uh, do you have a guess as to why it might be?
cassandra	Maybe because, maybe it's closer to the sun sometimes. Or maybe because at the bottom, the sun's not as cold.
bruce	Mhm. Maybe  say that, so say that again.
cassandra	Maybe it's because at the bottom, it's not that cold. Like bottom of the United States. So, so yeah.
bruce	Do you not, but you don't know why it's not as cold down there?
cassandra	Nope.
bruce	How about if you go, like um, you keep going down, like let's say you go to the, go down by the equator, is it pretty hot there?
cassandra	Isn't that where, um, at the bottom, is Alaska at the bottom or at the top?
bruce	Alaska is kind of up at the top of the United States.
cassandra	Oh, and Hawaii is at the bottom?
bruce	Um, Hawaii is, is further south and kind of out to the
cassandra	Yeah, um I don't know. If here, I guess it's kind of hot down there cause that's where every, all the hot states are.
bruce	Okay. How about down like at the South Pole?
cassandra	It's cold there,  ? Maybe if you keep going down, down, down, down, down it'll be cold because it's almost to the top. I think.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
