<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>caden</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Um, so let's just get started and you'll get, you'll get the idea. So the first question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
caden	Because at certain points of the earth's rotation, orbit around the sun, the axis is pointing at an angle, so that sometimes, most times, sometimes on the northern half of the hemisphere is closer to the sun than the southern hemisphere, which, change changes the temperatures. And then, as, as it's pointing here, the northern hemisphere it goes away, is further away from the sun and get's colder.
bruce	Okay, so how does it, sometimes the northern hemisphere is, is toward the sun and sometimes it's away?
caden	Yes because the at - I'm sorry, the earth is tilted on its axis.
bruce	Uh uh.
caden	And it's always pointed towards one position 
bruce	Mhm.
caden	And it rotates like  can I put this in diagrams-ish ?
bruce	Yeah. That's why this is here.
caden	Okay.
bruce	Here, you can use this one.
caden	Thank you. It's okay if I get some on the table?
bruce	Definitely.
caden	Okay. Here's the sun, and the earth, here's the, and here's just like an equator, here's the northern hemisphere, here's the southern hemisphere
bruce	Mhm.
caden	Now, um, I'm sorry it's actually  here's the sun, here's the earth, here's the northern hemisphere, here's the southern hemisphere. It's closer to here, the sun rays are closer to get closer to the northern half. When it's over here, the sun's rays are farther, have to travel farther, and therefore there are less rays and it gets colder.
bruce	And the earth is kind of going around like that .
caden	Mhm. Kind of circular .
bruce	Mhm. Okay. Um, so the way you drew this, did you try to draw it to-scale?
caden	I did not. Otherwise the - it would just like be a little dot.
bruce	What, what would it look like if you tried to draw it to scale?
caden	I will drawing it, okay.  Probably be about that.
bruce	Okay, so this, this distance
caden	No, not, not even distance wise. Maybe  even, I'm guessing billion plus miles.
bruce	Uh-uh.
caden	I'll add the little
bruce	And how big is this , how big is the earth?
caden	I do not know for a fact.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay, um,  okay, good. Um, what else did I want to ask you? So we just talked about why, why it's winter sometimes and summer sometimes, but there are also some places that are generally hotter and generally colder, like in Alaska it's generally pretty cold, and Florida it's generally pretty hot.
caden	Mhm.
bruce	So why is that?
caden	Because you're closer to the equator, and the equator is just in a general,  instead of tilting like, we're here, so we have a bigger movement around, like sometimes we're further up, sometimes we're further down. And Florida is more towards the equator, the equator kind of stays like a close distance to these rays, about the same distance approximately.
bruce	Mhm. So the equator, the equator is closer to the sun?
caden	Mhm. When it gets, when it gets closer in the southern hemisphere, that includes, that includes the tropics around the equator, the, Flor Florida is quite close to the equator. 
bruce	Okay.
caden	Not perfectly close. I know it's actually, has to pass through Mexico, Gulf of Mexico, parts of the Pacific Ocean, Caribbean.
bruce	What has to pass through there?
caden	Like uh, no, like as a diagram, like it's actually not really close to the equator, but it's closer than we are, so
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
