<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>elesha</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	So,  my first question is, why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
elesha	Um, its warmer in the summer and colder in the winter because the world um revolves along like like day and night, when it turns up and it turns down, so at that point um we're not as closest to the sun, I'm guessin', we're not as closer to the sun um during the winter time than um the summer time, but in other places it's near the  I don't know what its called, I forgot, but its like a line, that basically separates the top and the bottom, and
bruce	The equator?
elesha	The equator, yes.
bruce	Okay.
elesha	And at that point a lot of places are are warmer near the middle all the time because it's not really moving much, when it's tilting. And, then like, and um, Antarctica and places like that it's so far away that it's um it's colder there all the time.
bruce	Okay.
elesha	
bruce	Let's. I got most of that, not a hundred percent. So I want could we just pick one place. Let's, let's just talk about Chicago.
elesha	Okay.
bruce	And tell me why it's warmer in the summer here and colder in the winter just here in Chicago.
elesha	Um, well, it's warmer in the summer because it's closer to the sun.
bruce	Uh-huh.
elesha	And its colder in the winter because at that point, um  the, um, the world has rotated to a point where it's farther away from the sun which makes it colder.
bruce	Okay, so can  you show me with your hands a little bit, , like that's say this is the sun. And, so where's the earth and where are we in the
elesha	 Okay so, if this, if you are the sun
bruce	This is the sun
elesha	And then, this, well, can I use this .
bruce	Sure.
elesha	You're the sun, and this is the world  and as it's rotating  it's goin' farther away  farther away, and when its coming closer and, I don't really know how to show it with a
bruce	So, wait, where, so where are we
elesha	We 
bruce	 Lets say this is the, well let me be the earth and the sun. So here's the earth.
elesha	This is the sun , this is the earth , and we are here  at this point
bruce	Where, where are you pointing to.
elesha	And, so we're closer to the sun, and
bruce	Maybe you should use your own hands.
elesha	I don't know how to
bruce	 okay.
elesha	how to, how to explain it. I don't really know.
bruce	Okay.
elesha	It's kind of harder.
bruce	Can we try it with a picture?
elesha	Okay.
bruce	 So lets, lets do the same thing but lets, lets see if we can do it better with the picture.
elesha	Okay, so, this is the sun , and this is the earth ,
bruce	
elesha	and then like I guess that point 
bruce	Okay, so where, lets do us.
elesha	Well  and then at this point, if we're here , well if we're here  back here then I guess we're kind of like farther away, and then as it rotates we get closer well because  I don't know it rotates it revolves , so it kind of rotates not only like this way , but, well, the sun revolves around the I don't know. One of them rotate.
bruce	Okay. W- W- W- 
elesha	I just go off of memory.
bruce	Okay. So wait which is -  you're saying rotate and revolve. Just what's the difference?
elesha	Well , like, one like goes like , it'll go , like this , and then the other goes like this , so its going like this .
bruce	So it's going all the way around the sun , and also sort of going like that .
elesha	Yeah.
bruce	Okay. Uhm.
elesha	Which makes day and night, and then
bruce	Which makes day and night?  Just this one.
elesha	Yeah.
bruce	Okay.
elesha	I think that one makes day and night  and then this one  changes the seasons.
bruce	Oh, this one changes the seasons .
elesha	Yeah.
bruce	Okay.
elesha	I believe so. I'm not sure. 
bruce	Um, so let's say, so can we draw a picture that shows when it's summer in Chicago and winter in Chicago. So let's say, let's draw the sun again.
elesha	I don't know!
bruce	Okay, so you're.
elesha	I'm not really sure. I just know that I think it goes like that. But I don't really like at what point the sun and the earth is um  at what point it's um it's farther away that it becomes colder, where it changes the season. So, I'm not really sure.
bruce	Mhm . And you're saying its colder because the whole earth is farther away or.
elesha	Well, at that point wherever we are, we're farther away.
bruce	I see.
elesha	Because at that point, it could be like, we're  we could be, it could be cold here and warm somewhere else.
bruce	Okay.
elesha	But, I don't know. Because in Africa it's hot majority of the time, which would mean , I don't know.
bruce	What are you thinking now.
elesha	Now cause I'm thinking like bec-  if it's colder, I mean if it's hot, um, hot, majority of the time in Africa the rotation like this  would be the most logical reason why it would um  why it would still be hot because its near the equator, and since its rotating like this  even though, you see what I'm saying, so
bruce	I think so, just, just keep, keep talking.
elesha	Even though um, its going like this  it's not really leaving that hot point, but the other places, near the top or the bottom, it's gonna to be cold because its never leaving that cold point.
bruce	Okay.
elesha	So then, something else is rotating them like this , but I'm not really sure what that is.
bruce	What do you mean something else is rot
elesha	Something rotates around, but I'm not really sure. But. So that's the reason because the rotation is like this  I believe. So that's why sometime the season, when the season changes, um, I guess when it rotates this way , it's moves back and around. I'm not sure             
bruce	So you're saying
elesha	
bruce	The earth is sort of going around like this .
elesha	yeah.
bruce	Okay, lets say, let's say, it's like this . And
elesha	And we are, where are we, here?
bruce	Yeah.
elesha	Okay, then that would mean that it's, it's, wintertime I think.
bruce	Okay, and why is that?
elesha	Because at that point, its farther away
bruce	Lets say this is the sun.
elesha	Oh that's the sun, okay then, I'm sorry, then it's summer time
bruce	Okay.
elesha	Because its closer.
bruce	And then, what would it look like when its winter?
elesha	When its winter , it would have rotated like this because its because it's  back.
bruce	Okay, so it's all because of this sort of  leaning closer and farther.
elesha	I think so.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay, um, cool. Um, so now I want to, I was trying to stop you for a while from talking about different places on the earth but now I want to talk a little about different places.
elesha	Okay.
bruce	So were talking about why, it's gener, its warmer here in the summer, just in Chicago, and colder in the winter, um, but some places like you said like Florida are always pretty hot, some places Alaska are always pretty cold, so why is that?
elesha	I think that's because um they're closer to the equator because it's like a zero line pretty much and at that point it's like it really doesn't move when because if it if the rotation is  this way, then it's really not moving from the distance isn't really changing much
bruce	Mhm.
elesha	Which would make it hot majority of the time.
bruce	Mhm.
elesha	And then in places like Alaska and things like that it's closer, I mean it's farther away from the sun by so much that it's generally cold all the time.
bruce	Mhm.
elesha	So that's what I think.
bruce	So could you try to draw a picture of that, just as another way to show it.
elesha	 um, well, this is the earth  at the rotation, and this is the sun , if something is here  then it really doesn't, well, I don't know its not really either 
bruce	Maybe draw . Sorry go ahead. I was gonna say put a, you can start over if you want.
elesha	Okay, well. You want me to get another sheet.
bruce	Sure.
elesha	Hmm. Okay, so I'll just draw the earth first , this is the earth and this is the equator . And then the sun is like  I don't know how to make a circle tilted.
bruce	How to make a circle tilted?
elesha	Yeah.
bruce	Usually what I do is I just draw the line that it rotates around in an angle like that .
elesha	So if  if
bruce	Yeah, sorry.
elesha	Yeah.
bruce	Or if you make the equator tilted too .
elesha	Okay. So. This will just be the sun then .
bruce	Okay. 
elesha	 And then if this is the earth , and it's like the equator is like this  and we're here  then, we're getting that sun, but other places here  aren't getting the sun and here  aren't getting much sun here either, but places here and here  things like that, they're getting the same amount pretty much because I mean it does change but not as dramatically as places here and here and here  because at that point its changing so that's why it creates the seasons. They get less seasons here  because of it.
bruce	It's changing because the earth is kind of going like this .
elesha	Exactly.
bruce	And these points in the middle kind of stay in the same place all of the time.
elesha	I think so, yeah.
00:13:16 
bruce	Okay.  Okay! Oh, and the  okay, I think I got it.
elesha	Okay.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
