<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>harmony</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	So first question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
harmony	Because the, um, the earth’s axis is on a tilt, and during the summer days it stays more to the sun, so it’s more direct to the sun, and the heat transfers to the earth and heats the, goes to the atmosphere to heat the earth. While in the winter months it’s turned away, the axis is more, like, well for the United States it’s turned away from the sun and it’s colder.
bruce	Okay. Um, can you show me a little bit with your hands? So let’s say this is the sun  could you maybe use your hand and show me where  so let’s say that’s the earth. Okay, and where are we?
harmony	Um, well I’m not sure, but probably closer to the sun, so like around here 
bruce	Like, so where on 
harmony	We’re like probably, around like say my fist the earth, and we’re- your fist is the sun, we’d probably be right here 
bruce	Okay. And then that’s summer.
harmony	Mhm.
bruce	Okay, and what about winter?
harmony	Probably like, I don’t think the earth moves exactly, but maybe when it’s, um moving the axis is tilted a little bit so we’d be closer to the sun, it would be like a little farther away tilted.
bruce	Okay. Okay, I think I get it, but let’s try a picture. Okay? So let’s draw the sun and the earth then. Just what you said before, but just with a drawing.
harmony	 that’s number one . That’s the earth, and like the sun, and it’s like towards the sun more, like say this is the  face of the earth or something. And it’s closer to the sun during summer, while in the winter, it’s probably like say the face is maybe around here or something and the sun is still right there.
bruce	Okay.
harmony	And, I’m not sure—I’m not a very good drawer, maybe that’s why, but I’m trying to say like, okay  the earth’s axis is tilted. 
bruce	Mm-hmm.
harmony	Well where the United States is anyway.
bruce	 What, so what’s the axis? Can you put the axis on your drawing?
harmony	The axis is like, um, what the earth, I’m not sure.
bruce	Uhuh.
harmony	I can’t really draw it and neither. Can I explain it?
bruce	Sure, sure.
harmony	Well to explain it, okay, so here’s the earth, and then it’s like how like where everything is like longitude and latitude. So say, and, so say the southern hemisphere, cause africa’s southern too and it’s colder there all the time. So say Africa has kind of hot year round is like always faced toward the sun while the United States, or it’s able to like be on the earth’s axis, and like during different seasons while the world is spinning around like the weather changes. 
bruce	Hm-mm.
harmony	So, yeah  it’s hard to explain because the weather is different because of global warming and the carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.
bruce	Mhm. So can we pick just one place? Let’s just talk about just Chicago and just the United States.
harmony	Mm-hm.
bruce	So you’re saying
harmony	It’s able to experience seasons because, since the earth is moving on an axis. Since the earth is constantly in motion with the sun, it’s able to, like the 365-day period is broken down into seasons, and that season can be a trial period where the earth is where it is direct toward the sun. So like during the summer months and spring, like spring is getting closer to the sun, summer is like right there where you can experience a lot of heat, while in fall it’s going away from the sun, and in winter it’s like, further from the sun.
bruce	The earth is further from the sun or?
harmony	USA.
bruce	The USA.
harmony	Yeah, it’s cause the earth is spinning and it’s like how the earth where the earth is, and how we’re experiencing it 
bruce	Where the earth is and how
harmony	The earth doesn’t move, it doesn’t walk away to the left and right. It spins in motion, just like how could have a, um, the jacks and stuff and I could spin it but it stays in place it’s just spinning, that’s how the earth is. So the earth is spinning and where the United States is, during summer the earth is spun closer to the sun, while during winter is spun farther away where the United States is.
bruce	Okay, so the earth, the earth is, here’s the sun and here’s the earth 
harmony	Right
bruce	And the earth is just spinning like this. Is it moving in any other way, or does it just stand in this spot and spin
harmony	Mhm.
bruce	Okay. So it’s sitting here and it’s spinning, and so um, in the -  yeah  a new sheet  
harmony	 
bruce	oh that’s the sun, okay.
harmony	When this is in the direction, the little cap thingy, so during this time it’s facing right here it’s spinning and it’s the fall, that’s the direction is for the sun. And then it spins to the right and its’ at the winter, and it’s the earth spinning, and then it spins where summer’s gotten closer to the sun, it spins and goes again, it does another 90-degree spin to the summer, a 90-degree spin to the spring, and that was just the whole year on earth. And then it starts again with the seasons fall, winter, summer, spring. And all those seasons when it goes by say like it goes back to fall again, that was just one year, for Earth
bruce	Okay, I see. So the earth is like right here and like let’s say we’re right here we’re facing
harmony	We’re in winter now, and as you see winter is farther away  away from the sun. Like. Not  say the sun, so this is the United States experiencing winter. While, um, let’s see, Japan was somewhere or the Philippines could be experiencing spring.
bruce	Uhuh
harmony	So now as we move to summer, the United States experiences summer while the Philippine- Phillipines could be experiencing fall.
bruce	Okay
harmony	We move to spring United States is experiencing spring, 
bruce	Hmm-mm
harmony	Philippines is experiencing winter. 
bruce	Hmm-mm.
harmony	We move to fall, the United States is experiencing fall, the Philippines are experiencing summer. And this is because the direction of the United States when it faces the earth, and we just did one year.
bruce	Okay. So a lot of things I liked about your explanation.  I like how you’re explaining that you know why when it’s winter here it could be summer somewhere else, which is an important thing to take into account. But I want to throw in a complication now. So I wonder if you can work into your explanation some, some explanation of of day and night. Why it’s dark during the night, and light during the day.
harmony	Mm-hmm.
bruce	How could you work that in?
harmony	Okay. So as seen in winter, the nights are longer because it gets colder and we does, we do not see that much of the sun, while in Philippines it’s spring and they have regular days and night, like how all the sudden the think you gonna set your clocks. Now the United States goes to summer, we’re closer to the sun, so now we have longer, no we have shorter nights and longer days, and how the horizon and it gets dark and darker around eight o’clock, while in winter it get’s dark around 4:30 and 5. We move to spring, the spring and summer are the same thing, but since spring, can a draw another graph? 
bruce	Yeah.
harmony	 It’s the same thing, I’m just placing the seasons differently . That looks like an “A”.
bruce	I can figure it out.
harmony	Fall
bruce	Okay.
harmony	Spring. Let’s say we begin in fall 
bruce	Mhm. So you’re explaining why we have longer days in the winter, in the summer than in the winter, is that right? So, what I’m wondering is like how, you know, like every, what makes it dark during the nighttime and light during the day, so over like, even just in, in one day it changes from dark to light.  
harmony	Because the earth is in constant motion, so it’s like, so it turns the days are shortened because like that’s when the Earth is – that’s when the United States, well Chicago is not exactly in front of the sun, and that’s when the moon comes out.
bruce	Okay. So let’s just say it’s today. 
harmony	Right.
bruce	Okay, and it’s light time right now, so how, and then, so what’s happening right, how’s it going to be night in a little, what’s going to change to make it night in a little while?
harmony	Okay. Say that again.
bruce	 Okay. So let’s say, so, let’s say it’s daytime, and let’s say it’s winter now so we’re over, oh no we’re winter which means, so let’s say its daytime. Where would we be?
harmony	In winter?
bruce	Yeah.
harmony	That, I’ll have to draw another graph to, but I’d rather explain it. So, since the sun unfortunately is only maybe able to make, um, like say in the summer the sun is able to make extended, uh appearances on the earth, while in the winter those appearances are shortened because it has to go to the Philippines. So, that breaks down the day period into, the sun is like, um, well okay, so the sun is showing when there is day. Like I guess that’s how light comes into the atmosphere into the sky, and then since it’s, when it’s colder you usually see less sun and night comes.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay. I want to ask you one last question, um, and so we’ve talked, we talked about day and night, we’ve talked about why it’s summer and warm sometimes in Chicago and winter and cold sometimes in Chicago, but there are some places that are always pretty warm like Florida, and some places that are always pretty cold like Alaska. So why is that?
harmony	Because of where it’s at on the, okay, so this gonna make me think about, um, like the, I think tectonic plates on the earth and where it’s positioned, cause like how they, like how the earthquake in Haiti there like, the United States is not just the United States tectonic plate, it’s like the pacific plate and stuff, and California is like really not with the United States, it’s with the pacific plate. So like what is face on the earth, that’s where it was, and I think Florida is kind of near the South American plate kind of, and that’s where it’s warm at. So Florida is going to experience more warmth because that’s where it is on the face of the earth. An I guess because sunlight comes in and under that tectonic plate it traps more heat.
bruce	Okay. So it, somehow the southern tectonic plate traps more heat?
harmony	Not that exactly, that’s kinda like a twist of words, but I guess because of where Florida is on the earth, like where the different places is on the earth, that’s what they experience more. Cause like I also see the United States, a like the United states it experience one type, like not all places in the united states experience Chicago weather. There are different types of weather and that’s because where they’re at on the face of the earth. Even though we’re the United States, we’re still different locations of the face of the earth. So as Florida is in the southern part of the United States, it’s kind of near the southern part of the earth, and you know we say the south is warmer and stuff. So where it’s at on the face of the earth, it’s warmer.
bruce	Yeah. So that makes total sense, I was just wondering why, why being, why are parts of the southern, why are those southern parts of the earth warmer? So like why is, what’s a place that’s really hot, like the Sahara Desert or something, or. And that has something to do with the tectonic plates, or?
harmony	No
bruce	No?
harmony	Not exactly. Because if it has something to do with the tectonic plates, because like since earth used to be one mass continent, Pangea, then I guess like the whole weather’s probably the same. Then it broke, then like Pangea broke out into different places among the earth, so did they started to experience different types of weather. So it’s where you at or the position on the place of the earth, and where the sun is momentarily.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
