<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>holly</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	So my first hard question is, why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
holly	Because of the way the Sun rotates around the Earth. When it's on our side, it's warmer, and then when it's on the other side, it's colder. Although that might be day and night, but yeah, it has something to do with how the Sun and the earth rotate.
bruce	So show me, can you show me with your hands, you said, how the earth is
holly	So here's the Earth and then the Sun  rotates around it. And when it's on like this is our side. When it's on this side it's warmer, but when it goes away it gets colder.
bruce	So in the summer, can you leave your hands back up? So this is - this is winter  if we're on that side.
holly	Yeah.
bruce	And then there the Sun's around the other side.	
holly	And then now it's summer .
bruce	Okay. And why does being, why does being on this side  and the Sun over here why does that make it colder?
holly	Because you're further away from the Sun.
bruce	Can you just draw a picture of that now?
holly	Yeah.
bruce	You can use any one of these markers.
holly	I'll use green. 
bruce	I guess we can use that one. It might be too big.
holly	 That's the Earth. 
bruce	Very nice.
holly	My excellent drawing skills. 
bruce	Hm-mm.
holly	And then the Sun. And let's say we're right here. 
bruce	Hm-mm.
holly	When it's next to us it's warmer and then it rotates around and let's say when it's over here then it's colder because we're farther away.
bruce	Okay. And um. Okay. So it's the Earth - It's the Sun that goes around the Earth?
holly	Umm I think.  Yeah.
bruce	Okay. And what about um, um, other planets, do you know anything about other planets?
holly	I think all the, it's a big rotation. No! Not around the Earth! Wait. Yeah! It's a big rotation around each other, or the Earth. It's a big rotation. 
bruce	Uh-huh.
holly	The solar system.  And they all rotate and um makes different times. Yeah.
bruce	Okay, um, so you said something about day and night? So what were you starting to say about day and night before?
holly	I was thinking that day and night is also kind of like when it rotates, the Sun rotates around the Earth but I think it's not when it rotates around the Earth, per se, it's like when it rotates around the moon. I think. Not the moon. Like it doesn't go all the way around, it just kind of goes 
bruce	Mmm I don't get that part.
holly	It goes. It doesn't like - it rotates around - not the whole Earth. But like - No. Oh okay, so the sun - the Earth rotates around the Sun and the Sun also rotates around the Earth cause everything is rotating. When the Sun rotates around the Earth then that's day and night. But when the Earth rotates around the Sun, then that's different seasons.
bruce	Hmm. I guess I don't understand how they can rotate around they can both rotates around each other.
holly	 Like that.
bruce	So they're going like this?  They're both moving?
holly	Uh, well everything's in the solar system is always - not moving, but rotating.
bruce	Is rotating going around each other?
holly	I  yeah, maybe. Er, rotating also I think  like that. 
bruce	Oh so they're also spinning.
holly	Yeah, they're sp- they're always spinning.
bruce	Okay. So now, it seems like the spinning is something new you've introduced now  yeah? So let's just do day and night for a second. So can you explain to me how day and, day and night work, forgetting about the seasons for a moment?
holly	Uh, well, there's the Earth and there's the Sun. And the, and they rotate so when it's rotating and spinning, I think it rotates around the Earth so you can't, so it's night when it's not -
bruce	Can you draw me a picture of day and night? How day and night works? Maybe a picture during- when it's day for us and draw a picture when it's night.
holly	Like in solar systemal terms?
bruce	Yeah. Yeah.
holly	Okay.
bruce	Yeah.
holly	 So I think, I think it's kinda like there's moon and the Sun, and when it's day the Sun rotates to us and then when it's night the moon does.
bruce	And wh- So where is the, where is the Sun when it's night?
holly	The Sun goes where the moon was. They rotate around each other .
bruce	Okay. But why - why isn't the Sun making it light over here if it's just over there?
holly	I guess the Earth rotates too. Because th- like everything rotates around each other.
bruce	Okay. And. So is there any spinning going on here?
holly	Yeah, I think they all spin.
bruce	And does that does that affect day and night?
holly	Er, I know the Earth rotates and so, uh, oh the Earth rotates and so when the Sun is on the Er- when the Sun is shining on us, we're rotating. And so if it's shining here but then we're rotating so then it shines there and that's like time differences.
bruce	I see. Well so that seems a little bit different than the story you just told about the Sun and the moon. 
holly	Yeah.
bruce	Okay. So which one do you prefer?
holly	The second one.
bruce	Okay. So let's try to draw the second one right now.
holly	 Okay, so 
bruce	I'm going to mark this . This is your first drawing.  
holly	Not the most excellent artist. Okay. it's the Earth and the Earth is spinning. And then you have a Sun at a point, and let's say we're here. We're spinning. So when we're spinning, if we're on this side, we're farther away from the Sun so it's going to be nighttime. 
bruce	Okay. So it's farther away here and that's what makes it nighttime. And they were closer so it's daytime. Uh. And. Okay so that's day and night. Now let's, now let's do the seasons again.
holly	Okay. So the seasons are when the Sun rotates around the Earth, yeah. 
bruce	Okay.
holly	So when the Sun is going around the Earth. That's kind of like day and night it's the su- when we're farther away it makes it colder but it's more drastic because it's not um it's more of a drastic difference so it's
bruce	It's a more drastic difference than
holly	The Earth rotating around.
bruce	Why is it more drastic?
holly	Because it's farther away.
bruce	It's even - So let's say
holly	Because the Earth spins slowly. And I think the Sun goes quicker than the Earth. Slightly quicker because. Well no, I guess the Sun goes at the same time. But it's kind of like the Sun is the Earth is just spinning very slowly and the Sun is going very slowly but it corresponds.
bruce	So let me just ask you one last thing about this. So the, the sun, so draw where - what it looks like when it's summer, summer for us. Can you just draw summer?
holly	Summer for us would be  when the Sun is on our side.
bruce	Okay. And that's, is that summer daytime, or nighttime, or either.
holly	Uh I would say it would be daytime.
bruce	And what would summer nighttime look like then?
holly	Summer nighttime mmm  I guess, I'm kind of not good at three dimensionally, but if we're here, the Sun would slightly be like over here so it wouldn't be shining down directly down on us.
bruce	Oh so I see, so we've sort of, we've come around
holly	Yeah, we've spin -  The Sun like here but we're up there . I drew that kind of weird.
bruce	Okay. And that's nighttime.
holly	Yeah.
bruce	And if it was winter. Now what would it look like for us in winter?
holly	It would  be like that because the Sun is not near us.
bruce	And is it daytime or nighttime?
holly	Um. That's a good question.  I would say it'd be nighttime because we're not spinning close to the Earth. Earth. Er, to the sun.
bruce	It'd be nighttime? And what's it - what would daytime in the winter look like?
holly	
bruce	We're slightly closer but still, okay, okay I get it . Let me just. So this was two. And number three was this one?
holly	Yeah.
bruce	And then. Four was this one I think. Five. That's all I'm going to ask you about about the seasons. Now I want to ask you a related question. 
holly	Okay.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Um. So we've been talking about um the fact that it's - why it's warmer here in Chicago sometime and colder sometimes during the year. 
holly	Yeah.
bruce	Um. But also there are some places where it's always kind of generally warmer, like Alas- like Florida. And some places that it's always colder, like Alaska. So why is that? Why is Florida generally warm and Alaska generally hot?
holly	Cause it's closer to the Sun, er closer to the equator.
bruce	Okay. And why does being closer to the equator make it warmer?
holly	Um. I think because the Sun is always near it. Because the Sun spins around the Earth like this , so um the center of the Earth is the equator, so it's always right next to it.
bruce	Oh, okay I think I get it. Can you draw a picture of that?
holly	 So if this is the equator, the Sun is spinning around like this, so it's always next to the equator.
bruce	Okay. It's always-  So the Earth is like this 
holly	If the Earth is like this  and the equator is here, the Sun doesn't like move up or down, 
bruce	Uh-huh.
holly	It stays spinning around the equator . 
bruce	Okay. And why does that make the equator warmer again?
holly	Because it's closer to the Sun.
</CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay. Okay. Cool. Um. I just wanted to ask you generally about these pictures. I mean you were just sort of sketching it so you weren't trying to draw them perfectly.
holly	Yeah. 
bruce	But can is there anything you could tell me about what's sort of not perfect? Like did you make these roughly the right sizes, or did you try to get the distance from the Earth roughly to scale? 
holly	No. 
bruce	So what - what - how would it - if you tried to draw it to scale, how would it look different?
holly	To scale?
bruce	If you could try to draw it really so that, you're like, here you have the Sun smaller than the Earth, is that
holly	Well yeah, but I mean I think it'd have to be like more mathematically planned out if you wanted to draw it exactly to scale.
bruce	I'm just wondering about roughly.
holly	Uh yeah it would probably be more thought out about different sizes and angles and things.
bruce	Okay. But is the Sun the smaller than the Earth?
holly	Yeah.
bruce	And this is about, if the Earth was this big, the Sun would be, like here you have it that the Earth is this big, the Sun is just kind of up a little bit bigger than
holly	Well I don't think the Sun is necessarily that much smaller than the Earth, it just looks small from here because we're so far away. But I think it is slightly smaller.
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
