<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>kerri</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Okay. Um, so my first question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
kerri	Um, I think it's warmer in the summer because the Earth's axis is tilted more towards the Sun. So then the Sun, it gives off, like, then the Sun heat when we're tilted and we're facing the sun, it's the, like the rays it's just warmer cause it's kind of like closer to the sun. So it's warm during the summer because we're facing the sun and it's just like, yeah. It's facing the sun, and the axis is tilted kind of toward the sun, and then when it's winter, the Earth like the Earth turns around and the sun is a little farther away, the axis is tilted like a different way. And so the sun is not hitting it like directly. It's a little farther away, and it's hitting the, like North America, but not at the exact, uh angle as it would hit during the summer. So it's a little farther away, and it doesn't hit it on the angle of like, and it's not as close during the summer, so.
bruce	Okay. I think I get it, but could you draw a picture?
kerri	Sure. Okay, so here's like the sun. Okay, and during the summer, it's kinda,  the axis, and then you got all the things. The sun's light is hitting closer, and it's kind of like, say like we're right here
bruce	Hmm-mm.
kerri	It's kind of hitting us more directly.
bruce	Mhm. And that's summer you said?
kerri	Yeah. N-  I think I did it the opposite way.
bruce	Okay. I just -
kerri	Yeah s- . Yeah, so I think that would be the winter, and then  or I did it right the first time I'm not sure . And then the the Earth, when it rotates, it would be down, like more dow- more towards down here, and it would be kind of closer. So like say we're like right here. We, the sun it's coming directly toward us and we're like face the sun. And so the sun is kind of like closer in a way and it's facing directly towards us, and we are right there in front of the sun. And so it hits us directly and therefore it's warmer in the summer. And then here it's like a little bit and it has to travel kind of like on an angle so that when it hits us it's not so directly it's kind of like indirect. So then it's not as warm as it is in the summer.
bruce	Okay. And so this you said was winter?
kerri	Yeah.
bruce	And where are we?
kerri	Uh, we are like right in the middle  I don't know.
bruce	Right in the middle?
kerri	Yeah.
bruce	Okay. And so it's cold here because:::
kerri	The sun's not hitting it like directly as in the summer. And we're kind of like faced out and we're more  I don't know which way it is in the summer and in the winter, but we're more like either up or down, and not directly in the sun's path. But during the summer we're kind of like right in the middle on the side of the sun and so it's kind of like just straight out hit. And here like the sun, like if we were like right here during the summer, the sunlight would probably only hit like right here. So then the North Pole, it would be warmer there than it would be down in Antarctica  Antarctica  cause the sun would be hitting here and the light would like it would be on an angle so it would hit like here, here, here, but not so much at the bottom cause it's hitting the top like the top's just, so. Yeah, that's what I think of when I think of like the sun like the seasons, how it's like warmer and cold.
bruce	I most, so, I think you start to get at this, but have you heard that when it's summer here it's winter somewhere else?
kerri	Yes.
bruce	Okay. So does that fit with what you were just saying? 
kerri	Yeah, how like, yeah how the light is hitting here it's like summer up here and towards there, and then at the bottom it's winter. But then when you're over here and then the light's hitting the bottom, it's warm here and then colder up there.
bruce	Okay. So like right here you said it was, this is // summer 
kerri	// summer
bruce	In Chicago?
kerri	Yeah.
bruce	So where is it winter?
kerri	Like it could be winter on the on the other side. Or like, kinda, just like all around the edges but, and then I kind of like divide it, and be like this is like summer - spring, here like this is would be like the summer stuff, and here would be like spring and warm. And then here it would kinda be like fall and then there would be winter. Just like the way it get's like, the way it hits, it would not be like all different seasons it would just be kind of warmer and then cold.
bruce	Okay . So, I j- so one other piece I want to clarify now is just how, how the Earth is moving. So let's say this is the sun , and this is the Earth . Can you just show me how the Earth moves and maybe? 
kerri	The earth just moves like around and around the sun and it like as it moves it kinda, it tilts and it rotates . So it rotates and then it tilts and it rotates all around. And so the earth is rotating while it's revol- rev- it's doing a revolution around the sun. And so then, like it's also like the axis, the like imaginary line through the earth, when it like turns, it the axis the top of it is the axis, it like moves while the while it's rotating. So like here I drew it there and there, cause like when it's rotating it moves it can like move from place to place as the earth rotates. Cause like when it's summer, in um, north, or like, Antarctica when it's summer, it like north, Antarctica will be like right there. But when it's winter, and like the axis could be like this, but when it's winter, the axis could be like totally different or something just how the earth rotated between the seasons. So, yeah.
bruce	Okay, just one last piece. So let's say, so where would we be, what would it look like when we're, when it's summer in Chicago? Could you show me with , if I put this pen?
kerri	Um, I think it would be like this 
bruce	Mhm. And where are we?
kerri	We're like right here  because like we're in the northern hemisphere. So we would be towards the top a little, and it would kind of be tilted more so that when the sunlight hits it would hit the northern like most 
bruce	And on this side here? 
kerri	Yeah.
bruce	And how about in the winter, where- what would it look like?
kerri	It would probably look like this  and we would be on this side, the backside  and we would still be like on the red cap for the northern 
bruce	But, and, but we'd be tilted and away and on the other side 
kerri	Yes.
bruce	And where would, um, would the earth be still  over here or?
kerri	No, it would it would probably be like over here or like over here somewhere  when it's winter. So it's like the different extremes, like summer, and winter would be over here 
bruce	Okay, so now I want to bring something else into the mix: day and night. 
kerri	Okay.
bruce	So how, what makes, can you fit day and night into your story here?
kerri	Um , so well you have the Earth, you have the moon, and then you have the 
bruce	Why don't  you want a new sheet of paper - Why don't we start a new sheet of paper?
kerri	So you have the earth, the moon, and then the sun. So then the earth is constantly rotating around the sun and then the earth, when it's, the earth is constantly spinning, like just rotating. So here, like on this side  it's day, and on this side it's night, just depending on where the earth is facing. So like right now its day but in a couple hours we're rotating, and so in a couple hours it'll be towards the moon and then it will be night. So like when the earth rotates and it rotates towards the moon, when it's facing the moon it's night, and then when it faces the sun, it's day. So.
bruce	So that makes sense but now I want to connect back to this picture you made here.
kerri	Yeah.
bruce	So here you had sort of this side was summer and this side was // winter.
kerri	// Winter. Yeah.
bruce	So is that, but now that sort of looks a little like you were saying this side is day and that side is // night.
kerri	// Night. Yeah. So then like here would be winter and here would be summer, it's summer and day over here but then when it rotates and then like the earth kind of like rotates and like tilts kind of as it goes  so like right now it's spring and here it could be like fall or winter.
bruce	Where could be fall or winter?
kerri	On this side like  right now  okay, I'm just gonna go back to summer and winter cause that's easier. 
bruce	Okay.
kerri	So um summer so it's summer here and it's like daytime, and then when it's winter here, then the earth, when it tilts, it kind of like moves I kind of think in like a swaying way, so like you move to the right when it says move to the right so when it's summer it tilts towards there in like the day. And like, I kind of, I don't think this is accurate at all, but it's just kind of the way I'm thinking of it. // And so
bruce	// That's what I want to know.
kerri	When it sways this way it's summer, and faces  - and then it rotates around, so when it rotates, the axis gets flipped around, and it sways to the left. And so then it's night and then, so when it's swaying to the left, it is winter on the other side and then when it goes back to the summer it's rotating around to the night and it's like rotating the moon. So like the moon - So then it goes back to the original like position for the day and summer.
bruce	I think I got it actually.
kerri	Confusing 
bruce	No I think I got it. Good, good. I wanted to  we're going to come back to this in a second
kerri	Okay
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE> 
bruce	I want to um, but, I wanted to ask you one related question is so we talked about why it's sometimes warm here in Chicago sometimes cold, but there's some places like Florida that are always pretty hot, and some places like Alaska that are always pretty cold. So, so why is that?
kerri	Well, um, the equator. Like in the middle it kind of stays pretty neutral because when it moves here it's very like  when the earth is like this , here it's very cold, but the equator it's always pretty neutral, and then if it's the opposite way, the equator is still in the middle and it's neutral, so places like Florida are near- closer to the equator so they stay kind of like a neutral temperature because they don't have like the drastic changes that we do. And places like Alaska they're kind of more like up here, so like up there, so when it's like, it does it like when it's warm it's kind of like on the other side, so
bruce	So where's the sun now?
kerri	The sun is, oh sorry, here, I'll just say here, um 
bruce	You want another sheet?
kerri	No I could like draw here. So. And then the sun would be like there . So the equator is like neutral, oh the sun should be more down  that's okay, the equator's neutral, but then like Alaska it's more far away and then if, and then when it like tilts again, the equator, it's - wouldn't be like that close - but the equator is neutral like a it still pretty neutral in the same place, but Alaska, when it, um tilts again, it could be kind of close, but it wouldn't be like  here you would get the most sun and the most, like warm and on the equator, and here it's kind of like far out and it's like up and, it's very far away from the equator so it's not like the direct point of the sunlight. So it kind of gets like that kinda far away distant like warm like in the springtime here would probably be like the summer, because I went to Alaska during the summer and it's kind of like a spring day here. So that's what it's kind of like cause it's like more far away, it's not close to the equator so it's not warm, but it's not like cold, so it gets sunlight but it's just not as much cause it's farther away.
bruce	Okay. Okay good.
kerri	Okay.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
