<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>libby</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Okay, so, first question, no pictures yet.
libby	Right.
bruce	Um, is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
libby	Okay. So this is earth, and earth, and um so the sun and, is around the earth  I think.
bruce	Uhuh.
libby	Like, yeah, no cause there's the moon, and then the sun goes around the earth, and the earth goes around, and right okay, yeah, so, so  so
bruce	So the sun and the earth.
libby	So the earth, if the sun is on one part of the earth then it's summer, but if it's on the other part of the earth than it's summer, and then it's winter on the other part of the earth.
bruce	Okay. So how does that work again? So I get some
libby	Okay, so this is, this is the earth  okay, and it's a little circle. And then this is the sun, and if the sun is on this side of the earth so the sun's right here and it's shining on this part and it's summer. 
bruce	Okay.
libby	But on this part there is no sun so it's winter.
bruce	Okay. Um, no that makes sense. And, um, can you draw a picture of that?
libby	Yes. Okay . So this is the earth, that's a E for the earth, and then this is the sun,  the sun. And um, and if it's on this side then it's all like bright and sunny on this side, and it's summer, and then on this side it's winter.
bruce	So, can you draw the sun, draw the win, draw what it looks like in winter? So this is, it's, oh I see, so on this side it's winter.
libby	Yeah, and then, and then if it was like this, then it would be summer on this side and winter on this side.
bruce	So let's, so let's say put Chicago on there.
libby	So Chicago's right there.
bruce	Okay. And that's Chicago in the
libby	Winter
bruce	In the winter. And then
libby	This is Chicago in the summer.
bruce	Okay. And what's moving here, the sun is, how is the sun moving?
libby	The sun goes around the earth, no it goes like ' it goes like around like this way, like this way.
bruce	Sort of out of the piece of paper?
libby	Yeah.
bruce	It will go up like that and around?
libby	Like around.
bruce	Okay.
libby	I think.
bruce	Okay, that makes sense.
libby	And then, and then this goes around, this is the moon, and then this it all goes around the moon. Oh wait, no. No, I changed my mind. No, it's the sun. No yeah, I completely change my mind. This is the sun, and then this is the earth, and then the moon, I'm going to make the moon like that, even though it may not be a full moon or a half moon. And then this goes around that, and then this goes around that.
bruce	All right now this seems very different than what you said before.
libby	Okay it's very different, so the earth, so if this is Chicago, then it's right now it's winter, and then if it's over here, and this is Chicago then it's oh, no, right here it's summer because it's toward the sun.
bruce	Okay.
libby	Yeah.
bruce	So the earth , so on - the earth is, why is it winter right here again?
libby	Because it's towards not sun.
bruce	Okay . And over here it's
libby	It's towards the sun, so it's summer.
bruce	So how's the earth moving exactly? It's just
libby	The earth moves around like on an axis cause it's like tilted actually, the earth's actually tilted, and then it spins around on that little thingy. Like on that line, like it's an invisible line. And it goes like really fast, so fast. 
bruce	So is it spinning as it's going like that?
libby	Yeah it's spinning around as it's spinning around this way at the same time.
bruce	Okay. And, does the spinning around have anything to do with the seasons? The spinning around like this fast?
libby	 Yes, cause it spins. Yes, because it spins, so that it can get to that position, Like it spins, like it spins so it can actually like get to the where it is. Like, cause this may be like Chicago, but on the other side of the earth because it's three-dimensional, then it may be like Africa or something. Well obviously it's not Africa because Africa is like, but it would be so, it would be Europe, and then um and then in Europe it would be winter, because, um, no it wouldn't be winter. Yeah it would be winter. And then wherever this is, this area right here, that would be summer, and then all of this half of the area would be winter. And this would all be summer. So anywhere on the, but if it's turned like this way, and so Chicago is actually like on the other side, like on that side, then it would be winter, and then it turns again, and so it's on like that side cause it's turning, then it's on that side then it's winter, and then it turns again and then it then it's summer.
bruce	Wait, so it's winter over here also?
libby	Yeah. No, no, well obviously it's like more up there cause I'm not spacing this correctly. 
bruce	Oh, okay.
libby	But it would be, cause like it's, it's cut kind of like in half, so it would be like winter, and summer, and fall, and aut- and fall and spring.
bruce	Okay.
libby	Yeah.
bruce	Um, okay cool. And so, and, so we haven't really talked yet about day and night. How does, how does day and night work with this?
libby	Okay, so this is, this goes around like this, and so if the, so, if this is the earth. Oh, that's when the rotation comes along, on, on this thing. So like if the sun's up here then it's night cause that's Chicago. Then when it turns
bruce	wait, where, where's the sun?
libby	Oh, I mean this is the moon.
bruce	Oh that's the moon. Okay.
libby	Yeah and so it's nighttime. And then it turns, cause in a day it turns once, I think.
bruce	What turns once.
libby	The earth. The earth it turns once. And then this is the sun, and so when it turns then Chicago is actually on that side, and then it's facing the sun and it's day. And that's where the sun like goes and sets.
bruce	But why, then why isn't this also summer if it's on that side. I thought you said that
libby	Oh. So. What am I thinking? Maybe since the earth is so far away, oh because, oh because I think that it goes like that . And so, and so the sun is like right here. And so when it's close to it, but this is far away in the winter.
bruce	Okay.
libby	 And so
bruce	And now this is another answer, another completely different answer, or?
libby	No, it's just that this is a really bad picture. With this picture, you see this is better because it shows you how long it is. 
bruce	Okay, but so but now you're saying this is winter, the sun, the earth is further from the sun there?
libby	Yes, I think.
bruce	And here it's closer?
libby	Yeah. Cause it's closer, cause it's, like, cause this is Chicago, and this is Chicago, and this is Chicago, and this is Chicago, and this is Chicago.
bruce	Okay, but in this, but in this picture, in this picture it was on the other side of the earth.
libby	Oh gosh, I have no idea. All I know is that I think that winter is when it's far away from the sun, and and summer is close to it.
bruce	Okay. One thing you were saying was that like when it's winter here it's summer somewhere else.
libby	Yes.
bruce	Like Europe or Africa.
libby	Exactly . So, so in like France, here, oh  then no, I go back to this question.
bruce	 Okay.
libby	All right, so I ex this out, and going back to this, and okay, so so since it's turning on its axis, it turns once in one day, I think.
bruce	Okay.
libby	And so, and since, since it turns like one time in one day, then, um, and then, but then it's also turning, it turns once in one day, but then it's also going around the earth really slowly, because one time around the earth is 365 days, which is a year. And then, um, and then, the, um, and then and then the sun is going ar-, then it's, oh gosh. Oh no, I change my mind again.
bruce	Okay, which expl-, so which is right now?
libby	Okay, so right now I'm at, this is the moon.
bruce	Why don't you use a new sheet of paper, since you haven't started yet? 
libby	 This is the moon, and then, we're going around the moon, and then the sun's going, and then this is the earth, and then this is the sun, and the sun's going around the earth.
bruce	Oh, okay, so back to the sun going around the earth now.
libby	Yeah, and then the moon's in the middle.
bruce	And moon's in the middle. Okay.
libby	I'm pretty positive. And so since the sun is going around, oh gosh, that doesn't make any sense. I changed my mind again.
bruce	 Okay, you're allowed to change your mind.
libby	No, I'm seriously, I'm no, I'm ser, no I'm really like, I really get it now.
bruce	Okay.
libby	This picture made me get it.  That's the sun, and this is the solar system, and this is, no I just did a three  this is E, and then this is the sun, no  wait, no no I changed my mind again. This is the sun, and then, that's the sun, and then, okay, and then this is the earth. And then this is the moon, but once, if the moon is in between the sun and the earth, like right here, then it's blocking the sun, and so it's nighttime for Chicago, which is right there.
bruce	Oh, okay. Okay.
libby	And then, but then if it's Chica-, but then, um if the earth is right here, and the moon happens to be right here, then it's nighttime, it's nighttime, and then it's daytime, and nighttime.
bruce	Okay. And what's summer- ?
libby	And then summer is when the earth is tilting toward the sun at your part of the earth, because every part of the earth is summer at a different time. So if Chicago's like up here, or no yeah, then it's winter, but if Chicago's really close to the sun, like right there, then, and the moon's like right here because it's daytime. So it's daytime and summer.
bruce	And that's because of how it's tilted, or how it's
libby	How it turns.
bruce	How it turns.
libby	I think. Yeah. And then, um, and then, cause, and then, so the earth has nothing to do with day and night, that's the moon that goes around. Yeah, but then how does sunset happen? Cause the sunset, cause there's like a sunset, and so like, like I don't know. It has something to do with it.
bruce	Okay. We'll let's, you've, you've have a lot of the right pieces. In a minute I'll help you put them all together exactly right.
libby	Okay.
bruce	Okay? You've got, it turns out the seasons are supe - is supe, is a super hard question . Most adults can't explain it. In fact you if you ask professors at Harvard they mostly don't put all the pieces together quite right.
libby	I want to go to Harvard.
bruce	So there's no shame in not knowing it exactly.
libby	Yeah.
bruce	Okay. But let's, we'll, we'll come back it and I'll, I'll put all the pieces for you together in a second. 
libby	Okay. Sorry, it was kind of long.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Well that's good. I'd like, I was interested in how you think about it. Um, so I wanted to ask you one related question which is, we talked about why it's warmer in the summer in Chicago and colder in the winter, but there are some places where it's always generally warm, and some places where it's always generally, like Florida.
libby	Yes, and California.
bruce	Yeah, well part, yeah, Florida.
libby	Oh yeah, cause California is in the south. Yeah, okay.
bruce	Let's stick with Florida, and then let's pick some place like Alaska that's always pretty cold.
libby	Yeah.
bruce	So why is that? Why is Florida generally warm and Alaska generally cold?
libby	Because there's an equator.
bruce	Uh-uh.
libby	And the equator in the earth is in the middle, and it's like a imaginary line, and the closer you are to the equator, the warmer it is, so it's really warm in Ecuador because it's right on the equator.
bruce	Mhm.
libby	And then in the north pole, or the south pole, it's the north pole I think and the south pole, they're both really cold, but I'm thinking the north pole. 
bruce	Okay.
libby	Um, um it's like really, really freezing cause it's really far away from the equator, so like in the America, in America, like um, Florida is in the south, in the southern area, so that's the reason that it's like warmer, and then Alaska is up in the top part, and so it's colder because it's farther away from the equator. 
bruce	Okay.
libby	So like southern states are usually warmer, and then like, medium states are they're like neutral, and then northern states really like cold.
bruce	Why does being closer to the equator make it warmer?
libby	Uh, cause the Equator's hot, cause the sun, because the sun goes around the equator, right? Because, cause the sun is like this . Am I allowed to draw?
bruce	Oh yeah.
libby	And then, okay, cause this is the equator line, and the sun, like see how it like goes in like that. Cause this is the hottest part of the sun, so it goes like beams towards the equator, and then this is like America, like up here, and then this is like Alaska, this is like Florida, and so it's closer, well it's actually not that close, obviously. Because that's like Ecuador. But um , um, and so this is like the hottest part of it. 
bruce	So it's because, because the Equator is, is near the hottest part of the sun?
libby	That's what I think.
bruce	Okay. Uh, okay. So the
libby	The sun goes around
bruce	So there are some parts of the sun that are hotter than other parts?
libby	No, it's just that it's closer because this part, cause this part is kind of farther away cause it's like a circle.
bruce	Mhm.
libby	And since this part is closer, cause like the circles are like next to each other, and these two parts of the circle are closer.
bruce	Okay, so it's not really that this part of the sun is hotter?
libby	Yeah, just cause this is farther away. Cause this, there's more space in between like here and here, than here and here.
bruce	Okay. Now you haven't tried to draw this to scale exactly, right? Like, no, like how big is 
libby	Of course not.
bruce	Okay, so what would it look like drawn to scale?
libby	Okay, I do realize that the sun
bruce	Okay. Some people, most people don't try to draw it to scale. I'm just, now asking you what would it, look like drawn to scale.
libby	Like that .
bruce	So the sun is a lot bigger.
libby	Oh, no that doesn't make any sense because then the sun would like completely devour the earth.
bruce	What do you mean, it would be hot all over and burn us?
libby	It would be hot all over and it would like kill us. Okay, so it can't be that much bigger, I'm not exactly sure, it's like that.
bruce	Is that about the right distance, though? 
libby	No, no no no no no.
bruce	Okay.
libby	I'm going to draw so that we don't die. It's like, I don't know, if I draw it to scale it would be like really far away.
bruce	Okay.
libby	I don't know how far away it would be.
bruce	Okay, but, but far away.
libby	Far away, off in the distance.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
