<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>lisa</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Okay? Um, so here’s my first difficult question. You don’t need paper yet. The question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
lisa	 Cause the, um,  cause earth iss like tilted a certain way.
bruce	Mm-hmm.
lisa	And, it’s like tilted like towards or away from like the sun, like the part of it that we’re on.
bruce	Mm-hm. Say more about how that works.
lisa	So like, throughout the year the earth is like tilted a different way.
bruce	Wh-, when is?
lisa	Throughout the year its like tilted a different way.
bruce	Uh-uh.
lisa	Or something, like around. And when it like, the sun, so the sun like hits the earth at a different angle when it’s tilted a different way.
bruce	Mhm.
lisa	And so
bruce	And so, how is it tilted when it’s winter, let’s say?
lisa	Well if it’s like winter in Chicago?
bruce	Yeah, if it’s winter in Chicago.
lisa	Then the earth is like tilted, um, so the, the sun is more aimed towards different parts of the earth. 
bruce	Towards different parts of the earth? If it’s winter in Chicago, you said?
lisa	Mm-hmm.
bruce	Okay. And, in summer, how’s it, what’s it doing?
lisa	It’s like, nearer to the sun. It’s like tilted so that the sun, it like hits it a certain way. I don’t know.
bruce	Okay. Can you, can you try drawing a picture, of what you’re?
lisa	Sure.
bruce	Okay, go for it.
lisa	 I don’t know.
bruce	Well just try to draw what you were just saying.
lisa	I don’t even know. But earth is like that, or like  I don’t know actually. Just kidding. 
bruce	 That is not the earth 
lisa	Um  I don’t know.
bruce	So you’re very much on the right track. It does have do with how the earth is tilted, and the angle of the light hits the earth at. That’s right.
lisa	Okay, so doesn’t the earth have a like certain tilt though? I don’t know 
bruce	So can you maybe draw the sun and the earth when it’s summer in north, in Chicago?
lisa	I don’t really know  is like the earth like, if Chicago is like there or whatever.
bruce	Where is it? I just didn’t see it.
lisa	The dot 
bruce	Okay.
lisa	And the sun is like there.
bruce	Uhuh.
lisa	Then it’s like more facing toward the sun 
bruce	Okay.
lisa	But like in winter in Chicago’s like over there.
bruce	Over where?
lisa	Or it’s like tilted. I don’t know 
bruce	Where were you thinking the earth  might be in what
lisa	Well that’s not re-, well  no, just kidding. Just kidding. I wasn’t actually thinking that.
bruce	Okay. So this is Chicago summer?
lisa	I don’t really know, sure.
bruce	What would - And what might Chicago winter look like?
lisa	Like if the same thing, but with, it’s like that, maybe. 
bruce	It’s closer to the sun, or you just, you needed some place to draw it.
lisa	It’s just like a different tilt. I don’t know.
bruce	So that’s, so why might that be winter?
lisa	Because it’s like, tilted, well I don’t know.
bruce	It’s tilted how?
lisa	Like to the left.
bruce	I see. Okay. And the earth moves right?
lisa	Mhm.
bruce	So how, how does the earth move?
lisa	It like revolves around the sun, and it like circles around. It’s like, it turns around itself and like goes around. 
bruce	Okay. It goes around. So if this is the sun, how would it go?
lisa	Like if this were the sun, the earth would like go all the way around, but it’s not actually that size, but.
bruce	Uh-huh. And
lisa	And it would like spin.
bruce	Uh-huh. And, so let’s say, so let’s say this is the earth in summer.
lisa	Mhm.
bruce	Where’s the earth when it’s winter? Is the earth // like here, here, here?
lisa	// Like, it’s like here, or something.
bruce	Why do you think that?
lisa	Because then, like the, like the other side of the circle would be hitting. Well, I don’t know. It’s like tilted, well it’s stays at the same tilt, but it like goes around, so it’s like a little bit different.
bruce	Mhm.
lisa	I don’t know.
bruce	What do you mean if it’s at the same tilt?
lisa	Like it’s like 23 point something.
bruce	Yeah but what is, what did you mean it was at the same tilt.
lisa	Like it’s at the same degree tilt, but it like, when it like goes around, it’s like a little bit different. Like, I don’t know.
bruce	Mm-hmm. So let’s say this is the earth  and it’s tilted like that. So how might it move?
lisa	It would like go like that.
bruce	And it’s gradually changing how it’s tilted?
lisa	I don’t know.
bruce	Okay.
lisa	Yeah 
bruce	Okay. And wh- so you’re saying maybe it’s like over here in summer and up over there in winter?
lisa	I don’t know, maybe, but it’s like, yeah.
bruce	Well why would that being there as opposed to there make it colder?
lisa	Well not necessarily being there, just like being like different tilts so that the sunlight directly doesn’t hit it.
bruce	I see.
lisa	So it still get’s light, but it’s just not hot.
bruce	Okay. Okay, you’re super close. We’ll come back to it in a second and I tell you the right answer, but you’re super close.
lisa	Okay.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE> 
bruce	Um, uh, I want to ask you one other related question though before I tell you the answer to that one.
lisa	Okay.
bruce	Um, so we just talked about how it’s warmer in Chicago sometimes and colder sometimes.
lisa	Mhm.
bruce	Um. But there are some places like Florida that are generally warm, and some places like Alaska that are generally cold.
lisa	Mhm.
bruce	You know, so why is that?
lisa	Because, when it’s like closer to the equator it’s usually warmer. And when it’s like closer to like the poles its usually cold at like, when it’s like very far north or very far south, because, yeah.
bruce	Well why does being closer to the equator make it warmer.
lisa	Because the sun hits it more directly usually.
bruce	Okay, so what, why does the sun hit more directly at the equator?
lisa	Because the equator’s right in the middle, and the earth doesn’t like, super change the tilt, so it just like, it’s always right there, it always like hits it.
bruce	Can you draw a picture of that, so show me, that show’s why the sun hits most directly at the equator?
lisa	Well,  the sun’s there, like the equator’s like, right there like always like, like if it were like, it’s like sort of like 2-D but like, it always hits like right, you know.
bruce	I see, so that’s where it hits directly. And where’s Alaska? 
lisa	Like up here.
bruce	Oh it’s over there. And why does it hit there not directly?
lisa	Because it’s like tilted, a different away. It’s like not really like that but like that. And, I don’t know, I don’t really know how to explain it.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
