<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>marcus</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>cf</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Okay. All right, so my first question is, um, why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
marcus	Because of like the alignment, like in, like the sun, I think it has to do with. Like the sun, like the plan—like, like the course , like the sun is here, and like the planets, you know, go like around the sun and so like it depends like where, cause like the earth might be, like farther away from the sun, or something. And like in like, in the winter, and in the summer it might be closer, or, yeah, or um, like, yeah.
bruce	So how is, say that again, how is the earth moving?
marcus	It, it goes like around the sun.
bruce	Uh-uh.
marcus	And, like, and so like once a, one time around is one year, so like let’s say can I draw a picture?
bruce	Sure. Go ahead.
marcus	 Let’s say like this is the sun, and then, sorry, and then this is the earth, it goes like around, like it has a path that it goes on. And like, let’s say this is, pretend this is like here or something, like summer, I think, I’m like I’m not really sure, but maybe like summer might be like closer cause this is closer, and then this might be winter, or, in the, I, I don’t know.
bruce	And, so where’s the earth in the summer?
marcus	We’d be like, like closer, like this is summer cause it’s closer, or like, I don’t know, like this is winter cause it’s farther. And like, closer is warmer, I don’t know.
bruce	So why does this curve out farther here, did you just, does it really go?
marcus	I, I just kind of drew a circle, I, I don’t know, I just.
bruce	So can you draw the path of the earth in again? Is it coming?
marcus	Um, like, like here, and then since it’s closer for summer, and then it like winter it’s like farther or something, I’m not really sure.
bruce	Okay, and this line over here was just a mistake up there?
marcus	Yeah I was just, cause I was like, yeah it was a mistake.
bruce	Okay, um, okay. So here it’s a little closer, and there further away.
marcus	Er. Yeah.
bruce	So this is winter and that’s summer?
marcus	Even though I’m not sh, I don’t know if it’s right or not.
bruce	You’re not sure, but that’s your first
marcus	Yeah I don’t, it’s my first guess.
bruce	Uh-huh. Well that makes a lot of sense, uh, but have you heard, um, that when it’s winter here it’s summer in other places?
marcus	Oh yeah. Um, 
bruce	Is that a problem for your explanation?
marcus	Yes 
bruce	So could you just explain out loud why it’s a problem? 
marcus	It’s a problem because if earth is here in winter and it has, like if earth, if I said earth was here in winter, and in summer earth is here, well in winter like China would be like summer, because China’s on the opposite side. But if earth is here and this is winter, then it all has to be winter, but it’s not all winter at the same time.
bruce	Okay. So, want to take another stab at it?
marcus	Um, okay. Um, maybe, I’m just trying to think. Cause
bruce	Take a second.
marcus	Winter, um, it, maybe because  how, how like maybe because when the earth moves, like how it like rotates, it like, one side is more facing, well no that doesn’t make sense at all. Um, I don’t know.
bruce	Why doesn’t that make sense?
marcus	Because, because it’s, because you see the sun all the time. But maybe it’s like cause you see more of the sun in the summer then, but I don’t think that’s true. So I don’t know.
bruce	So here’s, what were you were trying to work out? Can you just
marcus	Well I was just trying but
bruce	It didn’t work. I still don’t understand what that was
marcus	So like the sun’s, okay, like the sun’s here, and like this is not to proportion, but whatever. And this is the earth, and let’s say like you know how like the earth is spinning, it’s like, it’s like spinning and stuff.
bruce	Uh-huh.
marcus	And so, when like, when like maybe like when earth is over here , the sun like China might be like, like the how it like spins it might be like China sees more of the sun, and then like, United States doesn’t. But I don’t think that’s right. Like, do you get what I mean, or no?
bruce	I think so. So, so this is day and night, and 
marcus	This is the sun, and it’s and like the earth is spinning, and like how it spins, like if it, as it like, um, as it gets over like here whatever it doesn’t matter where it is. But, as like, when it’s spinning, like the United States might see more of the sun, but then China might, because like, this might be like, like this is the earth, and then this is like China, or whatever, but then this is the United States, I don’t know, but it doesn’t really make sense. Like, this is China, but this is like the United States, and like, like this is the separation point like right here, and so China sees more of the sun, but the earth doesn’t. 
bruce	And why doesn’t that make sense?
marcus	Because I don’t think that’s right.  I mean it might make sense, it just doesn’t - but I don’t think that’s right.
bruce	It just doesn’t sound right to your, to you, or 
marcus	Because the, I don’t know. I don’t, I just, it just doesn’t seem, cause like, of what I know, it just doesn’t seem like it would be right. Cause I never really thought, like why is it the winter.
bruce	Uh-huh. So is this something you’ve learned about in school before?
marcus	I think in fourth grade we learned about it, but I forgot.
bruce	You don’t remember anything about it?
marcus	No.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE> 
bruce	Um, okay. Um, I think I might come back to this in a second and give you some more hints, but first I want to ask you a, a, a different, but related question.
marcus	Okay.
bruce	So what I want to know is, um, so we just talked about, you know, like in Chicago it’s sometimes winter and sometimes summer.
marcus	Mhm.
bruce	We tried to explain why that was. But there’s also some places like Florida that are always kind of warm, or generally warmer. And there’s places like Alaska that are always kind of cold. So why is that?
marcus	Because like, okay can I, I’m just gonna draw. 
bruce	Sure
marcus	 There’s like um the, the line, there’s like the imaginary line, the equator that goes through the middle of the earth. And so, this is Florida 
bruce	Mhm.
marcus	And then this is, where was like?
bruce	Alaska
marcus	Alaska, even though Alaska’s like over here, but whatever.  And so, um, and so, um, like the this line is where the sun reaches more, and so it’s warmer there because the sun, the equa- the equator, shows like, like I I just know that the equator, like here is where most of like the sun hits. And like, as I think, as you get like farther out, the le- the more cold it gets cause the less of the sun you see, or something.
bruce	Okay, that that makes sense. But why does that equator see more sun?
marcus	Because, maybe because it’s in the center, and so the center, cause like the, the earth is it’s a globe, and so, like, like when it like faces the sun, it mi- cause it’s like the center, maybe like the way like the alignment, cause like this is the sun, maybe alignment, like the more like, cause this is farther from I, I think, because this is like farther away from the sun or something, and um
bruce	Uh-huh. So, so the equator kind of sticks out, or something, and that’s why it’s
marcus	Well, I think that’s, I think that’s where the sun hits, I don’t know why, but I, cause it’s just like where the sun hits. I don’t know.
</CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay. Okay, that makes sense. Um, so let, let’s go back to the, to the seasons. I just want to give you one hint to remind you of something you might have heard before. 
marcus	Okay.
bruce	Um, you ever heard that it has something to do with the tilt of the earth? Does that sound familiar at all?
marcus	Yeah. It does sound familiar. Maybe because, yeah it sounds familiar so.
bruce	Can you do anything with it, or?
marcus	Um, it’s kind of like, because this is the sun , and this is the earth, and like, it’s like how, like if, if it’s tilted maybe, like one part’s, like if it’s, like okay. So this is the sun and this is the earth, and like this is China let’s say, and then this is the United States, and like it’s it’s like the earth is spinning, rotating whichever way
bruce	Mhm.
marcus	And, um, like rotating, like the tilt like, it’s rotating so that it changes like, like the tilting, or whatever, or something. And, and so, like China, like when it’s tilting like this w-, like when it’s like, th-, th-, the tilt, that, like when it’s tilted towards the sun, it’s maybe summer there. But when the earth, but when the United States, when it like, when the United States is more tilted towards the sun, it might be summer there, but right now it’s winter, and right now it’s winter the farther away.
bruce	Okay.
marcus	I don’t really know.
bruce	And how is, the earth is spinning like this ?
marcus	Yeah, like the earth, like the tilt, I, like it’s spinning so that, it’s like, whichever faces, like  I don’t think that’s right either. I don’t know.
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
