<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>mason</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Okay. So my first question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
mason	Alright. So, um  the earth it, it moves on an axis, it turns. And then, um sometimes when it’s uh, er it turns, and when it’s not facing eart—it di—when it’s not facing the sun directly, it’s, um winter, or like, and then yeah. So it’s, the reason it’s colder in the winter and hotter in the summer is because the earth spins on an axis, and depending on what side it’s on depends on if it’s hot or cold, or what side it’s on.
bruce	Okay. Can you just elaborate a little more 45?
mason	Um  I’m not sure, you want to help me out with this one? Or, I’m not sure.
bruce	So what were you, you were saying it spins 
mason	On an axis. Yeah.
bruce	So what does that mean?
mason	Well the earth, it rotates.
bruce	Uhuh. 
mason	Is what I, yeah.
bruce	Okay. And how might how might that make it be summer and winter?
mason	Hmm. Well I know  the moon and the sun come into play.
bruce	Okay.
mason	But I’m not exactly sure like, where the moon and the sun have to be to make it winter, or where they have to be to make it summer, but er summer but I know like, it
bruce	It has something to do
mason	Yeah, the earth and the moon come into play.
bruce	Okay. So let’s start, can you maybe draw something what you know about how the earth and the sun, and the earth moves?
mason	Alright. Alright, so here  would be this planet earth okay? 
bruce	Okay.
mason	And then that’s it’s axis, and then it, it goes on an axis like that.
bruce	Okay. 
mason	And then, um  like the moon it rotates around, around the earth and um  when, when it’s like either, or I’m not sure, er but like yeah, for that would be the moon for example, and like, well yeah that’s
bruce	Mhm. Can we have see the sun too?
mason	Oh the sun? Uh sure, I’ll put the sun right there. And I’m not sure, I’m not sure what that would make, though, with the sun put here and the moon blocking it but 
bruce	So that might that, what would the moon, the moon blocking it have to do with  might make it winter or summer or?
mason	Um  mmm, I’m not, I’m not sure  um, I know we learned about this about this in science. Like we we just had a question on it in like a practice quiz or something, but I’m not, I’m not sure exactly.
bruce	Okay. Well, you started to say something about the earth is spinning, and part of it is facing the sun in the summer, or something?
mason	Right.
bruce	So what did you mean by that?
mason	Um, well, depending on where the sun, or  I think, I’m not sure really, but I know the earth goes on an axis. It spins. And then the moon  the moon like revolves around the sun, or like the moon  or I’m, I’m not sure really. But I don’t know how to explain.
bruce	Okay, so the earth spins, spins on an axis. It spins like this . Does it move any other ways? Does it - is it like the sun is here and the earth sits here and spins like that . Is that right?
mason	It  it’s in one place, or it goes like arou—but it doesn’t like move like up, up and down and stuff, or
bruce	You mean it doesn’t go like this? 
mason	No.
bruce	Does it move at all like this? 
mason	Yes it does. 
bruce	Okay. So can you show me? So it spins and 
mason	It spins like, it spins around the sun. 
bruce	Okay.
mason	And obviously there are like planets, other planets.
bruce	Mhm.
mason	So.
bruce	Okay. And somehow that makes summer and winter, and you’re not sure how?
mason	I—I’m pretty sure. I don’t know, I don’t know, I’m not positive. 
bruce	So do you want to, so now do you want to hazard any guesses?
mason	Um.
bruce	See if you can make up a reason. If you just had to figure out.
mason	Uh, okay, um.
bruce	Make some guesses.
mason	So the earth, all the planets they revo—or they, they go around the sun. And what I’m possibly thinking is, I don’t, I don’t know if this is right or anything. Is it okay if I use this side?
bruce	Let’s, let’s use a different sheet. Cause you can see it goes through.
mason	Alright so here’s the sun. And when, for example, there are four, I’m making four section for like each, for fall, summer, winter, and spring.
bruce	Mhm.
mason	And, um, I don’t know this, but when earth is over here, when earth rotates over here that might be like fall for example, and then this might be winter for example, and this would be spring, and this would be summer. So when, so when earth goes like around, around the sun each, the seasons would change. 
bruce	Mhm. Yeah, so that, that makes sense. 
mason	I don’t know. 
bruce	And do you have any idea why, why being over here might make it winter, and being over there might make it summer.
mason	Um, I’m not  I’m not sure to be honest with you.
bruce	Okay.
mason	Is it  No, I don’t, I don’t know.
bruce	What were you going to guess?
mason	I was gonna  I was wondering if it was like  it wouldn’t make sense though, I was just taking a guess, I was just wondering if it was something like the atmosphere but that wouldn’t, that wouldn’t make sense.
bruce	Okay.
mason	Uh.  Um  Would the moon have anything to do with it, or?
bruce	How, just so, how would the moon have something to do with it?
mason	Well the moon.  It might be able to like, block sunlight from, from the earth or partially. Or, yeah, so.
bruce	Mhm. And that would make it colder and block the sunlight.
mason	Right. Not all of it, but some.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay. So I’m gonna, I’m gonna tell you, tell you the right answer in a second but I want to ask you one other question first.
mason	Okay.
bruce	Um, so we talked about why it changes from fall to winter or spring to summer, but there are some places like Florida where it’s always pretty warm, and some places like Alaska where it’s always pretty cold. So do you have any idea why that is?
mason	 Okay. Um  I  I know, I know that um, sometimes the climate of like the waters around it. I know that has something, something to do with it cause, like the breeze coming off of it, can warm, warm, warm it up like for Florida. But do you do you want to know like why the sun, like shines there or why it’s hot there? Or like
bruce	Yeah, I want to know why is it hot, you know? Why is Florida generally pretty hot?
mason	Hmm because  the  I’m not, I’m not, I’m not sure to be honest with you.
bruce	Okay.
mason	I wouldn’t, though I’d be interested in knowing that. Now that you bring it up, but I don’t know.
bruce	And you don’t have a guess?
mason	No.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
