<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>samantha</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	So, we don’t need that yet. First question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter.
samantha	Because, um , the earth goes on a, like it goes around the sun. And at different points the earth is, like tilted towards the sun, and that would be summer, and it’s tilted away, or upside down, I’m not quite sure which way, but it’s - then it’d be winter.
bruce	Okay. 
samantha	I think .
bruce	So how does that work exactly 
samantha	Okay, so the sun , and the earth it like  it goes around the sun  and so at different, and the earth it like  turns, I think. So at one point it’ll be  summer on like,  this side and the next point it would be winter on this side. 
bruce	Okay.
samantha	Yeah, I think. 
bruce	Okay. Um, could you draw me a picture?
samantha	Yeah. Okay, so . My sun.
bruce	Nice Sun.
samantha	Thank you  the earth is right there, and so it goes um  should I draw how it goes around?
bruce	Sure.
samantha	Okay  so it goes around this way, and then um, but it turns  sort of, okay. Um, and at different points when the earth is like, uh, when the earth turns on this side it’d be winter, this side would be summer, I think. Yeah.
bruce	Okay, um
samantha	That might not be right, but
bruce	Okay. So that make- So why is it winter on this, on this side?
samantha	Because it’s facing away from the sun.
bruce	Okay, um, so let’s say it’s winter in Chicago right now.
samantha	Okay.
bruce	Can you show where we, we would be?
samantha	Right  here. Or like, here, wherever. Somewhere on this half.
bruce	Okay. And so can you show what it would look like if it was summer in Chicago? Can you draw draw the earth for, summer in Chicago?
samantha	Yeah let’s draw it over here, and that’s half, this side would be winter. Winter , summer , and we would be like right there, sort of facing the sun.
bruce	Okay. Yeah
samantha	I, I think. I know it’s somehow the earth like turns towards the sun I think.
bruce	Mhm 
samantha	Yeah 
bruce	It seems like you’re not happy with that for some reason.
samantha	Well no I’m just  um, no I know it somehow goes around the sun, but I’m not quite sure how the earth, if that’s the way it goes. Like, if um, I know the earth turns and I know it goes around the sun, but I’m not quire sure if the winter and summer, or, how the earth turns. I’m not, like  quite sure about that like, which way the, I don’t know if it’s like  no, or you know maybe  it’ll be like turning um, like it’d be sort of diagonal. No, no I think it’s this one.
bruce	Okay, so it’s, so it’s, um here it’s summer becau- on this side of the earth.
samantha	Yeah.
bruce	Um, and winter on that other side there?
samantha	Ye—yeah.
bruce	And why again is it, is it summer on this side.
samantha	I think because it’s facing the sun, and that’s not.
bruce	Okay. Um, so let’s, let’s bring something else into the mix now.
samantha	Okay 
bruce	Let’s bring day and night into the mix.
samantha	Oh—Okay, . Yeah, see here’s the thing, I think, actually I think I did like the time zone sort of, like this would be day and that would be night because you’re facing the sun and the sun is like shooting light towards the earth, and this one doesn’t get any light. So yeah  maybe the earth is on a  I don’t know.
bruce	So, so does, is the, the, does that raise a, were you seeing a problem with your explanation when I?
samantha	Yeah 
bruce	Okay. Can you just say out loud what the problem was? Just
samantha	Like, um, like what you asked me?
bruce	Yeah.
samantha	Uh, you asked me which, uh how do we know when it’s summer or winter.
bruce	And, uhuh. What was the problem with, when I asked you about day and night, that made you not like your explanation.
samantha	Because then I realized I had drawn a diagram of day and night. 
bruce	Okay, okay. Um  okay.
samantha	Maybe it was winter because the earth is tilted like on an axis sort of. So it like turn—like  I don’t know how to explain it. Like I have it in my mind but I can’t say it sort of.
bruce	Try one, try one more time.
samantha	Um, okay so I know this isn’t right. That’s day and night . And um, so I know how it goes around the sun and it turns and that gives you day and night. But I think if it was like  tilted like, no I can’t draw it, but like instead of like this it would be like that maybe? 
bruce	Mhm.
samantha	And then um, but it’s still turning so this maybe  I have no clue what I am doing.
bruce	Okay, so something about the tilt.
samantha	Yeah, it’s something about the way that the earth is tilted that gives you both.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Yeah, okay. You, you were on the right track and I’m gonna, I’m gonna finish and close the loop for you in a second. // But I want to ask one question of you first.
samantha	// Okay, yeah, alright.
bruce	Um, so we just talked about why it’s generally warmer sometimes, why it’s warmer in Chicago sometimes and it’s colder in Chicago sometimes. 
samantha	Yeah.
bruce	Um, but there are some places like Florida where it’s always pretty hot and some places like Alaska where it’s always pretty cold. So why is that?
samantha	Oh, the equator. Because um  the equator is where it’s the warmest, and Alaska is far away from the equator, and Florida is really close to the equator.
bruce	Okay so I’m going to ask you why is it generally - why is the equator warm?
samantha	Um, because the way like the sun like hits it, or the way it’s facing the sun  if that makes sense.
bruce	I think so, can you say a little more?
samantha	Um   
bruce	In what way is it facing the sun?
samantha	 Uh, the sun is hitting it like directly in like the middle of the earth. Like if this was the sun , and this was the earth, um, the way it’s tilting, the sun is always directly hitting it like right there instead of like over here. And I mean it’s hitting it here, but not as like high, sort of like. It’s hitting it the  warmest, sort of like 
bruce	It’s hitting it the warmest here?
samantha	Yeah.
bruce	And less warm right
samantha	Yeah.
bruce	Okay.
samantha	I think.
bruce	Okay. No that’s on target. 
samantha	Okay.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
