<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>sophia</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>ft</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	Okay, so my first question is, why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
sophia	Well, in science we talked about, we did an experiment with like some people from a, I don't, from a university, they went to our school. 
bruce	Mhm.
sophia	And we were doing an experiment on light on a black can and a white can so then like the cold like the air the cold air like the white it's like like taking the energy in from the sun. 
bruce	Mhm.
sophia	So then the it's colder in the winter. And then, like, and they said that the black can, like the earth is starting to become like a black can.
bruce	Mhm.
sophia	Because the other stuff that's blocking like the the for the sun to take in to energy.
bruce	Okay. Um, so let's just talk about, so in the in the winter it's like the light can.
sophia	The white one.
bruce	The white can?
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	And that makes it?
sophia	Like it takes in the energy, and lets out cold air in the air.
bruce	Oh. So it, eh eh, I see. So it's sort of sucking up all the energy.
sophia	Yeah, Uh huh.
bruce	And, and so why is the earth whiter in the in the winter?
sophia	Um because like the snow it's white so then the snow takes in all the heat and it absorbs it.
bruce	Mhm.
sophia	And the black can, or like when it's in the summer it's like um the black can and then like reflects the ener, the um the sun, the heat of the sun.
bruce	Okay. Okay. So,  so let's just talk about Chicago for a second.
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	So in Chicago in the winter it's colder
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	Because?
sophia	Like cause there's um the snow and uh like the snow, or like there other resources  I'm not really sure what they are, but the snow to me is like um the like the white can, and the white can which is like absorbing the energy and the heat of the sun, and taking it all in and letting out something else, I don't know what they let out but
bruce	Okay. So if there was no snow, does that mean it should be pretty hot here?
sophia	Yeah.
bruce	So, why is it like some days, like today there isn't that much snow on the ground, but it's still
sophia	Like windy.
bruce	Yeah.
sophia	And cold.
bruce	Mhm.
sophia	Um, I think because like the wind um like the wind it's like taking it like from the lake, the lake there's like water and then the wind's coming and it makes it colder.
bruce	Okay.
sophia	It's like taking the winds- lakes- or the water from the
bruce	Okay, and that doesn't happen in the summer?
sophia	Well, sometimes that does happen, and sometimes it doesn't.
bruce	So, so you're saying in the winter we have more snow, and that makes it colder.
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	So, why is there more snow in the winter?
sophia	Um, because like I don't really know like the snow comes down so.
bruce	It just comes down.
sophia	Yeah, I don't know.
bruce	You don't know why it comes
sophia	No.
bruce	Sometime of the year and not
sophia	yeah.
bruce	and not other times.
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	Okay, uh, so, so understand that, um, some kids when I ask about this, um, to explain the seasons, talk talk about how the earth moves and how it moves around the sun.
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	Have you ever heard anything like that?
sophia	Well, I know it does like the when the like space is supposedly  it's cold up there and like when the earth is like far away from the sun when it goes around it, like it goes, um it's far away from it, and so then it's like just all the space around it it's so cold.
bruce	Could you just say that again?
sophia	Like when the the earth is rotating around the sun, there's a point where it goes like far away from the sun so it's like closer like more space and like and less sun. And then like when it gets closer to the sun that's when the summer comes.
bruce	Okay. Could you draw a picture of what you just said?
sophia	Yeah, Sure
bruce	
sophia	Thank you. So then the sun  and then there's the earth's, I don't really know where it's in, but like it goes around it, and so then there's a point where it goes like like farther like if this is the closest it goes and then see the closest part, and then it's apart, like when it goes over here it's like a little bit farther than from this space.
bruce	Okay, and which is summer?
sophia	So like yeah so summer would be like when it's closer to the sun, and it's getting farther away, and it's like supposedly space is colder.
bruce	Mhm.
sophia	It's cold. And so like the it's like where it hits a point like where it's like really cold and then that's when like I think that the snow comes.
bruce	Okay. So the space, it's out in colder space out here?
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	Okay. Um, so this is, so this is another kind of explanation of the seasons. It's
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	How does this relate to the one you just gave?
sophia	So like it's uh, like this part of the - this like when it's over here it's like the white can and then when it's like over here it's the black can cause like the snow is coming down from the cold air of space so then it snows and it gets colder, and over here it's really close and then it's like um like it doesn't absorb the heat it just like bounces it back. So, like if you were wearing a black sweater then it would like be more likely that you were it's really hot, if wore it in the summer. But like if you were wear like a white sweater it probably would be like not really that much hot.
bruce	Okay. So, I understand the thing about wearing the sweater. So here the earth the space is black so that means it's not absorbing much of the sun.
sophia	Like it absorbs like yeah it just like bounces it back. So like it reflecting the sun into the heat of the sun into the earth.
bruce	Right into the Earth.
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	So, but, I thought, wait it was, it's the the white that reflects
sophia	It absorbs it.
bruce	Oh. The white absorbs it.
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	So it's absorbing it and  um, making it
sophia	Like it absorbs it and doesn't take the heat into the earth.
bruce	Um, One last thing about this is, have you ever heard that when it's winter like in Chicago, it could be summer in different part of the earth. Have you ever heard that before?
sophia	
bruce	No, it doesn't sound familiar to you.
sophia	No.
bruce	 Okay, I was, we'll come back to this in a moment but let me tell you, I want to ask you a slightly different question. Um, so we were talking about here in Chicago it's sometimes warmer and it's summer and in winter it's sometimes, it's colder, but there are some parts of the earth, but there are some parts of the earth that are always hot, like Florida
sophia	And Africa, like Africa's like, cause uh earth it's like rotating and it's moving the countries or the continents around so it's like it switches the heat
bruce	Mhm.
sophia	Like if the earth like this part over here it's North America and the South America so it's hot, and then like it turns around when it's rotating, and it's like now it switches to like Africa right there so it's going to be like summer.
bruce	Oh, so you are you saying now why it can be
sophia	Like hotter in other places.
bruce	Yeah, yeah. Okay, so can you just say that again?
sophia	So
bruce	Would it help to draw another picture?
sophia	Yeah, I guess so. If this was the sun and then this is back where it was, and then the earth is right here, so this would be North America and South America. And it's like so this is when it's closest and then it switches to Africa or England or something kind of.
bruce	I see.
sophia	So then it's North America and South America are now on this side so then it's farther away from the sun. And now this one's
bruce	Oh, okay. Okay. So this is different then what you were saying a minute ago I think.
sophia	Mhm.
bruce	Okay. Um. . So, so, one oth, maybe another question I want to ask you about this then, is, um, how does this relates to day and night?
sophia	Um, well, I think that in the the day, well the sun is out and then like it's switching with to the moon. So then like instead of the sun, it takes away the sun, and then like they switch places like if the moon is like over here and the sun is down here, then it would be rotating around the night and then the day.
bruce	So, so wait, so the earth is spinning like this , the earth is around like this  and what are the sun and moon doing?
sophia	Like there like just switching places, I don't, I don't really, I didn't, I didn't learn that, how they, how the sun and the moon changes.
bruce	So you don't know where the sun -  where does the sun go when it changes places.
sophia	Uh huh.
bruce	You just don't know.
sophia	Uh huh.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	Okay, okay, um.  So I wanna, that's good, I wanna go back to Florida and Alaska though, so you told me so here it's like summer in Chicago, and then winter in Chicago when it's on the other. But, Alaska is like always cold. And Florida is like always hot. So why is that?
sophia	Oh, well, I think that since like Alaska's down here, and it barely like switches to the sun, so there's very little sun to it, it's like hiding it. And then um the space is just like out here, this is all the space, it's like closer to space than the sun. And then like Florida it's like out there, it's like um I don't really know how to explain it, it's like closer to the sun or something.
bruce	An, so, and, why is it closer to the sun?
sophia	Cause it's like on the North America and it's like North America isn't really hiding like like it's um here it's on the bottom but it's like outside in the middle. 
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
