<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>jacob</PNAME>
<INAME>herb</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
    <SEASONS>
herb	 So the first question I want to ask you is why do you think it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
jacob	 Well it's because of the Earth's... I don't know if was the Earth's rotation or it's axis.  When the Earth's at a certain angle from the sun then the light, er the heat from the sun shines only on a certain area on the Earth and the other side doesn't have as much sun so it's not as warm.  So when it's shining... the other... the area the sun is on, the area it's shining on the most it will be the hottest area 
herb	 Okay.  Is that explaining, actually can you draw me a picture of that?  Of what you just described?
jacob	 Okay.  This would be the hot area.  This area would be colder.  Then the equator is always a little warmer.
herb	 Can you draw me the equator? 
jacob	   And then the heat will just follow the equator.
herb	 Now does the Earth...Does the Earth spin?
jacob	 It spins on its axis and it rotates around ... it goes around the sun also. 
herb	 Okay, so it does both?
jacob	Yeah.
jacob	 That creates, I believe night and day, how which area is shining on the sun is day and the other one is night when the sun (sets).
herb	 Okay, and usually it's colder at night than when it is in the day
jacob	 Yeah 
herb	 So you're saying it's the same thing that causes day and night that causes winter and summer? 
jacob	 Umm,...also because of the moon comeing in front of the sun really causes night, somehow, a little more than how it causes the seasons.
herb	Umm, could you say that again?
jacob	Well, when the moon comes around it blocks out the sun's light, that also creates night
herb	 That also creates night
jacob	 So even all over the earth it would be night
herb	So sometimes the night's caused by the rotation of the Earth, sometimes it's caused by the moon? 
jacob	Well, I think it's mainly caused by the moon cause With the moon spinning, at a certain time it will always block out the sun, and the rotation of the Earth around the sun, then the sun, it would be causing the seasons that way (gestures over drawing throughout here)
herb	 What's causing the seasons?
jacob	Um, when it rotates around the sun (gestures in a big circle indicating revolution)
herb	Okay.  So are you talking about the winter summer thing?
jacob	 Yeah.
herb	Okay, so is that the same thing as this though?  The way you just described it to me before?
jacob	Pretty much, but as it spins and it goes around it turns the day and night (gestures), the day and night idea when the moon comes in front, that really, that somewhat causes a change in temperature but mainly because when it spins around and wherever the sun is hitting, that usually causes seasons. 
herb	Okay.  Have you heard that, for instance, like when it's summer in Chicago, it's winter somewhere else? 
jacob	Umm, yeah
herb	Okay, like winter in Australia or something like that?
jacob	Yeah, like at the opposite end of the earth.  Because here in the United States, (gesturing over drawing) if the heat's directly on that area, then the other side would not be getting as much 
herb	 Can you draw me a picture of where the US would be on your Earth?
jacob	 Here would be US , here would be Canada, South America, Mexico
herb	 You said when it's summer in America, where is it winter? 
jacob	 Probably be in the end of the Earth, around here. (seems to be indicating the side away from the sun.
herb	 Where's that?
jacob	 Umm, like around Japan and...what was it, and around Russia and things like that.
herb	 Okay, so when it's summer in Chicago is it summer in South America?
jacob	Well, this whole section (indicates the side facing the sun) would be summer cause the sun is shining this whole half of the Earth except for like Antarctica (points to north pole) which in the summer is always cold, I think Antarctica is here (points to south pole), even there are like days on the daytime it's very, they don't have very much daytime, it's usually night in Antarctica, I believe.
herb	 Uh huh, and why is that?
jacob	 Because it's at the bottom of the Earth and not as much sunlight comes there
herb	 Okay.
herb	 What about up here?  Same thing?  [Or different?]
jacob	 [Yeah.]
herb	 Can you draw me another picture of the Earth and the sun?  Maybe on a fresh piece of paper.  Show me how the Earth goes around the sun.
jacob	  The sun here and the Earth right here and it just follows around the sun in a certain pattern
herb	 Okay.  Umm, and the Earth is also spinning on its axis at the same time? (gestures over the drawing)
jacob	 Yeah, at the same time
herb	 And how about the moon?
jacob	 The moon spins, rotates around the Earth and every time at a certain time it will be right here covering part of the Earth.
herb	 Okay.  But is the moon bigger or smaller than the Earth?
jacob	 It's um, smaller.
herb	 Okay, so is it going to be enough to cause night for the whole Earth?
jacob	Not for the whole Earth.  Cause even though it's night on one part of the Earth, it's day in the other in the opposite.
herb	 So when the moon is over here and causing night on part of the Earth, where is it daytime?
jacob	 It will be daytime, I believe, at the opposite end. 
herb	 Can you shade in the area you think it's daytime?
jacob	 I believe this is day and this is night.
herb	 Okay, so it's going to be night right here, and day right here
jacob	 Mm hmm
herb	 How can it be day right here when it's not facing the sun?
jacob	 Well, the sun's light can spread all over the Earth, it's just the moon really blocks
herb	 Oh, okay. So the sun...
jacob	 It's like with that lantern thing, even though the lantern could be facing the wall, the back of the wall could still be lit, the light will spread all over. 
herb	Okay, let's go back to this for a second.  How does the light spread all over?  (goes back to drawing made during the flashlight part of the interview)
jacob	 Well, the rays from the flashlight bounce off of things
herb	 They bounce off the wall, right? You've got something standing behind the lamp and it could still be lit up because it's bouncing off the wall.  So that's like the same thing that's happening here? 
jacob	 Pretty much, I guess. 
herb	 What's it bouncing off of?
jacob	Uh (long pause here while he thinks). I'm not really sure actually. Maybe the sun's light just spreads all over and lighting everything and it just includes that area.
herb	So if you had, say you had a really big room again and you have a flashlight and a tennis ball, and you shine a light on the tennis ball. (he's gesturing carefully here)  Would the back of the ball be lit up too?   If the back wall was really really far away?
jacob	I don't think so, but I'm not sure. Maybe it's the opposite.  This is night, and this is day at this time, and it spins around and it's the opposite
herb	 So it's the other way around.
jacob	 It's probably the other way around.  But this would be dark and this would be day.
    </SEASONS>
    <CLIMATE>
herb	 Okay, so I have another question about this.  On any particular day, where do you think it's warmer?  Do you think it's warmer in Florida, or do you think it's warmer in Alaska?
jacob	Well, I believe it would be warmer in Florida.  I know it would be warmer in Florida because Florida is closer to the equator.   And the sun's heat goes directly to the equator, I believe, heating everything around the equator.
herb	 Okay.  Why does the sun's light go directly to the equator?
jacob	 I'm not exactly sure, I just read that out of a book.
herb	 Oh really? 
jacob	 That it's always warmer around the equator. 
herb	So what if it's winter in Florida and summer in Alaska? 
jacob	Winter's in Florida is usually like 60, 70 degrees but Alaska is really always cold 
herb	 Right, even in the summertime
jacob	 Yeah. 
herb	 So you think it would still be warmer in Florida. 
jacob	 Yeah.
herb	 So it's basically warmer all year round. 
jacob	 Yeah.
herb	 Good.
    </CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
