<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>jill</PNAME>
<INAME>betsy</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>cf</TCODE>
<BODY>
    <SEASONS>
betsy	Can you tell me why its warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
jill	It's because the sun um, we rotate around the sun like in an axis, but its not a perfect circle, and when, and then like, or not an axis like we orbit, its like not a perfect circle its like egg shaped almost but not very noticeable and the sun, the earth is on an axis on that orbit that when it goes around like theres one part thats closer and one part thats farther so thats kind of , that explains why it warmer near the equator cause thats where the sun hits it the most, but it depends on how the orbit is, like if, in the summer the sun is closer to the earth because we're, like the, the , our orbits circle is not like a perfect circle around the sun, its not like, this is the sun, its not like there (hand motions) its like that kind of (lots of hand motions)
betsy	ok
betsy	ok, ok, yknow maybe
jill	heres the sun, and that one, so this would be the summer this is winter,
betsy	and its uh, cause
jill	cause when the earth is closer the sun rays hit it like closer, so its hot
betsy	ok um, I don't know , I've heard that when its winter in the US its summer in Australia, have you heard that?
jill	no
betsy	no? yeah, I was just wondering. Yeah, that's what I hear, so I was just wondering how that would work given what weve talked about a description?
jill	um, um, I th maybe um, where australia is placed on the earth the sun hits it less but I don't think it, so i think its just colder there, but I don't think its actually like ss.. I think the whole earth is at summer at one time, like it goes together but where australia is placed it gets weird seasons becasue of that, like the temperature of the seasons are different
betsy	ok, yeah, I think I understand, ok uh, the next question is why its generally warmer in Florida and colder in Alaska, I mean you were talking about some of the stuff before, but I'll ask you more specific
    </SEASONS>
    <CLIMATE>
jill	oh, cause its where the equator is, Florida is closer to the equator and the equator is where the sun hits earth the most
betsy	ok can you draw me a picture of that so I remember
jill	this is the earth this is the equator,
betsy	sure
jill	this is florida
jill	um, and since and that's where the sun hits... where the, the earth rotates on its orbit, so where it rotates that's where the sun hits it the most, right here, so
betsy	ok
jill	like alaska, is here and its not gonna get as much sun or as much warmth the sun gives off, as florida would
betsy	ok can you show me where or how the suns light hits the earth? The directions or how it works
jill	ok, this is the sun over here, I mean it does go like that, but the warmest part goes like here and it like hits the most
betsy	and it hits the most because its like the equator? 
jill	no, well that's because, where, the, no where the earth orbits while  its rotating that's like the middle line where the sun like sees the most, where its closer
betsy	mm hmm, so its closer in the equator and not as close for alaska.
jill	yeah
    </CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
