<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>kelly</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	 So my first especially difficult question is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter.
kelly	 Because, because the earth is, at summer, the earth is more close to the sun and in the winter it is far to the sun, because the Earth's orbit is not a exact circle.
bruce	 mmm  mm hmm.  So this seems like a good thing to draw a picture of. So let's draw a picture of this
kelly	 Here's the sun  and here's the Earth at the summer and here's the Earth at the winter. 
bruce	 uh huh
kelly	 And when it's winter, it takes longer, it takes the sun rays will take longer to get there and that's why it would be so cold and at summer the light rays will travel more faster to the Earth and that is why it's so warm
bruce	 And why does traveling faster make it so that it's warmer?
kelly	 When the light rays hit the Earth, any objects going to absorb the heat, absorb the sun rays and give it back as heat and that takes a long period of time so when the sun rays get there faster it warms up maybe quicker than winter
bruce	 When the sun rays take longer?  
kelly	Yeah.
bruce	Umm, where are we in each of those pictures?  Can you put a little dot where we are?
kelly	
bruce	 Why did you draw us over here  for winter?
kelly	 Because umm, the hemishphere, when we're having summer, our hemisphere will be facing the sun, and when we're having winter, the other part of the hemisphere is having summer and we're having winter.
bruce	 Oh, so over here, some people are having summer even though the Earth is further away here?
kelly	 Yeah. 
bruce	Okay.  So it seems like you said 2 things are going on now.  How far you are from the sun and this thing about where the hemispheres are.  Is that right?
kelly	 Yeah.
bruce	So did you just figure out that last part as you were going or something?
kelly	 Yeah 
bruce	 So why is that, what was your thinking there?
kelly	Because when the Earth is rotating and if we're having winter, the other part in like Europe or some other place it will be having summer because we're facing away from the sun and they are facing toward the sun
bruce	 mm hmm.  So how about this part about being closer and further away - does that part still matter also? 
kelly	 Yeah, I think
bruce	 so how is, the Earth is going around like this, right?   What's it also doing here?  Is it 
kelly	 Rotating
bruce	 What does this all have to do with day, night, day and night?  Doesn't the Earth moving around have something to do with day and night too?
kelly	 mm hmm
bruce	 So how does that work?
kelly	 The day would be hotter and the night will be cooler
bruce	 okay.  So in the day we're pointed toward the sun and at night, away?
kelly	 yeah.
bruce	 How does that relate to summer though, I mean winter?  Cause in the winter aren't we always pointed away?
kelly	 Yeah, but at night it will be like fat (fast?)- it will take, it will be shorter, and in winter it will be moving slower
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	 Uh huh.  Okay.  Another question.  Now a slightly different question.  Let me write your name on here.  We were just sort of talking about why it's hotter in the summer, like here in Chicago, and colder in the winter.  But it's also true that in some places, it's just generally warmer and in other places it's generally colder, like's it's generally pretty hot in Florida and pretty cold in Alaska.  Why is that true?
kelly	Because Alaska is farther away from the equator, and some part of Florida is touching near the equator.
bruce	 Ok.  And why does nearly touching, why does being near the equator make something warmer?
kelly	 Because the equator is the hottest place on Earth
bruce	 But what makes it so hot, I guess, is what I'm wondering?  Why is the equator so hot?
kelly	  Maybe because the sun rays are hitting directly on it
bruce	 mm hmm.  That's sort of a guess you're making? 
kelly	 yeah.
bruce	 Can you draw a picture of what you mean by the sun's rays hitting more directly on the equator
kelly	  Here's the sun.  And when the light rays travel to the equator  it spreads out and maybe it would take, the light rays maybe it will take longer to get up here 
bruce	 So this is the equator?
kelly	 Yeah.
bruce	 And where's Alaska and where's Florida? 
kelly	 I think here's Alaska and here's Florida
bruce	 So, sorry, what were you saying?  So it takes longer to get up?
kelly	 Yeah, so it will, the sun's rays will take longer to get up here and then over here
bruce	 And what's this down here?  Isn't this part down here even closer than the equator?
kelly	 Um, no because when the sun rays hit the Earth, it will spread out, and here's the North pole and over here's the South pole, it will be colder there 
bruce	 I'm just wondering, the way you've drawn this picture, it looks like the South Pole is closer to the sun than the equator.  Is that what you meant to draw?
kelly	 No.
bruce	 Am I just misunderstanding?
kelly	  I don't know. 
bruce	  Let me ask it this way.  Suppose this is the sun and this is the Earth.  Can you point to where the North Pole and South Pole are?
kelly	 Up here and down there 
bruce	 And where's the equator?
kelly	 In the middle
bruce	 Kind of like here?
kelly	 Yeah.
bruce	 And the sun's/ why's the equator hotter?
kelly	 Because the sun's rays are hitting directly on there and then it spreads out.
bruce	 So it hits there and then it kind of spreads out up and down?  So no rays go up here?   They more kind of hit here  and then spread out?
kelly	 Yeah.
bruce	 Okay.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
