<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>kimberley</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	 So here's my hard question.  I want to know why it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter.
kimberley	 Because of the way the Earth is facing as it like goes around and stuff.  The sun hits it more during the summer so it's hotter, and then it's facing farther away during the winter.
bruce	 I think this is something that really needs a picture.
kimberley	 
bruce	   Let's do it, we can do it.
kimberley	 Well, okay....  Well, okay...okay, well, here's Earth and here's where we live.  And the sun is up over here.    And during summer, it faces and hits it directly so it's hotter .  If it were winter and we were over here it would hit, it wouldn't hit it.  And it would be hotter, uh, colder.
bruce	 I see.  And how is the Earth moving?
kimberley	 It 's revolving around the sun.  >
bruce	 It's moving like this?  .  
kimberley	 Yeah.
bruce	 Is it also spinning?
kimberley	 Yeah.  It's...Cause each circle is a day and it revolves all around
bruce	 Okay.  And it's here in the summer - where is it  Where's the Earth when it's winter?
kimberley	It will probably be around on this side   But turning it around, this would probably be where we were in winter 
bruce	 I see.  So you said it's going like this day and night?
kimberley	 Yeah
kimberley	 Well, maybe hitting the top of Earth we'll be at the bottom so we'll be cold the whole time.
bruce	 Oh, I see.  So in the summer we're kind of up here going around like this  and in the winter we're down here going around like that?
kimberley	 Because of [the way it's tilted]  I don't know exactly how it //
bruce	 [So in the winter] uh huh
bruce	 It has something to do with when we're tilted?
kimberley	[nods] //The axis
bruce	// So in the winter we might also be over here kind of...Is that what you're saying?
kimberley	 Yeah 
bruce	 On the bottom and going around.   And in the summer we're kind of on the top and going around.
kimberley	
bruce	 How does the Earth get flipped over? 
kimberley	 How? 
kimberley	 Umm...Okay, then we were at the top of this the whole time.
bruce	 Oh, okay, so now we're at //
kimberley	 //I'm not sure
bruce	 Sorry, you go ahead
kimberley	 I'm not sure how, but wherever it is before,  that part is not getting any sunlight in the winter.  Or not much.
bruce	 Okay.  Okay.  So you have some idea of how it works.  This part up here is getting more sun in the summer.
kimberley	 Yeah.
bruce	 And why again does this part get more sun than this part?
kimberley	 Because the rays are hitting it and it's tilted more and the sun's rays are going like this and it's tilted so that are gets all the sunlight. 
bruce	 So is it like, here's the sun  and here's the earth and its sort of tilted .
kimberley	 Yeah.
bruce	 So is that it - this part at the top gets more sun?
kimberley	 Yeah.
bruce	 And why is that?  Cause...Is it closer or something?
kimberley	 Because that's the direction the rays are going.
bruce	 This direction?
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	 Okay. I want to ask you a related question about this.  So we sort of talked about, we picked us in Chicago and we said it's warmer in the summer here and colder in the winter.  But it's also true that some places are kind of generally warmer than other places.  Like Florida is in general warmer than Alaska.
kimberley	 Yeah
bruce	 So why is that?
kimberley	 Because they're more toward the equator, and that's always warm.
bruce	 Uh huh, and why is the equator always?
kimberley	 I'm not sure.  Because I think it gets hit by the sun all the time no matter if it's summer or winter.
bruce	 The equator gets hit by the sun sort of all the time?
kimberley	 Yeah.
bruce	 Is there a way we could talk about that with this picture?
kimberley	 No.
bruce	 Not really?
kimberley	 No.
bruce	 Is there a picture you could draw that would make sense of that?  Here, I'll give you another sheet.
kimberley	
kimberley	 Well, here's the equator, and it's hitting,  it's still hitting part of the equator and this is having summer.  But if it did the opposite, only  the bottom.  And this  well, this is in winter.  And it's also hitting the equator, so it stays warm like that
bruce	 I see.  Okay,  Okay, that makes sense.  Sure.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
