<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>kurt</PNAME>
<INAME>herb</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
herb	 Why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
kurt	 Cause the Earth is turning at a tilt, and when it faces the sun it's summer and then when it keeps turning it goes from fall to winter 
herb	 So in the wintertime, what's happening?
kurt	 It's kind of, the Earth is tilted, so like, say the winter time in Chicago, like we'd be down here and the sun's up here  and it wouldn't be facing the sun.
herb	 It wouldn't be facing the sun at all?
kurt	 Well, it would turn on a daily thing, but doesn't it take it  uh, 365 days for it to turn once?
herb	 For what to turn once?
kurt	 Mm hmm
kurt	 Mm hmm
herb	 Turn it around what?
kurt	 Like-
kurt	 Yeah, just like on an orbit
herb	 On it..
kurt	 On its axis.  Yeah.  Around the sun.
herb	 Yeah, could you draw me a picture of what you mean.
kurt	 Um, yeah, alright.  In the winter say like America was down here 
herb	 Alright
kurt	 The sun would be kind of here
herb	 Uh huh
kurt	 And umm It's kind of like, when it goes around 
herb	 Mm hmm
kurt	 It's still moving  that's what makes it sunlight during the day and stuff but it's just cold cause we're kind of faced downward 
herb	 We're kind of faced downward. 
kurt	 Away from the sun.
herb	 Mm hmm.  So if it's faced downward, does that mean there are some other places facing upward, kind of?
kurt	 Other countries?
herb	 Other countries.
kurt	 Yeah, other countries are facing upward.
herb	 So if it's winter in Chicago, where is it summer?
kurt	 Probably in...kinda in Antarctica?  No, not Antarctica...
herb	 Like Australia?
kurt	 Yeah.  Kinda downward, tilting up, like how it's....  I was trying to think.  I wouldn't say Europe.  Cause Europe also gets cold.  
herb	 What gets cold?
kurt	 Cause I wouldn't say Europe cause it's kind of like on the same, kind of on the same even but downward cause it kind of tilts the Earth, all the countries that are down here, like Australia, would go up.
herb	 Okay.
kurt	 Cause, like the sun, it would face the sun.
herb	 Okay, that makes sense to me.  That seems right.
herb	 So can you draw me a quick picture of how the Earth moves around the sun?
kurt	 Like  it goes around the sun and back to its normal orbit.
herb	 Okay.  Is it the same distance from the sun at all points?
kurt	 Mm hmm.
kurt	 Mm hmm
herb	 So is the sun right in the middle of it?  Or is it kind of off center?
kurt	 So like here's the sun.  The planets are kind of going out .  They kind of just turn around.  That's why Pluto's so cold cause it's the farthest out. 
herb	 Right,  right, right, right.
kurt	 Out of the planets, cause we're like the third planet out from the sun that's, we're able to live 
herb	 But do they all go around the sun in the same way?  In the same shape?
kurt	 In the same?  Do they all go around in circles?
herb	 Do they all go around in perfect circles?
kurt	 Oh no.
herb	 What shape do they go around in?
kurt	 Umm
herb	 You can just draw it if you want.
kurt	 Let's say the planets...//
herb	 Why don't we look at it from the top down we can look at it from the top
kurt	 Well, I think they probably would go in circles cause I was looking at... I used to be at Queen of All Saints last year 
herb	 Okay
herb	 Okay.
kurt	 And that's what I learned so that's what I'm guessing.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
herb	 Okay...Alrighty.  I'm going to change gears again.  Now we're going to talk a little about heat and temperature.  Actually, let me backtrack for a second...Right...Sorry, one more question about this stuff, and then we'll move on.  So what's warmer, Florida or Alaska?
kurt	 Florida
herb	 Why?
kurt	 Because it's um, because it's closer to the equator, I'm guessing, below the equator
herb	 And what does that do?
kurt	 It's like, kind of tropical weather down there, and I think it's caused by global warming
herb	 Okay, is there any reason why it would be warmer down by the equator than by Alaska?
kurt	 Umm, cause it's kind of the center of the Earth, I think, and it's kind of warmer down there, it's warmer down there, I guess, kind of
herb	 It's just warmer?
kurt	 yeah.
kurt	 Um, yes.  From Chicago, always.
herb	 Okay.
herb	 Right
kurt	In the summertime it's kind of off and on.  But in the winter, in Florida it's always warmer.  
herb	 What if it's summer in Alaska and winter in Florida?
kurt	 In winter in Florida...Florida.
herb	 Florida's still warmer, even if it's wintertime?
kurt	 mm hmm
herb	 Okay, Great.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
