<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>leslie</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	  // mmm
bruce	Now I'm ready for my actually really hard questions even harder questions. First thing I want to know here is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
leslie	 Umm well, umm, you know times savings?  //  //  you know? like in the summer --when you have--
bruce	   //  // mm-hmm
bruce	 Daylight Savings time?
leslie	Yeah, daylight savings time in the summer we have more time, like, with, like, daylight and that's why it gets warmer.  And with the circulation of the earth  and the axis that it's on just has to do with like summer and winter .  >
leslie	And it depends on where we are on the earth, like if you look at, umm, India, it's toward the equator, you know?  //  so it's like always's hot.   So if you go up north then it gets colder because there's just, like, I can't really say less sun, but it kind of has to do with that and there's just a lot of snow and, like ice cause it's colder up there.
bruce	 mmm And the snow and ice make it colder?
leslie	 Yeah.
bruce	 There's something like less sun and snow and ice?
leslie	 Yeah.
bruce	 okay.
leslie	 Cause if you look at pictures of, like, Antarctica or whatever// then like, it showsyou can't really say there's no sun, but it's just cold there //  because it's not close to the equator
bruce	 // mm-hmm   //mm-hmm
bruce	 mm-hmm...  Okay.  So there's a couple of different things you said, so I want to get at the different pieces. You said, just then you said there's something about if it's closer to the equator, it's warmer.  Umm, let's pick one place, though.  Let's take like about here in Chicago.
leslie	 Okay
bruce	And in winter and summer it gets colder; it's colder in the winter and warmer in the summer  //  so why is it for just for Chicago that it gets colder and warmer
leslie	  // mm-hmm
leslie	 Well, umm, it's kinda like with our atmosphere, umm, cause we're not that close to the equator but we're not freezing, so we have like, like when it turns summer, like it has like more time with the sun so it has more time to heat up the earth (GEST-1), and so, that's, it's just with the side that we're on .  It depends on, like we're; since the earth rotates , we're on the other side from summer , you know?
bruce	 I see.  So could you draw a picture of that?
leslie	 Okay .  Like, here's the Earth and like, here's, like, our country. //  Umm here's the equator  and here's the other countries .
bruce	 // mm-hmm.
bruce	well drawn
leslie	 Then the axis is like right there .  Like we're, cause that's like; on the other side of the world  is like summer, on their side , you know?
bruce	 So where is it summer right now?
leslie	 On the other side //of the earth
bruce	 // And where are we?
leslie	 We're here , and we're , like,  by the winter part ...  I don't really know how to explain it.
bruce	 Where's the sun?
leslie	 Um, the sun is right here. 
bruce	 So, and we're right here now?   Let's draw a little stick figure where we are.   So this is the winter, and where would  // 
leslie	 But see,  actually, the sun is like right there  and it's focusing on this side .  Like, the other side.  Of the Earth .  So it's like coming down on that part.   Like, if you // 
bruce	 Is this a sort of a three dimensional picture? 
leslie	 Yeah.  It's supposed to be.
bruce	  Is like the Earth here , kind of, and the sun is kind of behind it?   Something like that?
leslie	 Yeah. 
bruce	 Okay, umm..
leslie	  Like it's I don't really know how to draw ano that's like a box. 
bruce	 What say this is the earth and this is the sun.   Okay, so where are // we?
leslie	  // We're on this side. 
leslie	 Yeah, cause we're //  on the side where it's like darker, you know?  Cause the side of the sun has like the heat and stuff, you know?   Which is summer.
bruce	// okay
bruce	  I see.  And where are we; so and when it's summer we're around this side?   And that's because, the earth is spinning around like that? 
leslie	 Well, I don't really know how it goes totally, but; I don't know.  It just depends on the time of the year, you know?  //   I'm not really; I'm not for sure if it's like, it like spins  for like seasons, butI don't know.
bruce	 But somehow we have to get around to this side. 
leslie	 Yeah, like towards the sun.   Cause the sun doesn't totally move , you know?
bruce	 Does the Earth move? 
leslie	 Yeah.
bruce	 How; so how does it move?
leslie	 It turns on a circle  , like, it's on an axis, so it just like turns .
bruce	 So it kind of stays right here  and spins around like this?   Does it also move all the way around like this? 
leslie	 Yeah
bruce	 How does it do that?
leslie	 It turns like that. 
bruce	 And it goes around the sun?
leslie	 Yeah.
bruce	 Let's say we're right here this is where we are in the winter.   Where would the Earth be in the summer?
leslie	 Like over here  
bruce	 The opposite side? 
leslie	 Yeah.
bruce	 Okay.
bruce	 Oh, I seeHow does that relate to when it's day and night?
leslie	 Umm, like when it turns?   Like, cause, like, I think the seasons have to do with going around the Earth , but when it turns it's like day, night,  you know.
bruce	 I see.  But somehow it also has to do with, the seasons seem like they have to do with turning around like this because it gets you pointing to the sun or away. 
leslie	 Yeah.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	 Okay, let me ask you about the other there was another piece to what you said before.  So we just talked about why - why it's colder, why it gets colder and warmer in Chicago.  But there are also places that are generally warmer or generally colder, like it's generally warmer in Florida and colder in Alaska.  //   And why is that?
leslie	  // mm-hmm.   
leslie	 Umm, because it depends on like, cause the equator is like directly in the middle , you know? //  It's like an invisible line that goes around the Earth .  And like, umm, India's, like, in the middle of it. 
bruce	 In the middle of the equator?
leslie	 Yeah.  And so it's warmer there.  Like in the middle of the earth is just ; like if you could dig inside the Earth , it like; it's all magma, like right in the middle .  And so like the middle of it like around  is like the warmest.  Like if you go to the top or the bottom, that's like the farthest away from the heat in the middle .  So...
bruce	 So, what makes the equator be so warm? 
leslie	 Umm, well, because,  like I don't know.   Cause the circle of , like, magma and hot stuff like in the middle of the Earth  is just like around there , and so it's like, since it's like that,  all around it's just the circle.     
bruce	 I see.  So it has most to do with the magma that's inside the Earth.   So the seasons have to do with the sun  and where we are with respect to the sun  //  but the being hotter near the equator is because of the magma and not because of the sun?   Or does it have something to do with the sun also?
leslie	  // Yeah
leslie	 Yeah, also.  Like, meaning with like both, you know?  Kinda like with the Earth  and the ground  and like what's inside the Earth  and like what's outside the Earth , like where the sun is , you know?
bruce	 So why; the sun tends to make it very warm at the equator? 
leslie	 Yeah
bruce	 So why is that?
leslie	 UmmI don't know.
bruce	 So is there something like here , like with the sun  would tend to make the equator warmer than the north and south poles?
leslie	 Well, like since it's on an axis , like the rays hit at kind of like an angle, and so it hits like there .  And then like here  it just mainly gets left out and that's why they're so cold.
bruce	 So it hits the equator
leslie	 The rays, since it's like mainly there , it just like doesn't really hit it as strong as like in the middle, you know? //   Cause it's farther away, since it's on an axis. 
bruce	  // I think so
bruce	 Uh-huh.  So maybe we could draw a picture.  So let's say this is kind of a side view of the sun and the earth.   Something like that.  Is that good?
leslie	 Yeah.
bruce	 So where would the axis be?
leslie	 Like this is the sun and it's like raying down , and then ,like, that's the axis , and ,like, here's the equator .
bruce	 That's the equator there?
leslie	Yeah.  And like, well it depends on how the axis is.  Like maybe the equator is like there , or something, you know?  And so like the rays are like right there, and they just shoot  and so it like takes them more time to go  to like, the like  ; the North pole and south pole .
bruce	 It really hits those places right away.   It hits them more directly, maybe? // Does that make sense?
leslie	 // Yeah.
bruce	 Okay.  That's it for this stuff. 
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
