<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>mark</PNAME>
<INAME>herb</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
herb	 First question I'd like to ask you is why is warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
mark	 Part because of the Earth's axis, uh, revolution around the sun.  It hits an angle, say... it's the Earth's axis, and sometimes the Earth,  this is the sun and this is the earth and it's like slanted this way  so it takes longer for it to reach and the sun's UV rays aren't as strong and it's also at an angle, it slants.
herb	 Why is it not as strong? 
mark	Cause it takes longer to travel.  It's weaker.
herb	 So you've got the sense that basically, the longer it takes light to travel, the weaker it gets?
mark	 Yeah.
herb	Okay. Can you draw me a picture of what the Earth looks like going around the sun?
mark	  Okay, this is the axis around and the Earth is right here.  And that's why, cause the Earth is slanted.  It takes longer to hit Earth. That's why it's colder in the north pole and colder in the south pole, cause it takes a long time and the equator is so hot.
herb	 Okay, so what does the slant look like?
mark	 The slant, the slant looks like
herb	 Can you draw the line?
mark	 It kind of slants this way if it's in winter time and it slants, say in summer, it goes around back and the Earth's here it slants forward
herb	 it slants forward?
mark	 So that's why we have hotter season and that's why around the world we have different seasons.  Say like we have winter here and probably like China somewhere having summer or something
herb	 Right.  And that's because at one point, you're tilted toward the sun and at another point you're tilted away?
mark	 Yeah.
herb	 Okay.  Um....okay in this picture can you point out to me where Chicago is?
mark	 It's wintertime, since Chicago is right here.  Cause wintertime it takes a long time and if it's Chicago, it should be right by the equator right there cause the sun shows.
herb	 Okay, so you think when it's summer, Chicago is closer to the equator?
mark	 No, Chicago is closer to the sun.
herb	 Oh, closer to the sun.  So it's tilted.
mark	 mm hmm.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
herb	 Gotcha.  One more question on this stuff. Do you think it's warmer in Florida or in Alaska?
mark	 Florida.
herb	 Okay.  Umm, can you tell me why you think that  is?
mark	 Cause Florida is right by the equator and the equator is like how a circle is and the equator sticks out the most and it takes less time for the sun to travel, but Alaska is all the way up north by the North pole so it comes up at a little bit more of an angle, more like a slant.
herb	 Okay.  So it's the same reason why the North pole is colder than the equator.
mark	 Yeah.
herb	 Okay, good.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
