<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>ovadya</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>cf</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	 So here's my first especially hard question.  I want to know why, why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter.
ovadya	 Because...it's colder in the winter because the Earth spins around and it's like close to the equator, in the winter.
bruce	What's close to the equator?  Sorry, I just didn't hear.
ovadya	 Uh, the su- the Earth when it spins around it's, doesn't get closer to the equator
bruce	 Uh huh
ovadya	And in the summertime, it does.  Cause it's hot by the equator.
bruce	 What gets close to the equator?
ovadya	 The Earth.
bruce	 I see.  Can you draw a picture of that?
ovadya	 
bruce	 So what's this you're drawing here?
ovadya	 This, this is like the United States and it like doesn't get close to the sun 
bruce	 Right now, it's not close to the sun? 
ovadya	 It is, it's summer, that's why.  Um, I don't know how to draw it.
bruce	 So what, last, so here you have the sun in it this time.  So what does the sun have to do with it?
ovadya	 The sun is warm and when the sun spins around, when it gets closer to the sun it is more heat.
bruce	 I see.  So wait - so how is this moving here again?
ovadya	 It spins  on an axis.
bruce	  Just like this?
bruce	 Okay.  Is there any other way it's moving too? Or it just spins like this?  
ovadya	 yeah.
bruce	 Okay.  Umm...and when it's closer, what was the idea again?
ovadya	 When it's closer, the sun is warmer.  Just like in the daytime it's warmer than it's night.
bruce	 uh huh.
bruce	 I see, so this right now is summer or winter, or you're not sure? 
ovadya	 Right now it's summer.
bruce	 So this is a picture of summer?
ovadya	 Yeah.
bruce	 And what would a picture of winter look like?
ovadya	 I'm not sure.
bruce	 You're not sure?  Okay.  But the basic idea is that somehow this spins  and that makes this closer and farther away.
ovadya	 Yeah.
bruce	 Okay.  And the Earth is spinning like this.  Does the Earth- does the sun also move around too? 
ovadya	 No.
bruce	 The sun stays in place?  Does the Earth, in addition to spinning, does it move around?
ovadya	 No.
bruce	 So it sort of stays here and that makes it summer and winter.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce    Okay.  Okay, so that's about what makes it summer and winter.  So it gets, even like here in Chicago in the summer it's really hot, and in the winter it's really cold.  But there are also some parts of the Earth that are always really hot or some parts where it's always generally hotter and some parts are generally colder.  Like in Florida, it's pretty much all the time hotter than it is in Alaska.  So why is that?  Why is it hotter in Florida and colder in Alaska?
ovadya	 I think cause they're near the equator.  Florida is near the equator and Alaska's not.
bruce	 mm hmm
ovadya	 And it's warmer by the equator.
bruce	 Okay.  And why is it warm near the equator, do you think?
ovadya	 Cause it's right in the middle, and it's away from the south pole and the north pole.
bruce	 Uh huh.
ovadya	 It's colder at the bottom and the top.
bruce	 mm hmm.  I guess I'm sort of wondering what does, so how does being in the middle make it warm?
ovadya	 Cause you're not close to the poles.
bruce	 And the poles are just cold?
ovadya	 Yeah.
bruce	 What makes the poles cold then?
ovadya	 The sun doesn't reach over there, that much.
bruce	 I see.  I see.  Umm, and why doesn't the sun reach the poles as much?
ovadya	 Cause the sun stays in the same spot and the Earth stays the same way it is and it spins around and doesn't reach the poles that much.
bruce	 Do you think you could draw a picture of that?
ovadya	  These are the poles.  It spins around.  It doesn't reach.  The sun doesn't reach the poles that much, the light, the sunlight.
bruce	 So why isn't the sunlight reaching the poles?
ovadya	 I'm not sure.  That's why it's like, on the poles, they don't have, like in Antarctica, um, there's they have like less daylight than we do, all the time. cause in the winter we get less daylight too.
bruce	 mm hmm.  And do you know why that is?
ovadya	 
bruce	 Okay, that's the sun  and this is the Earth  and the North and South Pole are not getting so much light.
ovadya	 Yeah.
bruce	 Okay.   Isn't there - Is there some light going from here to the-
ovadya	 No.
bruce	 Just not very much goes there?
ovadya	 No.
bruce	 But it does go here? 
bruce	 And why, why is that?  Do you know?
ovadya	 I'm not sure.
bruce	 Okay.  Okay.  Now I'm done with these, these sorts of pictures.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
