<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>randy</PNAME>
<INAME>herb</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>cf</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>

herb	 Why do you think it's summer ...
randy	Because of the Earth's movement, right?
herb	 How do you mean?
randy	 Umm, like, the Earth turns on an axis and stuff.  And when it turns it's the angle of where the sun hits it.  And when it's wintertime, the sun, I mean the Earth, moves probably farther away or something. 
herb	 Okay.  Draw me a picture of that.  What's happening to the Earth.
randy	 Umm, okay.  The sun.  and here's the Earth, and it's kind of at an axis.  And I guess this is where the sun is over here.  I don't know how to start to kind of show it.
herb	 The earth turns XXX too?
randy	 Yeah.
herb	 What happens when that happens?
randy	 day and night.
herb	 Day and night.  So is day and night the same as summer and winter in this?  Is it the same thing that makes it happen?
randy	 I don't know.  That one actually, I don't know.
herb	 Okay.  Does the Earth - tell me how the Earth moves around.
randy	 uh, like...
herb	 How does the Earth XXX
randy	 Uh, around.
herb	 Okay, well, the Earth spins around 
randy	 yeah.
randy	 Oh yeah.  Like if the sun's up here, and like in a couple of months when the Earth moves I guess it will uh this point will be over here someplace. XXX
herb	 Does the Earth move in that direction or something?
randy	 ...Like what do you mean?
herb	 Like, uh did you learn about orbits?
randy	 yeah.  Somewhere I did.
herb	 Do you know what an orbit is?
randy	 The orbit is the rotation  of the Earth?
herb	 Rotation of the Earth how?
randy	 In relationship to the sun.
herb	 Does it go around the sun?
randy	 uh, I don't know.  I haven't talked about this stuff in a while.  Don't know.
herb	 How about the moon?
randy	 It goes around the sun, I mean goes around the Earth.
herb	 Okay, can you draw that - how does the moon go around the Earth?
randy	 It's uh, out here, and it  goes around it.
herb	 You're not sure if the Earth goes around the sun? 
randy	 I guess it has to if this one...or something.  I don't know.
herb	 Okay... Have you ever heard that when it's winter in Chicago, it's summer somewhere else?
randy	 Yeah.
herb	 Where is it summer when it's winter in Chicago?
randy	 Maybe Florida?
herb	 Okay.
randy	Did you mean a different country or something? It would be summer in ....Africa maybe or something?
herb	 Why Africa?
randy	 I don't know.  Cause it's farther away from the here or something?
herb	Okay.  Do you have any sense as to why it's summer in one place and winter in another place?
randy	 Uh, because... I don't know.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
herb	 Where is it warmer, Florida or Alaska?
randy	 Florida.
herb	 Why?
randy	 Because Florida is closer to the equator and Alaska is farther.
herb	 Okay.  Why does the equator matter?
randy	 I don't know.  I just heard that anything closer to the equator is warmer.  Maybe it's just South America.  So up here it gets cold
herb	 Okay.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
