<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>richard</PNAME>
<INAME>heather</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
heather	So I want to just ask you a general seasons question. Why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
richard	uh, its because of the angle of the earth I think, uh towards the sun and where you are on earth, that would make it warmer if you are turned toward the sun most of the time
heather	so, if we could draw, could you draw a little model? Like a little picture of the earth and the sun and maybe winter and summer lets say
richard	the sun is right here and over here the earth would be on an axis this way and it would still be on the same axis here so if we were over here it would be colder and if we were over here it would be hotter because your nearer the sun and you'd be farther away from the sun here, and if you were up here then it would like in between kind of
heather	so um, this is, did you say the summer?
richard	that would probably be the hottest, well I don't know if this would be the hottest or if it would be right here, but uh this would be the hotter area and this would be cooler
heather	ok so, this here is say us when its cold, is that what your saying?
richard	yeah
heather	so um, I have a question, so ok, this is us, so wheres like the equator on here? just ask out of curiousity.
richard	not quite sure but I think it would be like this , I'm not sure though
heather	ok, and this is northern and southern hemisphere?
richard	yeah
richard	//yeah
richard	yeah, I think so, because of the tilt away, like over here it would be colder
heather	but south america would be, say, right there
richard	right where, right here?
heather	yeah
richard	I think that its like straight, its farther away from the sun here. Its also tilted more, uh, yeah, I think that that would, here it would be colder I think right now if we were here and they were there, not sure though, and here it would probably be hotter...
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
heather	that's a hard question but yeah your pretty much, pretty close. Ok so I have another kind of similar question, um, so, besides seasons where you go generally you get temperature variation, theres also like climatic variation like general, so like alaska is generally colder than florida
richard	yeah
richard	why, I don't know, uh, bottom I think that there'd be a least amount, a smaller amount of sun, even in the winter time, because its like, or even in the summer time, because its farther away and its like tilted, and its always down
heather	whats down?
richard	well like if the sun were here, it be over here, it'd be down while the rest of the country
heather	could you draw it? You know I was gonna ask you
richard	yeah
heather	that would be great
heather	so is this the sun?
richard	yeah
heather	ok and these are like rays of light or whatever, ok im sorry its so small im trying to look at it to see what you drew
richard	that's the sun, this is like a cross section kind of
heather	ok, and this is the earth right?
richard	yeah
heather	and you said, so, where would ok so wheres florida and alaska
richard	like here it'd be florida or something and this would be alaska
heather	uh hu
richard	and I think that the rays would more directly hit near this because its on the equator here and then this part would , this rays wouldnt hit it straight on or anything like that
heather	uh hu, ok
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
