<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>robbie</PNAME>
<INAME>bruce</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>side</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
bruce	The first thing I want to know is why is it warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
robbie	Because the Earth, when you're in the wintertime, the Earth is facing, the Earth that we're on, the side of the Earth we're on is rotated, so it's not facing the sun, the sun is on the other side-
bruce	This is, is the winter you said?
robbie	Yeah, like the winter, we're, we don't, we're, the sun is shining down onto the other side of the planet more and we're on the other side, and as the days go by, the Earth turns, so then we're, the sun is coming down, we're closer to the sun than we were before, by like, just a little bit and where the Earth is rotated on its axis and now we're facing instead of kind of being away from it, and you can still see the sunlight and still see the sun, but the light doesn't get there are far as quickly,  and so in the summer it- not as quickly, but in the summer the sunlight is, um, the sunlight is coming on to us, the sunlight is coming on and the warmth is more because we're facing the sun and we're facing the sun this time, we're not as the Earth turns  there's the dark side and the light side pretty much.  That's why the days are shorter, the days are shorter in umm, winter.  Cause the Earth is turning, and then, and um you see - on it's axis and it's spinning and just kind of turning so we're in the northern hemisphere and so when it turns down so the Northern Hemisphere is closer to the sun then it's summer, then when the northern hemisphere is farther away from the sun, it's winter 
bruce	 Okay.
robbie	 Heh.
robbie	 Yeah, it's kind of a bad explanation.
bruce	I don't think so, it's just hard to talk about these things just in words, so why don't we do a picture?
robbie	 Okay.  .  This is the sun.   And this is the Earth .  And there's the equator and this is the northern hemisphere and this is the southern hemisphere .  We're in the northern hemisphere.  So as the Earth goes on its orbit, it's turning.  And when it turns, when it turn- er, when it not, I'm sorry.  When the Earth goes all around its orbit, that's one year.
bruce	 mm hmm
robbie	 And it's umm, and it's also turning while it does this, on its axis
bruce	 mm hmm
bruce	 So here, the northern hemisphere is facing the sun, so it's summer [and here]
robbie	 [Yeah, right, but] it's colder, it's colder in the southern hemisphere at that time, right
bruce	I see.  Umm, okay, that makes sense.  How does this relate to the, to when it's day and night, though?
robbie	 Umm, well, the sun is more on the, the Earth is spinning  everyday, you know, the Earth goes around and spins once, but when the sun is facing the northern hemisphere more, the sunlight gets there, almost the same as the light bulb almost to where it has to illuminates and its kinda go- and like illuminate around  and so, you see the sun for longer in the northern hemisphere because you're kind of facing it and that's why the days are shorter, nights, days are longer and nights are shorter.
bruce	 I see.  So the sun, tell me if this is what you're saying.  That here's the southern hemisphere-
robbie	 Right
bruce	 And for the light, for the sunlight to get there, it kind of has to go around-
robbie	 Well, it doesn't really go around, I mean you still see it but I mean it just goes out and then they see it there, it's just that it gets here quicker and as you turn, as the Earth turns around, it goes, it gets there not as fast, for the northern hemisphere because it's becoming night, but then the southern hemisphere doesn't see it at all.
bruce	 Wait, the southern hemisphere doesn't see ?
robbie	 Well, at night.  I mean, the southern hemisphere, that's why the night is shorter because the sun is, the sun is, umm, the sun it's, I'm sorry, I'm bad at explaining this but the sun is not, it's not shining as much on, .  As you're facing the sun, you see it longer until you turn so you can't see it anymore.
bruce	 Okay.  I think I've mostly, I've mostly got it.  So wait, when this is turning, what makes it turn into night now?
robbie	 What do you mean by that?  Like it turns,  it turn, the Earth spins as it's going around its axis, uh, as it's going around its orbit.
bruce	 As it's going around here 
robbie	 Right.
bruce	  So but when it spins, eventually the north pole, the northern hemisphere gets around to there
robbie	 Right.
bruce	 But is that, doesn't that mean it's winter?
robbie	 No, it's spinning in a different way  I'm not sure how I should say that - it's spinning kind of like that around  and then as it goes it kind of starts spinning like that around, that around that around and it kind of gradually gets like that.
bruce	 Oh, I see.  And the spinning this way is what makes it day and night.
robbie	 Right.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
bruce	 Uh huh, okay.  Okay, I get it.  I get it...  Now here's a somewhat related question.  Umm, so we just talked about how it's, what makes it kind of change from summer to winter here in the northern hemisphere
robbie	 mm hmm
robbie	 Right.
bruce	 So I'm wondering, so that's my next question, is why is it warmer, I'm just going to take this sheet , why is it warmer in Florida and colder in Alaska.
robbie	 Because Florida is closer to the equator and the equator is always, the sun is pretty much always on the equator, like near the equator, cause like the equator is like both the dividing line between the southern hemisphere and the northern hemisphere
bruce	 mm hmm
robbie	 So even though if the sun is on the southern hemisphere it still stays on the equator and if it's on the northern hemisphere it's still, it still is on the equator too.  But if it goes, if it's all the way up in Alaska, Alaska, you know, if it's on the southern hemisphere, Alaska's far away.  But Florida is closer to the equator, not as far away, so it's warmer in Florida than in Alaska.
bruce	 Okay, I think I got that.  Can we just draw a picture to be sure?
robbie	 Sure
bruce	 I think that made sense 
robbie	  Okay, here's Alaska, whatever, and uh Florida's down here 
bruce	 uh huh
robbie	 There's the equator , wherever, it's lower, and northern hemisphere and southern hemisphere, and the sun  is say, shining on the southern hemisphere at the time
bruce	 mm hmm
robbie	 But it's still, when it shines on the southern hemisphere it's pretty much shining on the equator because the equator is the dividing line
bruce	 mm hmm
robbie	 And Florida is closer to the equator, so it's shining, the sun is closer, shining closer on Florida than it is on Alaska which is all the way up here,
bruce	 I see.  How about when it's shining on the northern hemisphere?
robbie	 Well, the northern hemisphere, it's shining on, um, you know it only goes up so far up to the tropic of Cancer
bruce	 uh huh, I see
bruce	 I see, I see.  How does - can you tie that to this picture?  So here it's shining on the northern hemisphere.
robbie	 Right.  And this is the equator, and then when it turns around on the southern hemisphere, the equator is still there.
bruce	 Right.  I mean where is it - right now, where is it shining on, is it shining on - is it shining...
robbie	 On the northern or southern
bruce	 It's shining on the northern hemisphere
robbie	 Right now, yeah
bruce	 But here you said- you were talking about it shining only at the topic of Capricorn 
robbie	 Oh yeah, hmm... Well it's probably, it's been, it probably has not, I mean, if this is as high as it gets, it's only been summer for like, June 23rd, June 21st, so it hasn't been summer for all that long so it starts, it goes to the equator, that's it's little starting point, it goes up here, and it goes back down to the tropic of cancer or whatever in the bottom of the southern hemisphere, and then it will come back up and do it again
bruce	 mm hmm
bruce	 mm hmm
bruce	 And what's, how does this relate to that  picture, so how, so here you talked about whether it's shining on the equator or shining on the tropic of whatever this is, Capricorn or Cancer , I don't remember which is which
robbie	  Neither do I.
bruce	 But where, at what point in this picture is this shining on the equator and when is it shining on the tropic of Capricorn?
robbie	 Alright, say this is, this is when summer begins, and this is when fall begins, and this is when winter begins, and when spring begins it's here  , so right now, it's right on the equator-
bruce	 I see 
bruce	 mm hmm
bruce	 So that makes total - I totally understand what you're saying, the only thing that slightly confuses me is that from the picture you drew, it sort of looks like the place the sunlight is hitting the most on is right here on the top.
robbie	 Yeah. It's just cause I'm a bad picture drawer, umm, I don't know, you could say like, say whatever is the northern and whatever is the southern, and the equator is like this and you could say this is the northern and this is the southern
bruce	 mm hmm
bruce	 I see, so it sort of moves back and forth
robbie	 Right, it will be like on the northern one here more and then it will go down, and then the southern will be facing and it will shine on the southern and then it will go here and then it will be equal and then it goes here and then its shining on the-
bruce	 So right here, it sort of points like this 
robbie	 Right, this would be like...
bruce	 And then, this would be summer you said. 
robbie	 This right here I think, yeah, yeah, that would be summer 
bruce	 and what happens, it sort of tilts  around like this
robbie	 Yeah, till it gets to...
bruce	 Does it sort of keep going around?  Is that the idea?
robbie	 Well, yeah, kind of.  It's harder with a picture.
bruce	 uh huh.
robbie	 When it's, when it's, at the beginning of fall and the beginning of spring, it's pretty much shining down the smack dab of the equator, and as it gets, no, I got kind of confused again, yeah, actually, yeah, that's right
bruce	 mm hmm, it's kind of hard to keep track of these things.
robbie	 Yeah, I know.  And as it gets to the beginning of summer, that's pretty much mostly northern exposure where it's pretty much shining all on the, well, not on all but like on the tropic of whatever and as it goes around, it will become fall, and it will, it will be shining on the equator again, and then it will go around and it will be winter and it will be pretty much this southern exposure.  And it comes around and it will be spring, and it will be on the same, it will be on the equator
bruce	 Okay.  Sounds good.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
