<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>vanessa</PNAME>
<INAME>betsy</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>cf</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
betsy	 I'm going to ask you about why you think it's warmer in the summer and colder in the winter.
vanessa	 Um, 'cause the Earth is closer to the sun during the summertime.
betsy	 Okay.
vanessa	 'Cause of the Earth's rotation around the sun , and at that point, it's closer.
betsy	 It's closer.  Okay, and that makes it...
vanessa	 Warmer.
betsy	 Warmer? Okay, why don't we draw a picture 
vanessa	   These are the XXX...And then during the summer it's probably like over here.
betsy	 Okay.
vanessa	 Like closer.
betsy	 Okay.  Can you show me, just so I make sure I remember, where the Earth might be in the summer and write "summer" next to it?  That's fine.
vanessa	 Okay.
betsy	 And this is winter?
vanessa	 Okay.  
betsy	 Okay.  I've heard some people say when it's winter in Chicago, it's summer in Australia.  Have you ever heard that?
vanessa	 Yeah.  But it's always summer in Australia.
betsy	 Is it?
vanessa	 Because it's always warm.
betsy	 Okay.  And umm, so when it's closer in the summer this is where the Earth is, okay, so when it's closer to the sun, it just gets more of the sun's...?
vanessa	 Yeah.  Sun's light.
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
betsy	 Okay.  Okay.  Okay, that's great.  Thanks.  Next question for this part is kind of similar.  Can you tell me why in general it's warmer in Florida and colder in Alaska?
vanessa	 Because in Florida, it's closer to the equator, and that's where the sun hits the Earth the most during the year
betsy	 Okay.
vanessa	 And what was the other one?
betsy	 Alaska.
vanessa	 Alaska, it's farther away from the equator.
betsy	 Okay.
vanessa	 And not as much sun hits there all the time.
betsy	 And that's really interesting to know what that might look like , the sun hitting the Earth.  So that would be great if you could draw-
vanessa	 Well, at least it's not warmer there.  Cause the sun hits Alaska.
betsy	 It hits Alaska...
vanessa	 More than everywhere else, like during...during....they get a lot of light.
betsy	 Alaska does?
vanessa	 
betsy	 Can you maybe draw me a picture of what that sun looks like, the sun's rays look like, maybe explaining why Florida's warmer than Alaska?
vanessa	 Okay. ...Oh, I can't draw this.
betsy	 That's fine, it doesn't have to be the perfect picture.  Just curious - general proximity.
vanessa	 Okay...  Forget the United States, this can just be Florida and Alaska.
betsy	 Okay.
vanessa	 It's like on an axis.
betsy	 What's on an axis?
vanessa	 The Earth.  This is wrong, but that's supposed to be the equator actually, should be up there.  It hits mostly this way, so Alaska doesn't get, like as much heat as Florida does.
betsy	 Okay, what hits like that?
vanessa	 hmm?
betsy	 Uh, which - I think you were talking about from the sun what hits...
vanessa	 Um, the sun, it hits everything in the rays
betsy	 Okay
vanessa	 But when the Earth rotates, it, some places don't get as much sun as others.
betsy	 And why doesn't Alaska get so much sun?
vanessa	 Cause like, it's in the northern hemisphere
betsy	 Okay
vanessa	 The northern hemisphere doesn't get that much light most of the time.
betsy	 Okay.  And do you know why it doesn't get as much light?
vanessa	 No.
betsy	 No?  In your picture you said the equator gets lots of sun most of the time.
vanessa	 That's because when the Earth rotates, like the equator is right there in the middle?
betsy	 So there in the middle it means it can...
vanessa	 It can get more light
betsy	 Okay.  So that's the equator and it's getting lots of light.  And this is Alaska and it's not getting a lot of light
vanessa	 Yeah
betsy	 So it's getting less light cause the sun's rays aren't hitting it?
vanessa	 Yeah, directly.
betsy	 Directly? Okay.  Great.  That's great.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
