<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>william</PNAME>
<INAME>herb</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>none</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
herb	 The first question I'd like to ask you is, why do you think it's warmer in the summertime and colder in the wintertime?
william	 Because I think the Earth is closer in the summer than winter.
herb	 Okay. Can you draw me a picture of what that might look like?
william	  Let's say this is the Earth...the sun...not exactly as this is
herb	 That's okay
william	 This is summer.  Winter.  
herb	 Okay.  So basically, in the summertime it's closer to the sun and in the wintertime its farther.
william	 Yeah.
herb	 So now have you ever heard that, for instance, when it's winter in Chicago, it's summer somewhere else?
william	 Yeah
william	 Like the opposite of the place that's Chicago.
herb	 uh huh.  Like what.  What place would that be? 
william	 China.
herb	 Okay.  How about maybe Australia?
william	 Okay.
herb	 Now if it's winter in Chicago and the Earth is far away, how can it be wint - how can it be summer in Australia?
william	 Because the sun, I think, that is the opposite I mean .  I think it is the sun is slanted, it makes
herb	 The sun is slanted?  What do you mean?
william	 They go slanted around the sun.
herb	 Okay.  Can you draw me a picture of that?  I'm just not sure exactly what you mean.
william	 I just think that, I'm not sure about it
herb	 uh huh
herb	 So you're saying the Earth is slanted?
william	 uh huh
herb	 So what is this line?
william	 The center of the Earth.  Orbit.  Orbitation.
herb	 Is this line/ What's right here on the Earth?
william	 North Pole.
herb	 And what's right there?
william	 Arctic.
herb	 Okay, so this is the North/South line?
william	 yeah.
herb	 And where is Chicago?  About, approximately?  You don't have to be exact.
william	 Somewhere around here.
herb	 Okay, do you want to put a point on it?
herb	 And where is Australia?
herb	 Okay, so have you drawn me a picture of winter or summer here?
william	 Kind of winter.
herb	 hmm?
william	 Winter.
william	 yeah.
herb	 Okay.  So does the Earth kind of spin on its own?  On its own axis?
william	 
herb	 So what does that do?  What does that cause?
william	 Causes summer, season.
herb	 Umm, okay.  What about, what about umm, what about night and day?
william	 It also causes, because the sun's shadow blocks the other side of the Earth.
herb	 uh huh.  So does the spinning of the Earth cause summer and winter and night and day also.
william	 yeah.
herb	 It does the same thing?  I mean it does both things?
william	 Yeah
herb	 Okay.  Can you draw me a picture of how the sun and Earth move together?  Or how the earth moves to the sun?  Does it move around?  Does it stay still?
william	 The sun always stay in here, in same place.   The sun moves around, and here moves, goes around.
herb	 Can you just draw that for me?
william	 And this goes around, goes one circle, moves a little bit.
herb	 Can you draw me a picture of the orbit?  What the orbit looks like?
william	  like that
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
herb	 ok, and how does/ excellent.  Okay, great.  Let me just ask you one other question about this.   What do you think is warmer?  Florida or Alaska?
william	 Florida.
herb	 Florida. Why?
william	 Because it's near the equator.
herb	 Okay, and what does that do?
william	 It's the center of the Earth.  It's where the sun's rays go the, the... Florida is near the equator because the sun's equator gets more sun's rays, the sun is direct shine on the earth equator so it bigs warm.  But Alaska is near the North pole something, so Florida is more warmer.
herb	 okay.  So it's warmer because the sun shines more on the equator than it does on other places.
william	 yeah.
herb	 okay.  Great.
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
