<TRANSCRIPT>
<PNAME>zelda</PNAME>
<INAME>heather</INAME>
<PREPOST>pre</PREPOST>
<TCODE>tilt</TCODE>
<BODY>
<SEASONS>
heather	what I want to ask you is about the season basically, so im sure since you're a little kid you always herad that the seasons change that it has to do with the earth and sun. and, why do you think, what is, could you tell me your best guess, why its warmer in the summer and colder in the winter?
zelda	because, I think because the earth is on a tilt, and then, like that side of the earth is tilting toward the sun, or its facing the sun or something so the sun shines more directly on that area, so its warmer.
heather	Can you draw a picture? It doesn't have to be artistic or anything
zelda	so that was the sun, and like the earth, if this is the top its like tilted so the sun shines on like the bottom part, its tilted back
heather	ok so put us, ok so this would be, say, draw winter and draw summer and draw the states, or whatever, yknow like, like a picture for winter and maybe another picture
zelda	This would be winter
zelda	and summer would be like this, like, and then, we would be like right here and you couldn't see it cause its like over like tilted that way
heather	ok , and this is the sun
zelda	yeah this is like the north pole
heather	ok, so could you write on there, this is winter? And summer, and you said that's the north pole? And that's the north pole, is that whart your saying? So you were saying that when its winter-or, when it summer we're getting more direct light from the sun, is that what you said?
zelda	(nods)
heather	and then, what happens in the winter time? It's the earth is
zelda	its like, its still tilted, you still get sunlight cause like during the day, but its not as much cause its shining like this and then the bottom part is getting more but some still goes up like over the top but it not as strong, so its not as warm, but you still get some light
heather	and why isnt it as strong?
zelda	because the um, United states  or whatever is tilted like away, so, its kinda hard to explain, its not like a three-D
</SEASONS>
<CLIMATE>
heather	Right, I know, K, um, so I have a slightly different question, so besides the seasons, y'know climate and temperature change during the seasons, we also have kind of general climate variation, for example yknow its generally cooler in alaska and florida is usually pretty hot. um, do you know why that is, could you maybe try and explanation as to why that would be?
zelda	I think because, um, alaska is really north and its closer to the north pole which doesn't really--it gets sunlight, but its like even if the earth is tilted to where its summer, it still doesn't get that much, and florida is closer to the equator which always gets sunlight year round, even when its tilted away because the center of the earth, so it always gets sun.
heather	ok, so um, your saying that uh, florida gets because its closer to the equator and the equator you said always gets sun all year round, it gets more direct light from the sun?
zelda	Mmm Hmm
zelda	It was closer to the north pole, and the north pole doesn't get, it gets hardly any sunlihght, just enough for light
heather	uh hu, and why does it not get as much sunlight?
zelda	because its at the top of the world and even when the world is tilting towrds whichever way its tilting its always at the top and so it doesn't go either way, it doesn't go far enough over to get enough sunlight for it to be warm
heather	could you draw a picture of what you mean? try to.
zelda	like if this was the earth and this was like the north pole, it doesn't tilt far enough (ok this is the sun) far enough over for it to be like equal to where the equator is just tilts back and forth like a little bit
heather	ok do you wanna lable the parts for me, thanks
</CLIMATE>
</BODY>
</TRANSCRIPT>
